<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-basketball/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1893-04-01/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Basket+Ball+Game+Indoor+Sport&r=-0.179,-0.372,1.359,1.768,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NOW FOR A NEW GAME
Baticing Baae Ball inCaml In
stitute Gyuasuiuu.
A GAME ALL CAN PLAY.
N INDOOR BPORT
which is new to this
city has bees iatre
duced by Mr. MauaI
A. Joyce, the athletic
instructor at the Car
roll Istitute. The
game has met with
great popularity is
other places where it
has been played, and
from the interest which
it hnt excited among
the members of the
Carroll Institute is bids fair to asset with the
Succes here that it bas in other cities. Almost
owery might basket bell is played in the gym
anshetts the institute, and the sport is not only
Smithy and invigerating, but exciting and full
ot interest.
Bushet ball wva Arst started about a year ago
ad ree that time it hes spread throughout
Se esuntry esecially in the gymnasiums of
he yong Men a Christian asociatioss. It is
paticularly adaptable to business men. as little
narmarx A. Joyce.
se metpractice is required to learn it and there
6, no incident roughness if the rules are
stictly adhered to. It is the intention of Mr.
deyce is try to have other teams formed in the
symmasisme in the city and to have regular
entestn between them. It eomameade itself in
s it can be played in almost any sized room
den any had of lot. whether it be large or
mail, and that the number of player. need
only be limt. I b the size of the ground. It
bkings into play all maseles of the body. thus
being a healthy exercise, and at the same time
te a ws incidens to moet sports are want
1. The only apparatus neessary for the
oe to be played is a regular Rugby foot ball
mnd re half-bushel baskets.
movwr rT PL 6TD.
Theegh she courtesy of Mr. Joyce a Stan
aoprter witnessed a game of basket ball played
M the Carrer Institute on one of the evenings
of this week. The two baskets are attached to
th =anig strack at the opposite ends of the
gymmsam and U.s object of the game is to
Shen e heU in the opponent'e basket. The
uame consist of mine men each. made up of a
gaiheeper. two backs to assist him. a center, a
eight and left henter, two forward and a home
ma. They are arranged in this order from
Oe gnal whica they are defending. It is not
asessmry that the players thou!d remain in
teir glaces. but they should move in such a
way as to gie the forward player an oppo:
baesy Is gee a good tos at the goal or the
baecks to keep theer opponents from obtaining
so mmm by taking it from thea when they are
ghbntsto throw. It is the luty of the goal
ba~to beep the ball away fromi the vicinity.
etgoal. end it is more often neessary for
hi to bat the bail with his had tha for
e~er meambers of the seama to do so.
L. Serim. 3. leeward
4.ame.. eae...
4. Sm. .a.5
en.. ...s-....e.
The game is started by the teems lining up
ba their respseutve positions and then the
safeae tomes the ballian the air, It must not be
te.-d antal it strikes the ground. Thea the
players ean catch it. and the object of the one
who obtains it isto pass istso one of the players
ahis own sidec.who either passes itto inotherwho
msay be in a favorable position to tom f~ar goal
or else attempts to auake a goal himself. To
bee a foot bal into a basket euasiended ten feet
a cen SsA.av
beG airani eiasest lags en~t. held it.ie
net en eas messean means, end thee.
thanmy ethe at guat are madebut
as t ase -s eemtl, and e sensty
ohB~in meds. esnammty, an the
qshad esty. The haDeam be aoma
an ists with -n or beth --a-~
In bM the sesm s e 40 -a -e
e be h ss:
asmmmS he es h the det er hased
A e esms e with te hasb mUs
am thmm... ..a. a. he
Gotas o ben shile rmaI and Mas to stop
The har maw be held in ds baud The arms
Iee or bod soat not be used for blding it.
If h lb is beld for any length of time th
referee tess it into the air. as in the baegtnmg
of theam
o the5 ein, holding, J~n .trp, n
or striking b allowed. The t iafringem m
'f this rule eosnts a foal and a second dis
q"mli= a player, but, as in foot ball, a substi
tats may take his place.
IN TaN BAsKET. C
When a ball goes out of bounds it is put in
play in the same way as in a foot ball game.
The game consists of two halft of twenty
minutes each or such time as the captains may
decide on. and time is taken out for delays.
A goal counts three points and a foul one
point for the opponent. and a majority of the
points decides the game.
There are a referee and umpire, whose duties
are the same respectively as the same officials
in a foot ball game.
Any player has a right to get the ball at any
time while it is in the field of play. provided
that he handles only the ball and not the op
ponent.
ADVANTAGEs OF THE GAME.
To an observer the game seemed to be one
that will solve the problem, which has been a
knotty one for some time, of introdncing a
game which will meet the excitement incident
to most outdoor sports and at the same time
be suitable for indoor play. At present when
the outdoor season closes most of the athletes
drop tbe sports in which they have been in
terested and the benefits thev derived from
them are lost. This game is one that requires
skill and agility. but strength is not one of the
necessary factors. and, consequently. men of
all physical conditions can take part in it. It
has also been found to have been a useful
sport for girls and women, as it is especially
APTEn THE FALL.
adapted to securing good health without having
the nervous strain caused by some of the
sports now indulged in.
In its principli. it is a combination of foot
ball and lacrosse. It resembles foot ball in
most of the rulings, but in the method to be
pursued to obtain a goal the game more closely
resembles lacrosse. Although at first glance it
would hardly seem possible to have any amount
of team play in the game, still it is only by the
concerted action that a team can play to the
beet advantage. A novice in the game inva
riably feels disposed when he obtains the ball
to make a shot for the goal, which could not be
made from any distance one time in a hundred,
as in order that the ball should remain in the
basket it has to be skillfully and easily tossed,
not thrown. A good player will. when he has
the ball, quickly look for one of his own team
who is in an uncovered position to whom he
can tos it. In this way a well-drilled team
could almost entirely keep the ball from the
hands of a team made up of new men. Quick
ness of eye, hand and foot is one of the first
requisites for a good player, and he also must
keep his head about him. A moment's hesita
tion or a wrong pass may give considerable
advantage to the other side.
If an umpire is chosen who strictly follows
the rules of the game there is little chance for
any roughness, as running with the ball is
prohibited, and thus the injuries coming from
sharp tackling in foot bal are done away with.
The attention of the player is fastened on the
ball and personal feeling in the matter is lost
sight of. The object of each player when one
of his side obtains the ball is to place himself
in an uncovered position so that one of his own
team can pays it to him, while the opponents
should in this eae stick closely to the men
with whom they are paired so that a pass to
them would gave an equal opportunity for each
to catch the ball. It is in this respect that
cool-beadedt.euand quickness count. Idi
vidlual play on the part of one man will destroy
all the good work that the rest of the team may
do. If the game in played indoors in a gym
naisium the passee should be more of a toes
rather than hard straight throw.
As the game has apparently obtained a good
foothold in this city and as it is a healthful and
at the same times exciting sport it is to be
hoped that the efforts of Mr. Joyce to make the
game a popular one in this city will meet with
success, Some of the men under him are bo
conming quite proficient and before long he will
have a iirst-class team,</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014635/1893-04-21/ed-1/?dl=page&q=basket+ball+basketball+game+sport&sp=6&st=text&r=-0.268,-0.077,1.536,1.536,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>FOE MEN AND WOMEN.
Basket Ball as Playod in Y. M. O.
A. Gymnasiums.
Mj
ClifcliertcyE"i,j-,h EVrsetraM ?m&
JK. MIS
sure, 2l-v' litl. Unl5t, n-I M
k -UfisS&iJsiv ""Pl?
ft
t&Wj
7"s "TwVi
A f
ftUVJtoir tfifiT-I b tuu t.l3 j Tnl?) VSy
ChnA!lpr. Jff a 6ienntt ft iir- v
!(jaudnlr..J fit AtD'ss'ti ..t.ri'S-.
"ltr-Ucr for I cUf" Sr vi fr -ctrir
Vnll. 1U.1MK. r-ia Hmtr 1 f
mw,t iipi-'in".' tt BcsraKi
THOMAS F. BAYARD.
STb Xtoiiorab'-a Career' at Onr 2Vew Am
lMador to J Cngantf.
Thomas Francis J 'ayard, the new
Bmbassaaicrto the con rt of. St. Jamets
-cvas borchi Wibninglton, Del., in 1S2S.
Ecrras fitttidfor a m:rca;atiIo life-ami
f-
IF
II OX. TnOMAS T. BATAHD.
placed in a businessliause in Xew York
.Hty. He returned to "Wilmington in
1S48, studied In vr, and -was admitted to
tho bar in 18rl. He was appointed
United -States -district attorney for Del
aware, but resigned tin- following yer.
"n 18'r he reciox d to Philadelphia,
-ivheiehe becamo the partner of Vil
liam bliippeu. He returned tolVilraing--son
and succeeded Ins father to the
.United State.- senate in 1S08. ITe was
reelected in lc7o and again jn ISl. ?k.
Cleveland appointed him scrctarj' of
Atate iu 1SS5. On tho day -on which he
was olecU-d to the serrate for a full
term his father was also reelected a
A Knme for lloth Sexe It Is Something
Like 1'i.otball, I'.ut Has No Hough
features and J 5 Full
or Fun.
For a long1 time gymnasium instruc
tors were confronted by the necessity
for a game which could be played in
doors by old and young, male and fe
male. They wanted a game devoid of
lough features, yet one which should
be thoroughly scientific, and which
should atford plenty of opportunity for
good healthy exercise for the scholar
or business man, and training for the
athlete, feuch possibilities, says the
New York Sun. have been discovered in
the game of basket ball, which has be
come so popular in Fchool and club
fjjnnnasiums throughout thp country.
The (fame was first introduced by the
directors and pupils of the Y. M. C. A.
fill
tSOAI.3.
training school at Springfield, Macs.
Its advantages were t,oon perceived,
and the sport, spread to the gymnasiums
controlled by the Young Men's Chris
tian association, and was further in
troduced in scholastic institutions and
club gymnasiums. At the training school
Ihc g.iuic was developed, and a strong
team was drilled in the simple work
ings of it by James Naismlth, one o the
Springfield instructors, and an earnest
worker in i be Held of all-around sport
and recreation. In New York and
senator lVoui Delii ware to-servo for tha IJrooklyn.are sereral good teams, and
unexpired fl of his original term. H1 P'V "lt; a ir"IU w' l-l"ie-
This is the only case cf a father and The game can readily be played in al-
-sonLeing voted for by tho same icgis- ost the smallest gymnasium. As the
lature to fill the senatorial office. In sizeb of tht! exercising rooms vary, the
vpnate he served on tho committees sjauie purycu uy cuii iwiu ia suKuiy
on finance, judiciary, prh'atc land
rlaims, libiary and revision ofDaws. In
1SS1 ho was elecrcd president pro tem
nore of the senate. He was a.candi-
different. All th match games axe
played under regular rules, however,
-andth" peculiar disad vantage which a
"gym" may have for the visiting team, is
idate for president in ISSO and 1S54. In- remecieil so Xar as possible. Hie game
Wudinghigrest-rraiidfather, Gov. Has-, can be played out of doors on a large
Ptt. h i the fifth member of his fam- umuiibwcu an i .11 Syw
r 1 i. iin?iim. rrin r
piy wni) nave oecnpicu seats 111 11191
jUnitfldita,tes senate,
WHEELMEN'S PRIZE CUP.
r9 Be Competed Vov at tho Gr(At Kce
j The League of Ameiiean TVlieclmen
iJUavo been presented with a very hand
jsomo -trophy to baxrapcted for in their
;Sntcrna,tannal jaco meet, to bo held at
idiica'o next? Augnst, Il&nry Ij. Sal- j
fojistall, a. memUT of the Elizabeth A.
jfff Wheelmen, is the donor of the prize.
jit is a sterling bilvcr cup, gold lined,
itod stands twenty-eigBt inches high ou Jl". "v
The goals pictured in this col
umn arc iised, the upright one for the
field, on wliich it can be placed at any
point, and the other for Indoor play.
The latter is attached to the gallery or
the wall of the room. The string is
used to turn the goal so that tho ball
may readily be regained. These goals
are the improved article The first
goals, from which the game got its
name, were only peach baskets nailed
to tho wall or running tiack.
The game can be played by a number
of men at once. In a small jrvmnasium.
howover, flvo aside is the most con-!
In larger rooms nine
men can piay on a biae. Lnis is con
sidered the regular, number, and they
are placed a -hown in the accompany
ing illustration. Tho game itself is
strictly one of passing the ball fiom
man to man. It can neither be kicked
nor batted with the fist. The object is
to get the ball into the basket or goal.
A large person is useful, but one of the
best players it tho Twenty-third
htreet Y. Jf. C. A. gymnasium is
a little hap not much oTer
GOAL,
KOMT
iTjsagvtfROi.
imitTPimimmmm,POSEMOXS OF TITE FLAYTJIS.
four feet tail. To get an un
covered position is of the utmost im
portance, as the player can thus easily
get the ball and as easily pass it to one
of his side near the goal. It requires a
great deal of practice to put the ball in
the goal, wliich is placed at some dis
tance above the players' heads. 2Cbt
alone must a pla-or be bkillful, he
must also be very lively. A player
must thiow the ball from the spot
w here ho catches it, but ho can turn
around to throw it. 2vo interference is
allowed, and tackling and pushing are
strictly prohibited. A player may only
obstruct the passage of the bail after it
is thrown.
When the game is played 011 a field
the player may run with the ball if he
continually throws it above his head
and cr.tcho it again. The ball may
also be diibbled along the ground with
the hand.
Tt-.di play counts for everything in
basket play. Tlie t.wo forwards and
the home man should always work to
gether to get the ball into the goal.
The backs guard the goal, and the cen
ter men are supposed to get the ball
and pass it forward toward the home
man.
The game is usually played in two
halves of fifteon minutes each, with a
slight intermission. When a goal is
made the same goes right on. It is
perhaps the fastes' game played to
day, and is played with a snap "which
football player in lining up may well
.RUSSIA</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86088296/1893-06-01/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Game+Sport+Indoor&st=text&r=-0.322,-0.118,1.643,1.643,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE GAME OF BASKET BALL.
Interesting and Exciting Sport For Thos
Not Able to Exercise Kegularly.
The unnounceinent that at a woman's
educational institution not far from this
city tho students played a close and ex
citing game of "basket ball" wasperhaia
the first item which attracted public at
tention to a sport that is rapidly becom
ing very popular in this country among
those who have neither the physique nor
the taste for baseball or football. The
rules of the new sport are comparatively
simple, and the ease with which the
fundamental laws of the game can be
acquired in a few minutes' practice have
served to make it popular wherever it
has been introduced, while its freedom
from much of the roughness and intri
cacy of football has also tended to make
the devotees of basket ball enthusiastic
in their praise of its merits.
The name "basket ball" is derived from
the fact that scores are made not by car
rying the ball across the goal lines or
kicking it over the goal bar as in foot
ball, but by throwing the spheroid into I
a moderately small basket, which is hung
about 10 feet above the ground or floor.
To accomplish Buch a feat usually re
quires much practice, and as a rule tho
try at goals are far more numerous than
tho scores. Either hand or both hands
can be used in holding the ball, and it
must either he thrown or be batted with
tho open hand a punch with the fist or
arm, or a kick, constituting a foul.
The game differs from football also in
tho fact that no player is allowed to run
with the ball, but must stand where it is
caught, and a fair catch can be made
only with the hands. If the ball is held
for an unnecessarily long time, the um
pire takes possession of it and puts it
"ia play" by throwing it in the air, no
player being allowed to touch it in such
an event until it has struck the ground.
If a ball goes out of bounds, it is put in
play as in football, and no player is "off
sido," but every player has the right to
touch the ball anywhere or everywhere
in the game, provided the ball is in play.
No pushing, tripping, 6hoving or tac
kling is allowed, and every such offense
constitutes a foul, which gives one point
to the opposing nine. As a goal counts
but threo points and a foul one. there is
every incentive to avoid rough play. The
players advance the ball by tossing it to
some member of their own nine, and
there is the best opportunity for success
in personal skill combined with good
team play. The "forwards" and "cen
ters" usually toss the ball forward, but
when it gets dangerously near his own
goal, the goalkeeper often bats it with
tho open palm.
Ono advantago which basket ball has
over many other forms of popular sport
lies in tho fact that, while it allows 18
players to participate, it can be pursued
tho year round in tho open air during
tho warmer months and in the gymna
sium whilo cold weather prevails. Again,
basket ball can be played by persons
whose physique is not of tho most robust
type, although many athletes also have
found, in it a healthful form of exercise.
It has pypved of great value In furnish
ing exercise for business men, women
and children, as wpll as brawny students,
and from the general success it has al
ready attained wherever it has been in
troduced there is every probability that
basket ball will soon become a very popu
lar and widespread form of outdoor and
indoor sport. Boston Advertiser.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058130/1894-11-25/ed-1/?sp=13&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Sport+Game+Indoor+Outdoor&st=text&r=-0.282,-0.078,1.564,1.564,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BASKET BALL
JTHAMChGIVIXO GAlE 31ETWEEX
oPlioUORES AXD IRESllJIE
3 Iopular and Graceful Game bat
Has Foiinil Great Favor AnioiiK
Girls Some of the Rules nUll HeK
iilations Observed in PlajinK1 It
Basket ball is to tie womens col
lege what football is to the mens
The Bryn Mawr girls are particu
larly enthusiastic over this sport and
the Smith college students are in train
ing for a match game some day
Thanksgiving week
A picked nine from the sophomore
class will be pitted against a picked
nine from the freshmen class The
Smith college girl is immensely inter I
ested in basket ball which she also
calls cradle ball
1
I j
I
r
r
j
1DiUikct For IIKIOOM
Daslcct Vac Outdoor
L At Bryn Mar the students are
equally as devoted to this game in
deed their interebt in it is tremendous
and vies with 5 oclock teas and the
atricals in mitigating the ennui l of var
sity life The freshman and sopho
more classes are particularly alive to
this sport Miss Elsa Bowman is the
captain or the sophomores nine while
Miss Corlnne Putnam is the leader of
the freshman
WHY THE GAME IS POPULAR
The beauty of tne gameor one of I
I its beauties for it has manyis that II
it can be played by any number and
the more he merrier it is usually i
J
J voted The ideal number however is
nine on each side There is a goal I
keeper two backs to assist a center
a right and left center two forwards I
and a home man I e a woman in this
c1 TJ y
Tire accompanying diagram shows
the positions of the players
The end and aim of the game is to
toss a ball which is the size of a small
football into one of the two large bas
kets suspended at each end of the field
The winning side is the one that lands
the ball in the opponents basket The
basket is placed about ten feet high
When the game is played in the
gymnasium the basket Is bracketed to
tb side of the wall For outdoor use
it is supported at the same height by
au upright post The price of the bas
Jets or goals is 15 per pair for in 1
door use when supplied with a pipe
or post for outdoors the cost is some
what more The balls which are cov
ered with Jeather and about twenty
A four inches in circumference cost
about 3 each a rubbercoated ball
J can be purchased for 115 1
Basket ball can be played in a gym I
nasium in a large room or a small
b 1 HeW 01 a large field if in the latter I I
as many as thirty or fifty players may I
take part I
APPROPRIATED BY WOMEN I
The man who originated the game j
01 invented it or whatever the proper
word may be did not intend it merely
for amusement his idea was to pro i
vide a good allaround physical exer
cise and as such it cannot be im
P oyed upon combining as it does run
ning jumping bending pnd twisting
nearly every muscle and joint in the
body is brought into exercise
Mr James Naismith of Springfield i
Mass originated basket ball about
I
three years ago As soon as it became
known among the gymnasiums it
spread like an fclHdenfie Primarily
intended for young men for whom
most of the good things of life are in
tended it was soon taken up by young
women who declared that If there
was anything good in the game they
would like io become acquainted with
itThe
The girl forthwith bought a book of
rules which they masteredin very
brief order donned their gymnasium
ostumes and began playing at once
The fine points of the game however
Were only acquired by practice
I RULES OBSERVED
j The three players ivho are designat
ilL ed as forwards occupy the third of
the ground nearest the opponents
pwal the centers occupy the middle
third and the backs the defensive
third of the ground The forwards
of one team stand near the backs of
the other
Out of doors with plenty of room
the field may be 150 feet long the goal
lines running through the baskets per
pendicular to the length of the field i
the side boundaries 100 feet apart
The ball is put in play IJ by the icferee 1
throwing it up in the middle of the
field this is done at the commence
ment of the game at the beginning of
the second half after each goal and J
when a foul has been made The time
of play is two halves of twenty min I
utes each I
A goal is made when the ball is I
Yf thrown or batted from the ground into
the basket provided it stays in It is
a foul if the ball Is struck with the
I fijts or kicked
The ball must be held by the hands
fl
0
i
the arms or body may not be used for
I holding it
No pushing tripping shouldering or
striking is allowed infringements of
this rule count as a foul
The score is counted by points A
goal counts three points a foul one
point for the opponents A majority of
points decides the game
DIANA CROSSWAYS
r
tUT
o
LrORWARD hOMERFORWARb
i a
7 7 7 u j
z 1s t x f
lC TER S CENTE I1 R CENTR
I
bJ
bJu
S
S S
V
LBAClf GO1l8EtPtR RBACK
CO
BASKET p</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84023253/1895-01-25/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Basketball+Basket+Ball+Game+Games+Sport+Baskets</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The basket ball game next Satur
day evening is arousing a great deal
of interest and as the two teams are
quite evenly matched the outcome is
awaited with interest. It is prob
able that this game will decide who
will play in the team which is to re
present the Association, and this
itself will spur everyone on to do his
best.BASKET BALL.
Those who were interested in the
basket ball games played last winter
will be pleased to learn that the town
and school boys are tohaveonemore
battle for the supremacy. A word
about the game which has become so
popular in the past few years will
be interesting to those who enjoy
good honest sport.
Basket ball was invented in 1889 by
ames Nuismith, teacher in the interna
tional training school, Springfield. Dur
ing its first season it wasnot particularly
popular hut has gained in favor and may
now be called quite as important sport in
the Y. M. C. A. world as football and
baseball, but it is essentially an indoor
game and the interest that is excited in
an exercise confined to the gymnasium
can perhaps never equal the zest which is
thrown into a game like football, played
under the blue of heaven, in the fresh out
door atmosphere and sun's rays that seem
to penetrate the muscles ot the athlete
and impart added vivacity. However,
at the season when football bruises have
long ago healed and conquests on the
gridiron are matters for rumination, he
who sighs for the pigskin can find much
satisfaction in basket ball, it possessing
all the elements of football but, if rules
are enforced, lacking the excessive rough
ness. The ball used is perlcctly round,
made of a rubber bladder, covered with
leather and is about a foot in diameter.
Briefly outlined the game according to
official rules for 1805, is played as follows:
baskets especially constructed tor the
purpose, are placed in a vertical position
with the mouth ten feetlrom the ground,
one at each end of the field (gymnasium),
occupying much the same position in re
lation to the players as do football goals.
i ne competitive teams tane positions on
the field as in football, save that there is
no line-up, The teams are composed of
five men when the playing space is less
than 1800 square feet, seven when it is
more than 1800 and less than 3600 and
nine men when over 3600. The referee,
with a player from each side, takes posi
tion in the center. He puts the ball in
play by throwing it up. Which side has
first ball depends on which center man
secures it. The ball is not kicked or
struck with the fists but thrown or batted
with the flat of the hand and the object
is, to get it into the basket, doing which
scores a goal. On the number of goals
secured depends the victory. The net
work of rules which govern the action of
the game is quite as elaborate as football
and will not be given here. Suffice it to
say that spectators easily comprehend
its action. The putting of a ball into the
basket may seem a veryeasv thing to do
but as a matter of fact it is very difficult
to acomplish with the floor empty and,
of course, much more so when two teams
are at strife. One of the rules says that
the ball shall always be kept in motion.
Two twenty-minute halves are played
with a rest of ten minutes between "the
halves. This is the time of actual play.
Each side has itscaptain while position
is the same as in baseball. The referee is
judge of the ball. He is the superior offi
cer ot the game and decides all questions
uul ucuimciy lulling on me umpire, i lie
umpire is judge of the men, calls all fouls,
notifies the offenders and has power to
disqualify men.
The game which was to be played
on Thursdayevening of this week has
been postponed until Saturday even
ing. The two teams have been prac
tising faithfully and will be able to
play a very interesting game. It is
hoped that the public will turn out
and encourage the gymnasts, as all
the proceeds over and above the ex
penses are to go towards much need
ed new apparatus for thegymnasium.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1895-11-26/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Play+Games+Game+Foot+Sport&st=text&r=-0.249,-0.075,1.499,1.499,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The game of basket ball played last
evening ln the rifle gallery of the National
Guard between the teams of the Y. M. C.
A. and the Cycle Corps was one of the
cleanest, hardest-fought games that has
been played in the series. Although the
Cycle Corps came out victorious by a score
of to 1, they had to work with all their
energies to attain that end, and several
times It looked squally for them.
It has been claimed by several persons
Interested In the game of basket ball that
the contests were degenerating Into wres
tling matches and slugging bouts, with a
little foot ball thrown in, but last evening's
game demonstrated that basket ball can be
played as lt should be. if the players will
only conform to the rules. A number of
persons were present to witness the games,
and frequently applauded the good plays
made.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1896-04-02/ed-1/?sp=13&q=Co-eds+Basket+Ball+Match+Basketball+Basket-ball+Teams+Team&st=text&r=0.316,0.161,0.718,0.934,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>CO-EDS AT BASKET BALL
Secret Practice at Berkeley for
the Great Match on
Saturday.
Greek Letter Fraternities to Present
Plays Paul Revere Lodge
Was Honored.
BERKELEY, Cal., April I.— The Berke
ley Co-ed basket-ball team are ready for
their battle with the Stanford nine next
I Saturday. They have gone into secret
practice and are devoting their time and i
i attention to signal work and to giving
their muscles the hnal course of ex
ercise before they stand up against
the wearers of the cardinal. They
are ail on the gui vive, as are
j the other women athletes of the
i university, for the contest on Saturday
will be t*e first contest they have entered
for honors. "We have the reputation and
the athletic prestige of the university to
uphold," said one of the fairest members
of the team to-day, "and we are going into
1 the struggle with* the purpose of coming
i out victors. We realize the odds we will
have to contend against in not being in as
I good training as we might, and then the
Stanford girls are much more experienced
than we. At any rate we will do our best,
J since we have accepted Stanford's chal
i lenge."
Two or three of the young women have
the appearance of being overtrained,
judging from their pallid faces and worn
expression. This may be due, however, to
anxiety over the result of the came. Tlieir
new costumes consist of white sweaters
and blue bloomers with gold trimmings.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063615/1898-12-18/ed-1/?sp=18&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Game+K+U+Naismith+Sport+Team</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BASKET BALL AT I U.
XKW BAJIE I.. CHKlT FA VII IX IX TUB
CLASSIC SHADES OF LA1VIIEACU.
How It I Plajeil The Tennis That
Ilnie Hern Formed The Fncnlty
Eiijoj- Ihe Game Clinncellur
Snow a. Crack Plnjer.
LAWRENCE. KAS.. Dec. 17.-(SpeciaU
The basket ball "fever" has broken out
In Its most violent form among Kansas
university people. Dr. Naismith. the new
physical director, brought the germs with
him, and that they were healthy specimens
is evidenced by their activity.
At first only a few of the students siw
in basket ball the diversion. But the dis
ease spread rapidly. Not only doe- eai h
class already possess its basket ball team,
but the literary and the scientific men of
the faculty are backing their "crack fives.
Eve-ry evening the gymnasium is filled with
a scrambling mass of humanity, and the
spectators who can recognlz. a friend or
acquaintance In the melee must be gifterd
with second sight.
Five men compose a team at basket ball.
The floor Is divided into three parts. Tho
center men of the plaving teams oe-upy a
space chalked off in the middle, am, the
other four dispose themselves In various
graceful attitudes in the end sections. The
referee tosses up the ball just above the
heads of the centers, who are standing
face to face. Each makes a jump and en
deavors to hit the hall, knocking it over
to his own men and toward his goal. Then,
the scramble begins. The accomplished,
and gentlemanly contortionist in the pat
ent medicine show could not rival basket
ball players In the way of tying French
knots in their corporal systems. The ma.-s
of writhing humanity turns over and over
in kaleidoscopic fashion, suddenly un
winds itself and is again resolved Into
parts. A man goes diving after the ball
and comos triumphantly up out of the
fray with his arms full of another man's
head! The aim In playing basket ball, so
it Is claimed. Is to throw the ball Into tho
round baskets, suspended at each end ot
the field, a greater number of times than
the opposing players. In reality, however,
it would seem that the cherls-hed object of
each plajer was to make as large and
choice collection of hruises as possible.
But that is basket ball from the specta
tor's point of view. To the players It Is
an all absorbing sport. Some of them
even have the audacity to assert that It Isi
a "gentle game, don't you know." Gentle,
indeed! One might as appropriately speak
of a bucking broncho as "well-mannered."
When the field Is not divided into sec
tions the game is reallr rough, but If thi
chalk lines are drawn, and fouls are faith
fully called whenever a man over-teps.
his boundaries, the bruise hunter adds to
Ills collection more slowly. It Is amusing:
to watch the players trying to remember
to have the proper respect for the bound
aries. Indeed It is truly pathetic to sej
what limitations of power a simple chalk
line can put on thee great, strong athletes.
In actual agony they har.g over the edge
and reach out helpless, longing arms to
ward the ball. Now and then an unruly
foot goes across the line, and then the
sharp whistle of the referee Is heard. A
foul entitles the players ort the otht.r side
a chance at throwing goal.
The game consists of two halves of
twenty minutes each. A twenty minute
rest is given between, and a new- team
put on to utilize the rest time. Each time
the ball goes Into the basket two points
are scored for the side whose goal Is
thrown As In baseball, a small score
Indicates a good game.
The Inventor of Ilnsket Hnll.
Dr. James Naismith Is the inventor of
basket ball. Unlike most of our games It
Is not the development of some medieval
sport. It was worked out on scientific
principles to meet a long felt want. Dr.
Naismith was physical director of a Y.
31. C. A. training school at Springfield.
Mass.. where the problem of supplying thlsj
need was brought to him for solution.
Busket ball was the result. It was In the
winter of 9I-52 that the game was intro
duced. The rules were made out and hung
In the "gym" fdr the inspection of playerj
before the game was ever tried. The men
were a little skeptical "at first about it.
but after the; ball was once thrown up no
coaxing was needed to Induce them to
Play. Basket ball came Into general favor
first through the Y. M. C. A. Having been
Introduced through the association it was
natural that it should spread through that
medium. Before long, however, colleges be
gan to investigate and adopt the game, ami
In the short .-pace of seven yeirs It has
gaimd a wide iopuhirlty. In the Eastern
colleges, both for men anil for womn.
basket ball Is the reigning favorite among
sports. The rules are not changed for tho
young women players, though doubtless the
game is played with a bit more tenderness.
Though at first sight the game appears
to be a free for all scramble. It soon be
comes evident that a number of sclentiilr?
,1'laya are iossibIe. Unfailing good judg
ment, anu goon muscular control are the
first requisites for a good player. The treat
ment of the ball Is the subject of several
rules. It can be tossed, rolled on Ihe floor
and pushed around, but must never In
kicked. There are no signals, and a play
lasts until the ball Is passed Into the basket.
Tennis In the 1'iilverslt jr.
The Kansas university men are going to
be great basket ball enthusiasts. Each
class has a picked team, and places on thei
teams are as much sought as on the var
sity eleven. Among faculty members thero
are two teams the Snow hall and tho
Frazer hall, representing the scientists and
the literary men. On the former team
Dr. WHHston. Marshall Barber. Clarenco
McClung. A. H. Clark and Dr. Naismith
hold positions. Their opponents are A.
G. Cantield. AY. H. Carruth. E. M. Hop
kins. M. W. Sterling and Archie Hogg.
On Tuesdays and Thursdays at 3 p. m. thesj
distinguished individuals lay aside their
dignity and their collars, don sweaters anil
pugilistic airs, and come forth into the
arena to dw battle. With a grace that
is acciuired only through long years of
bending over desks and laboratory tables,
they scamiier now here, now there, after
the elusive canvas sphere.
When the faculty teams met for their
last practice. Chancellor Snow- appeared.
He was Immediately besieged to play. The
chancellor protested that he was too green,
but such fetching invitations could never
be turned dotvn. The head of the universi
ty disappeared Into a dressing room, and
In a few moments, he emerged In a cos
tume of which the most noticeable feat
ures were- white canvas shoes, a seraphic:
grin, and a neutral tinted sweater. With
characteristic vigor he attacked the game,
and before long he was the champion play
er. There is nothing slow about the chan
cellor when he gets into action.
Tournament in January.
On January 13 an Indoor tournament will
be given. Basket hall will be the chief
feature of the c-xhihltlon. The old skat
ing rink on Kentucky street will probably
be rented for the occasion. Dr. Naismltii
says he enjoys working with college men
far better than with others. He believes
there is no artificiality whatever about e-ol-Iege
students. "If a man is a man they
will respect him and his endeavors in their
behalf." he says, "but they won t Stan. I
trilling a minute. When I find it yo'ing
fellow who kicks on the referee's decision-..
I just ask him n call fouls for a few mo
ments. After he has called a few and other
men have kicked on his rulings, h,. never
kicks again."
Pr. Naismith has much influence t
the young men in his charge. In Mrs. Cora
McColli,m Smith he has an able colleague.
The revolution In feeling which a few yearn
have brought about among the physical
culture students Is remarkable. When the
training was first Introduced about four
years ago and the girls lirst donned their
suits, the presence of a man within a ra
dius of three blocks wrought the most
awful consternation. Now men pass back
and forth throuch the r-vm to and from
the laboratory during the girls" cla.-aes and
ni'liing is thought ot it. Before long :hi
g.rls will trv basket ball. too. Equal suf
frage in ainietirs is one oi me cnarms of
Kansas university. Visitors to Lan-rem-o
must get a basket ball guide beforehand and
lecrn tne nngo. it tney wis.i to dd able to
converse intelligently with university peo
nle. for that is the all absorbing rnnle re
the day. It may not be a great while. Judg-
i hi; iruiii uiijjemuiii e ueioic processors
will be whistling students down in their
recitations and -allInc "foul" when thir
make mistakes in their translations, so
jreai is cue iiiuiience oi iiaoit
ADELIA ALICE Hl'MjPIUlEY.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1903-09-20/ed-1/?sp=24&q=High+School+Girls+Illustrating+Play+Basket+Ball</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>GIRLS ILLUSTRATING PLAY AT
3IISSES HOFFMAN AND HENSEL
Of -High's basket-ball team, IllustraUng
methods of ploy whilo preparing for a
game.BASKET BALL
By a Republic Photographer.
MISS HENSEL</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92053934/1904-11-19/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Rules+Basketball+Basket+Ball+Dribble</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NEW RULES ON BASKETBALL
Changed Conditions For Championship
Contests.
Up to the present the basketball
rules have been amended each season
by additions and omissions in various
places. This year, however, the rules
have been rearranged and many rules
bear different numbers and are not
found in the same successive order.
An advantage in the new rule book
also is that at the top of the page i3
the page, so that it is no longer neccs-
indicated the rule number printed on
that page, so that it is no longer ne
cessary to turn back or forth to ascer
tain which rule is being read.
The first new feature is that the
rules became effective Nov. 1, 1904.
This settled a fixed time for everywhere
and did not leave it open for teams to
play old Ule3 because "they did not
have the new book and there is noth
ing in the rules saying when they be
come effective," In referring to the
basket, the word "basket" is not used
in contradiction to "goal."
The minimum size of playing space
(2,400 square feet) is omitted in rule 1.
section 1. Rule 3, section 1, requires
a background of wood at least three
quarters of an inch thick for the bas
kets. Screens are no longer permitted.
The paying of the officials expenses in
serial championship games is no longer
mandatory.
An important change in rule 11, sec
tion 10. prohibits more than one player
of each team from tackling the ball at
the same time. A "dribble" is now
only counted such when the player ad
vances more than two steps wtiile roll-
UDUDDDDGBD
You can eat anything, digest it and
enjoy it if you give your stomach a
thorough course of treatment with
Dr. laber's Pbpsin lompouna.
Perhaps your stomach is over
worked and accumulates undigest
ed matter whici ferments and up
sets the entire system, causing
belching and bloating, bad breath,
a languid, weary feeling, sleep
lessness, etc.
T&ESER'SIEEEMMlGOrJlFOUnD
cleans out the refuse, heals the irritated secretive linings of the stomach, stim
ulates an activity of the digestive fluids and tones up the entire tract. Blood is
pure when digestion is complete. Dr. Taber's Pepsin Compound produces
perfect, healthy digestion. 9
TABLETS, 10c, 25c, 50c. at drug stores. Uquld Form, 50c. and $1.
KTKZPMTK? To prove its merits, we will send sample
m mmwtmmm package by mail. Free, to any address.
DR. TABER MFG. CO., Poorto, Ills.
ing or bouncing the ball.
The rule that in a dribble both hands
shall not be used simultaneously more
than once is still effective. Under rule
11, section 17, a man is not out of
bounds if only one foot is outside.
Players may be changed at any time
during the game (new rule 1, section
26). Last year's rules as well as the
new rules authorizes the referee to
award one point to the man fouled by
an opponent while trying for goal.
There was some doubt formerly as to
whether the team whose player was
fouled should also have a free throw
for goal.
The uew rules add that "this shall
noi interfere with a free throw for goal
from foul line," thus making It pos
sible to secure four points on this olio
play, if while being fouled the player
throws the goal, two points are scored,
oue point is awarded by the nfere
aud the ilayer is allowed an additional
free throw for the foul giving him uu
opiiortunity of scoring one point moro
if he throws the foul goal.
Under the old rules if a player threw
for goal from outside and missed thu
basket the ball went to the center,
while under the new rules the ball con
tinues to play. r
Under rule 12, section 1 and 4. tho
referee is required to promptly dis
qualify any player using profane or
abusive language.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn89066315/1917-11-12/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Basketball&st=text&r=-0.335,-0.084,1.67,1.67,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Introduction at the University of
Missouri of the Wisconsin style of
basketball, under the direction of Dr.
W. E. Meanwell, formerly basketball
coach at the Madison school now
athletic director here, began last
week when the first practice of the
season was held at Rothwell Gymn
asium. Missouri will learn a new
sort of basket ball this year, and,
judging from the play as Director
Meanwell taught it at Wisconsin, the
Tiger basketball work will be ofj
special interest throughout the en
tire Missouri Valley.
BatLetball l'nictlcc
Behind Closed Doors.
Director Meanwell, In his office at
Rothwell Gymnasium one day last
week, told of the old M men that were
back this year, he noted the material
as he saw it in the Missouri Valley,
and then he was asked for a brief
outline of the sort of basketball he
would teach at Missouri. The Tiger
athletic head hesitated a moment, and
then, "Mow," he said, "I've been ex
pecting just such a question as that."
Then he continued," But if you'll come
out here any night after practice is
started in earnest you'll see that I
mean what I say when I tell you that
Tiger basketball practice this year,
and every other year while I'm in
charge will be behind closed doors.
You have heard of secret football
practice well, that's what you're go
ing to have in basketball now. But
when you do see the Tiger team in ac
tion you'll see a real Valley contender,
be assured."
Wisconsin Won 92
Out of 101 Games.
There is perhaps no where in the
United States one man who has had
such unusual success with his basket
ball work as has Athletic Director W.
E. Meanwell. Fron one side of the
United States to the other and as far
from Wisconsin as the University of
Texas, there have been men sent to
see the Wisconsin game of basketball.
A record of four championship teams
in six years, with ninety-two victories
out of a total of 101 games Is perhaps
a record unequalled in the history of
basketball games in the United States.
As a result basketball stars from al
most every high school in the country
have been attracted to Wisconsin
Illinois, Missouri and many other
states having contributed men who
hae been responsible for Wisconsin
successes. Here in Missouri two
Kansas City high school stars, Diggle
and Smith were onvDoctor Meanwell's
teams and, according to the new Mis
souri sports head, were two of his
most successful players.
While Director Meanwell refuses to
discuss just the kind of basketball he
is teaching his team at Missouri the
kind he taught at Wisconsin has been
described as "short pass basketball
where a shot farther than eight or
ten feet from the basket is practically
barred. The idea seems to be to take
only a few shots at the basket but to
make these shots good when they are
taken. It is a good defensive game."
Short Pass Game Said.
To Tire Out the 1'Iajers.
v Athletic Director Meanwell's game
of basketball has been characterized
as one in which the men are too easily
worn out it has been asserted that
the short pass is more wearing on the
men than the long "whale" from one
end of the gymnasium to theother, as
Director Meanwell characterizes it.
less wearing on the men than the long
pass. According to authorities the
Meanwell teams have always succeed
ed in keeping the ball in their pos
esslon 70 per cent of the time. The
Wisconsin style of basketball was used
to some extent two years ago when
VanGent. coach at Texas, gave the
Kansas Aggies so close a run for the
Valley championship. While the style
of VanGent was not an exact copy of
the sort used by Meanwell now, It was
similar in many ways. VanGent was
center on the Wisconsin team for
three years.
Four M Jtten Are
Back This lear.
There are four of Missouri's
basketball M men back this year.
Captain J. L. Campbell, Sam Shirkey,
both forwards, C. H. Slusher and
Harry Viner, both guards are in
school this year, 4mt Viner and
Slusher are both on the football team
and for this reason are unbale to do
any work on the basketball squad.
The last year's freshmen who are in
school are Osborne, Wackher, Mc
Cann and Keith, with Craig Ruby,
star Kansas City basketball man and
captain of the Tiger freshmen two
years ago, also in line for a place on
the Varsity.
For six years Wisconsin had secret
practice in basketball. Starting this
year Missouri will not only, have
secret practice but, in addition, If the
methods of Meanwell at Wisconsin are
followed there will be grouting done
and regular reports on the plays of
other schools well be studied. Director
Meanwell has not announced as yet
any plans for "scouting" but it is
possible that this line of work will
be added to Missouri's basketball pro
gram.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038485/1916-02-27/ed-1/?sp=15&q=Basketball</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BASKETBALL NOW
ONE OF AMERICA’S
FAVORITE INDOOR
WINTER PASTIMES
Growth of Game in Alabama
and the South Has Kept
Stride Set by Eastern and
Northern States
AVERAGE OF FIFTY
TEAMS PRODUCED
IN VARIOUS STATES
Over 100 Teams Now Play
ing Under Organized
Heads as Compared With
Ten in 1906
My FRED BODEKER
The remarkable popularity of bas
ketball during the past 10 years has
elevated the game to the position of
one of the foremast in American sports.
The past decade has witnessed a seem
ingly impossible growth In the basket
game and even experts are puzzled over
the problem.
Basketball has proven itself to be
one of the best sports in every way
that help the American people to
amuse themselvefe in,the gymnasium.
Basketball makes no uncertain de
mands on heart and lungs and on en
durance generally. Basketball is a
game. That’s all—only a game. It is
not a combat nor a battle nor a fight*
as some people would term it. It is
just a game.
Authorities have often repeated the
statement that basketball does more
to form a man's character than any
other sport. The period of adolescence
is the time when basketball and sim
ilar games are played and when life’s
habits are formed and the character
largely determined. Politics is a game
and so is almost any business, and the
people are merely players in the game.
And so is basketball—it is a game and
one of the best.
DEVELOPS THE BODY
Basketball develops many parts of
the human body. It develops alertness,
gelt-control, skill, speed and brings ev
ery part of the body into action. The
game arouses the interest and enthu
siasm of every spectator. The simplic
ity and small quantity of apparatus
required, together with other chief
qualifications of the game, make it
one of the most valuable of our com
petitive games.
Basketball belongs to the large fam-
ily of games originated to amuse the
American public. It was first started
in 1891. Dr. James A. Naismtth, now
a member of the collegiate basketball
rules committee, was an instructor at
the Springfield Y. M. C. A. Training
school and undertook to devise an in
door game which would develop man
kind. Basketball was at first very sim
ple. Since then, however, the game has
undergone complete revision; but bas
ketball lovers all over the nation owe
to Dr. Naismith the honor of “invent
ing’’ the game.
Since 1891 basketball has made mar
velous strides. The game was adopted
by colleges, high schools, athletic as
sociations in all parts of the country.
The big eastern colleges first fell in
line and soon the movement spread to
the south. Beading southern colleges
and institutions quickly adopted the
game and by 1900 basketball was a
game that was beginning to be played
by all important institutions.
GROWTH IN 1906
In 1906 the game began to grow even
more popular. Athletic clubs in all parts
of the south were producing teams and
tights were being staged for the
•'championships.” Not only in the south
was the game popular, but the middle
west and the eastern states were far
ahead. It Is roughly estimated that
something over an average of 60 teams
were being produced in every state in
the union or over 2400 teams were
playing organized basketball to say
nothing of the innumerable grammar
schools and independent teams that
numbered as many more.
But basketball did not stop its won
derful growth. The game has some un
seen power that attracted clubs, col
leges and schools to adopt it. As the
years passed the number playing the
game increased and by 1910 the num
ber playing in 1906. which was es
timated to have been over 240°, was
estimated to have been doubled, or
nearly 3000 teams. This does not
elude independent teams but omy
teams as high schools, athletic clubs,
colleges and other educational institu
tion
Dr. Joseph E. Raycroft. chairman of
he joint committee on basketball
ules. is quoted as saying that the
umber of teams playing basketball
I 1910 was over 7000. This, however,
considered by many to be too large,
onsidering that six men 5s ine aver
ge number of players on one team,
ver 42,000 men were playing in or
anlzed basketball in 1910.
In Alabama in 1906, the number of
tarns playing basketball was something
he 10 or less, which Included the Bir
slngham Athletic club, Birmingham
Ugh school, Mobile, Montgomery, and a
ew others. The effects of the growth
ver the nation took effect in Alabama
nd the number in 1910 jumped to nearly
3 teams. A few hight schools were
laying the game, being seriously handt
apped by the lack of an Indoor court,
phile almost every athletic club and
M. C. A. in the state was represented
y a team.
OVER 100 TEAMS
In 1*16, the beginning of the present
eason, which Is about to come to a very
uccessful close, the number playing in
his state Jumped to over 100. Over 60
igh schools are playing basketball, with
ImoBt 40 athletic clubs and other instl
utions of this kind. The game is played
y every grammar school In the larger
itles of the state, while countless teams,
.norganlzed as in the Y. M. C. A., and
lass teams of various educational ln
tltutions, are following the same exam
Not only in Alabama but in all parts
t the country Is the game making
apld strides toward the top of the lad
ler as an indoor sport. The number
paying In the United States at the
n-esent is estimated to go over 23,000
earns, which means that about 156,600
leople are playing organized basketball
X this number Alabama can boast of
Jmoat 700 players, which, although be
nw a majority of the statee, is well in
he advanced list.
Add so it can be seen, Alabama with
ractically every other state in the' union
fast taking to basketball, and expert
rltlcs who have watched Its growth for
he past decade predict no decline In
ts power to attract the attention of
he apart loving publle.
SOUTHERN ASSOCIATION SCHEDULE, SEASON OF 1916
Although the proposed basketball tourn
ament for high school all over the state
by the Birmingham Athletic club, sched
uled for the latter part of this week,
will have no bearing on the prep cham
pionship, in which every higli school
and preparatory school in the state is
interested, lively competition promises to
be the feature of the games. No defi
nite announcement has been made as
yet as to what teams will enter, but it is
expected that at least eight teams will
qualify.
The tournament will be held on Friday
and Saturday of this week, provided the
plans work out successfully. Although
Coach Alpha Brummage, who has charge
of the tournament for the Athletic club,
is having some trouble in inducing the
teams to enter, he stated yesterday aft
ernoon that he was confident that the
tourney would be a thorough success.
Up to the present writing, seven teams
have signified their intention of enter
ing. Central High school. Bessemer High
school and the Ensley High school are
counted on as sure factors, while the
four out-of-town teams that have stated
their willingness to enter are the Bibb
County High school, Shelby County High
school, Etowah County High school and
Marbury High school.
Every possible effort is being made to
induce other teams in the state to enter.
The tourney can be made a big affair if
a sufficient number of teams enter. The
Jasper High school, of Walker county,
is seriously considering entering, as are
the Sidney Lanier High school and sev
eral other high schools, although a defi
nite statement has not been made.
The tournament will be under the rules
and regulations of the Alabama Inter
scholastic Athletic conference, of which
the majority of the above schools are
charter members. The court of the B.
A. C., where the games will be played,
will be entirely changed so as odds will
favor no team as to court. Coach Brum
mage stated yesterday that he wanted
the state high schools to be made aware
of the fact that no high school had
anything to do with the arrangements
of the tourney and the plans were en
tirely in the hands of the Birmingham
Athletic chib. He also stated that the
club would especially see that no team
was handed a "rough" deal.
As above stated, the result of the
games will have no effect on the prep
championship, but will settle the cham
pionship of the A. I. A. C. To gain
this honor alone, especially in the initial
year of the conference, would be worth
the time of any team. It is an honor
worth while trying for and the various
high schools around the state are cor
dially invited to enter and seek to gain
the laurels of the Alabama Interscho
lastic Athletic conference.
NO MORE MISSING
GAMES WILL CAUSE
ANGUISH IN LEAGUE</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020645/1926-01-24/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Basketball</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Advertiser.—As the Cotton States'
basketball tourney booked to be held
at Auburn February 18, 19 and 20,
looms near It appears that there will
be strong contenders from out of the
state on hand to participate In the
prepper setto.
While no invitations have been is
sued, Information is being sought as
to who is who in the various sections
of the southeast and Judging from the
records being received at the Ath
letic association offices, especially
from Tennessee and Georgia, the tour
nament this year will be brimful of
basketball talent.
From up in Tennessee, information
has been obtained on several teams,
some of which will doubtless be seen
In competition. The Columbia, Ten
nessee Military academy, coached by
Emmett McGauley, former captain and
•tar of the University of Alabama
quintet, is said to rank well In their
section of the Volunteer state.
From Baylor school of Chattanooga,
comes news that, the Baylorltes are
having a good year and will be in
shape to take on tough opponents. The
Baylor school is coached by “Hub”
Barks, former captain and forward of
the Auburn Plainsman squad.
In Nashville, at Montgomery-Bell
academy, is a team coached by Coach
L. P. Emerson, one of Uie best known
prep ooaches In the country, who needs
no Introduction In the Cotton States Other teams are being watched by
the basketball coaches with a view of
selecting the moat outstanding Individ
uals, for the tournament, which is less
than a month away.
Wocoala Preppers
Cop 34-15 Victory
Over Prattvillians
Flashing a strong attack In the
first few minutes of play, the Woco
Ala basketball team of the prep di
vision at Woman's college breesed
through an easy victory over Pratt
ville High Saturday afternoon at the
local college gymnasium, 34-1$. The
locals outclassed and outplayed their
opponents at all stages of the game,
the visitors being unable to break j
through the stubborn defense of the
Methodist aggregation.
The game was the first to be played
by the local prep aggregation since
their admission to the Alabama Ath
letic High School association. With
the exception of a short rally late In
the second period, the Prattville lassies
failed to show an offense.
MltUee Stanford, formerly of Tusca
loosa High, carried the attack of the
locals, and registered twelvo' field
goals, and was easily the luminary of
the contest. She showed fine floor
work, and missed few chances for
field goals. Velma Carr made a fine
co-worker with Stanford, this pair
worked like veterans throughout the
tilt. The local guards, Minnlo Motley
and Stella Moore stopped evtry at
tack of the visitors, while Matthews
and Hinton turned in a neat game at
the pivot positions.
For the visitors the work of Eliz
abeth Moore stood out, this lassls scor
ing all the points made by tne team.
The local preppers are coached by
Mary Belle Quinn and Elizabeth Tay
lor. members of the senior class at
[Woman's college, and who have en
joyed considerable experience in bas
ketball circles at the college.
Line ups:
Prattville: Moore (15) and McCreary,
forwards: Smith and Chambliss, can
ters; Wadsworth and Jones, guards.
WocoAla: ($4), Stanford (14) and
Carr,- (10) forwards; Hinton and Mat
thews, centers; Moore and Motley,
guards.
Substitutions, Prattville, Anthony
for McCreary. WocoAla, Woodall for
Moore.
Referee, Watllngton (W. C. A.).
Scorer, Jimmie Walker, (W. C. A.).
the cellar and have also added a big
right hand pitcher, Lundgren from the
Southern association, to the pitching
staff.
This winter the Red Sox added Em
mett McCann of the Coast league to
play second base alongside Pudley Pee,
former Tulsa star.
The new catchers are mostly major
league veterans.
CLIO AGAIN WINKER.
CLIO. ALA.. Jan. 23.—Louisville HI
again fell victim to the Clio Jackets
in a close score of 10 tr 0 In Louis
ville Wednesday.
The Jackets are'showing wonderful
improvement in handling and tossing
the basketball, and hope to le repre
sented in the County Basketball tour
nament, which is to be held In Blue
Springs January 1-|0.
r:. -ji; V.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/2023271000/1944-09-22/ed-1/?sp=7&q=Basketball</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>He played football an basketball and was on the track team in
college.
Prior to his entrance in the Navy he coached eight years in Ne
braska and South Dakota high schools.
McGillis, softball team coach, is supervisor of gymnasium activities
n the temporary recreation building.
Langstaff, Company 1 Instructor
Another member of the group is Delbert Langstaff, Sp(A)2c, from
Sioux City, la., who is a graduate of Morningside Colege, where he
played basketball and baseball.
Veteran of last season’s Depot varsity basketball and baseball
earns, he serves as athletic instructor for company 1.
Hollon, Former New York Player
Wilbur Hollon, Sic, who attended Brooklyn College, is athletic in
structor for company 3.
Former football and basketball player in New York, he is now in
charge of barracks recreation.
Hawkins, Star on Depot Teams
Leonard Hawkins, GM3c, of Marion, Ind., attended Wilberforce
University, Xenia, 0.
He played on last season’s Depot basketball and baseball teams,
and now serves as company 6 athletic instructor. He is a member of
the football and basketball committee.
Carlock in Charge of Bowling, Billiards
Hoyle Carlock, Sic, played football and baseball at Sumner high
school in Kansas City, Mo.
He is athletic instructor in company 2, and is in charge of bowling
and pocket billiards activities.
Hammond Former Pittsburgh Player
Fred Lee Hammond, Jr., Sic, of Pittsburgh, attended Sharksburgh
high school in Pittsburgh, and plays basketball and football.
He is athletic instructor for company 7, and a member of the De
pot football and basketball committee.
Walker World Champion High Jumper
Another outstanding specialist is Melvin E. Walker, Sp(A)3c, of
Chicago, a graduate of Ohio State University and an Olympic high
jumping champion.
Formerly supervisor of recreation in the Chicago Park District, he
holds two world’s high-jumping records, and has made records in this
country as well. An All-American football and
basketball C.I.A.A. champion, he
was formerly head coach at Samuel
Houston College.
He is chairman of the football
and basketball committees, and
will conduct tournaments in these
activities.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063730/1929-02-17/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Basketball</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>he Arkansas Razorbacks »ere
within one victory of clinching their
fourth straight southwest confer
ence basketball crown tonight after
they defeated the Rice Institute
Owls, 44 to 13, to sweep a two-game
aeries.
As on the previous night there
waa no doubt of the result after the
firat minute of play. The giant
Porkers swarmed down the floor and
began looping baskets and the Owls,
cellar occupants, rapidly left be
hind. PARIS. Tex., Feb. 16.—VP)—Paris
Junior college defeated Gainesville
Junior college, 34 to 23. in a Junior
college basketball game here tonight.
FIGHTS IN MERCEDES MONDAY
CHUCK BURNS Cameron county'* basketball title i
has been settled, and the crown fell
upon the broud shoulders of the
Brownsville Eagles, and it could not
have fallen to more worthy players.

Coach Plato took a bunch of green j
and untried basketball players as a
whole, and has welded them into a
smooth working court outfit. They
didn't look good at the start of the
season, but an indomitable spirit
could not be held down, and many
of the weak points were overcome
by the team as a whole, and today
it stands as the best this county ha;,
to battle other county champs.
a
In defeating El Jardin, the locals
met worthy opponents for the title.
Coach Richey’s Comets have earn
ed the admiration of fandom in
these oarts by their fine and hust
ling play. With a limited amount
of material, the Comets battled
their way to the finals in excel
lent fashion, and lost to a better
team in the final game.
e
Cameron county can well be proud
of iis basketball champs. W ilson j
Tract girls and Brownsville high
schocl boys' teams. The Aztecs, as j
the Wilson Tract champs are called,
under the mentorship of Coach L. A.
Francis, swept aside all opposition
to gain the honor, as they did last j
year. The Eagles, under Coach Pla- j
to, got off to a slow start, but final
ly got going, and the way the local
quint went about their business on
the court field in the past few games,
reminded spectators of the champion
ship football team of last year. It
must be remembered, too, that prac
tically every member of the local
quint was a member of last year’s
grid outfit. The starting lineup of
basketball team, is composed entirely
of star gridders, such as Barnhart,
Weller, O'Bryan, Sylvester, New
man.
e e
Ezell Darby, a former San Benito
high school football, baseball and
basketball star, was in the city yes
terday afternoon, refereeing' the El
Jardin Brownsville game. Darby is
anxious to play baseball this sum
mer, and will. He pitched for Waco
last season, after leaving school at
San Marcos. At present he is as
sistant coach of the Donna schools.
If a Valley league is organized, Ezell
ought to make some team a good
manager.

Brownsville is a good haaeball
town, and a whale of a football
town. If a winning eloh represents
the school, hut a poor basketball
city. It has a winning high school
court team, and about a dozen local
fans attended the championship
game yesterday afternoon on the
local court. It is a fact that El
Jardin was represented by more
fans than Brownsville.
e a e
It is true the schedule hasn't been
carried out as advertised, causing
fans to go to the field at night, and
no game being played, due to a last
minute change in the schedule, as
the school officials are apt to do
in regard to a basketball contest,
any minute. So that is a thing that
must be stopped by the schools.

But the thing this city needs most
is a gymnasium for its students.
Games like basketball, handball,
indoor baseball, etc., would become
popular with local fana If they
knew the games were to be played
on indoor diamonda. Let’s hope
a gymnasium is built for the
public schools of this city.

Cameron. Willacy, Starr and Hi
dalgo county champs in basketball,
will meet this week. Friday and Sat
urday, to determine the championship
of this part of the state. Raymond
ville, from Willacy; Brownsville,
from Cameron; McAllen, from Hidal
go, and Rio Grande, from Starr, are
the four clubs to fight it out this
week end.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-badminton/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059522/1886-04-04/ed-1/?sp=12&q=badminton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>How the Young People of New York
ltclux Strict Formality at
Badminton* Occasionally the .in.,
car bell could be heard but nobody luliruiutl
into the Badminton club. The only signs
<»f life were supplied by the nimble young
swell who danced carelessly about in the
sunshine, batting the feathered toy up to
ward the roof. With the rich colors of his
costume and his nimbleness he might have
been tnistaden by a buloonist peering from
above for a huge tropical bird of some cay
but gawky sort disporting itself grotesquely
in the sun.
THE SOLITARY
young; badminton player who was romping
so joyously was a howling swell of a very
high order. He didn't look like a man of
pint importance, but socially his position 1
is enviable. A man who at the age of j
twenty-eiirht can boast of membership in
the Summerset club, of Boston; the Savage
club, of London; the Jockey club of Paris,
and the Union. Knickerbocker and Union
League clubs, of New York: has a racing
■table of his own and spends SGO.OOO a
year without earning the reputation of
being a spendthrift or a fool, must neces
sarily amount to something in the woild of
society. lie seemed as happy as a clam at
high tide, batting away there skillfully,
when a brougham drove up to the door and
a young woman and her maid bustled in he
gave a yell of meeting that was quite un
dignified, and reminded one strongly of a
street Arab.
••Late again. Miss Agatha," he chirped,
happily. "Ton me soul it is quite heart
rending for a man of my conscientiousness
and t lustful nature to receive these disap
pointments every play-day."
''Indeed, you are a paragon,"' said the
jrirl. smiling brightly, and aoastaglsßf wraps
t" the maid. "It was the fault of mamma
Ibis morning. She was desperately blue
when she irot out of bed, and so she climbed
bark in again. Then she insisted upon my
rending to her until she felt more composed,
and there you are."
She had scarcely finished speaking when
there was a great chatter and bustle about,
and half a dozen people hurried in. Two
of the guls were in full tennis rig. and
when one of the men slipped off his long
ulster he revealed the fact that he. too. had
put on his play-day togs before suiting
from home.
WHAT STRUCK ME HARDEST.
However, was the fact that the belles
were so much more shapely and graceful
than the beaux. More than one bony fellow
had on what 1 believe actors call "Mats."
That is to Kay, their legs were artificially
enlarged and straightened by padding. No
till was jruilty of such deceit. But 1 don't
mind telling you just what girl; do in their
One when costuming for badminton or ten
nis.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85047239/1886-10-13/ed-1/?sp=5&q=badminton</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>PLAYING BADMINTON
A TWO HOJRS FROLIC FOR NEW
YORKS SOCIETY YOUNG FOLKS
Arrlrnl of the UlcucstHwolI of tlio Dun
silo Aflor nil ISlnbornte Cniirne of
Thought Sixty Thtinsnnil u Ycnr nutl
i llio ltesiilta Thormf
People wlio lnmglno tlmt tlio young men
and women of Now York society tiro still
mul formal In tholr manners would have
been somewhat surprised at tlio crowd of
young pcoplo who met together ono
nftornoon to play badminton In a queer
little Fourth avenue building
It didnt take a very shrowd obsorvcr
to discover that badminton as played In
Now York consists of conversation to a
very largo extent Interspersed with n fow
cursory bits of hit nnd rclsplay with tho
racquets Tlicro wore no chnperones at
nil at this gamo nnd it amounted to a
merry sort of a frolic for two hours In tho
middle of tho day It was amusing to
listen to the talk for tho English accent
which Is affected so laboriously by soino
of tho aocloty people was picked up nnd
dropped precisely as fancy dictated by tho
gorgeously attired pooplo who made bad
minton an excuse for meeting without
being oppressed by tho presence of chnpur
one duennas
A DKEP AND LOCIICAL CONCLUSION
Tlio biggest swel of tho dandlos arrived
an hour before time Ho was a small man
with prominent teeth rather n pallid face
and a pair of shadowy sldo whiskers Ho
pranced up to the door of tho flimsy frame
structure and nodded carelessly to a stolid
Englishman who stood by the door with n
straw In his mouth and his hands in his
pockets
Good mnwnln Fowbes said tho now
comcr screwing a slnglo glass Into ono of
his weak eyes and glaring hard at the at
tendant Is any ono heahf
Not yet sir said tho attendant re
spectfully
Aw muttered tho young man otm
plncently I am tho llrst ono thon Hav
ing arrived at this deep nnd logical con
clusion after an elaborate course of
thought ho cost n ghostly and transparent
sinllo at Forbes mid drifted through tho
doorway Into the burn liko structure
Hero he cast a critical view at a not which
extended across the floor went to ono
of a sorlos of small lockors and took
therefrom a racquet Then he ascended
the smidl stairway to a gallery vhoro
there were a fow dressing rooms and pres
ently emerged In all tho glory of whlto
flannel knickerbockers and shirt with long
red stockings a blue nnd whlto silk Nor
folk Jacket nnd a blue worsted Tom
OShantcr cap perched artfnlly upon his
rather peculiar looking head I Around one
of his slim wrists there was a broad leathor
band clasped with four buckles a scheme
by which champion badminton nnd tenuis
players strengthen wrists that have been
strained by overplay Tho single glass
now hung over his breast Ho dnnccd
about for a moment to limber up his legs
and then stepping out into tho Inclosuro
across which tho net was placed ho
slipped off his silk jacket produced n llttlo
cube into which was inserted a rim of
feathers and tossed it in tho air When it
came diving forward with bullet llko
directness ho caught It deftly on the end
of his racquot and scut it Into tho air
again
A HOWLINO SWELL OK IIIOII OllDCB
Tho solitary young badminton player
who was romping so joyously was a howl
ing swell of a very high order Ho didnt
look llko a man of great Importance but
socially his position Is enviable A man
who at tho agtuf 23 spends ftWOOO a year
without earning the reputation of being a
spendthrift or n fool must necessarily
amount to something in the world of
society Ho seemed as happy ns a clam at
high tldo batting away there skillfully
when a brougham drove up to tho door
and a young woman nnd her maid bustled
v in ho gave n yell of greeting that was quite
undignified nnd reminded ono strongly of
a street Arab</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1890-03-09/ed-1/?sp=18&q=badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>PLAYERS OF BADMINTON.
JWO CLUBS WHER1- THE WRDS" ILV >VEB
THE NETS.
A DESCRIfTION Of THE GAJfE-IT- POPTJIiAltlTT
AS A I.KNTl-V AMUSEMI \T *a
pkople wi llesown is
The pame of badminton, "f nli games "t akill. is
pcrhaps loast kti .wa by iho publle i.t large. It
is ncarly as mueh a game "i egilitj and quick
ncss as iciinis, and, altho igb the Mercite required
is not Tlolent, thecnjoymenl experlenced i.y tbe
playcrs in a cloaely oontested game la Jui
kcen as m tho more wldely known -istor game.
lat nn Indlfferenl player badminton i- much the
r.etter form nt sp-'M. and iho women w o go io
lor it are mdre entbuBlaatic iu it* supporl than
the most eonfirmed playcra -.i tennia The
liko it becauae it givea them an nppetite. and iu
this it nevei f.ii!-*. Cocktalla ire i t. to I c com
jiaicl with H- Sherry and bitters hecomes na
aotbing, nnd ;i good dinnei preceded bj badniin
tBadminton may be played either i the lawn
or ladoors. ln Ita Indoor fonn it is. and is likely
to renniin. Sew-York'a fashionable L??nten paatime
aml n- auch ii certainly deservcs praise.
Ih. game aa now played i-- nol ..t greal i??
tlquity, oi il ll la, there ia no deflnlte reoord of
the lnit, lt ia I Anglo-Indlan origln, and baa
been siii.o 1E. i u favorite with -.ngllab oJheera i
India. The form ol game played ln Sew-York
ri..es not diffei materlallj fr..m thal played bj
tho Aiiin.ilaiil Badminton Club In India. and the
rulA* now adopted ure pructically tlie -ainc
Tho BBaterlala for badminton aro differcnl
iboee uaed for tei igb the gai
mlghl appeai simil r n e net la from two feel
to two feel si_ ii cl es in bre idth, ai I ln_t
N-i.i- sei upon tlu ng poles
nnd ia 1 ung al a distam c ol from Hve i
j et to six fe 1 from tbe surfa. e oi Ihe court.
Inste i-l ol balls, sli ittlecocka, or bir la, oa they
nrc teehnlcally c lled, are used. Tlie racq cts
nr b it* with which l aboul are
rencrally ol a Lighter weighl and souiewli kl smaller
than the ordinory tennis i icque.,
tennla ruc<] et can be For in
door pl ig a i ird wei ;1 i incc is
iiaed, bul oui or?, un ac. wind, i ce
weighliLg. an ounce and three-eeTered with rubber to prevenl uu urj from nio__t
urc, is I.-fi-.
Vl_vr>'
Cil's OF THE BIRDS
In dreaa ry for
pla- ii Iminlon. Tbe exei bi*. nol
lent. tennla Hannels cuu l*e and
even U nnis shoes re d. lf ln\v
aro woi feli aoles should bc
ctiosen. Women should wear lost sligl tly
.liortcr tharj the invc tional aa i
af aome aofl Bes tuaterial thal will nol Intei
fciv wll ii.
l s of the court musl be Ln a
tneas ;rc delermlned by the lize ol the Boor oi
la\\;i npon to lie 1 dd out. Oue1 w
elghl Uil ki i md twenty feel broad
but the ed by the
N< xx- ork I
nn elevatl :i i Iee1 it answers thi
is as geod aa ui I 11 iu.ir .--i
aat carefully with chalk lines, oi lf _
Mr::,. i and I.
Frn::i one to i ir peraona play <>n a aiie, and
t!.e ahuttlee. k or bird^ niuM in
Beturaed on a "volley" or before lo
court Burface. The "blrds" are sei ed and re
t i
cepi that if the shuttlecock falla to the eourl
gorface it ia ni <1 a nii__ to I plnyei
laila to return il and lo bia aiile. Tbe servicc is
from t!. i c ia, 1 lie
pl;iV,T bi fe within u section
?i i two i.-i t und sx, ineliea from the
earaer. Th* divisiona f the eourt* nr.- onlj oh
Berve.l on the aerve, aml the playera can Btand
wliere tliey plea>e on tbeir own si ;'ft?i it
Tlie Bhuttk I ser ed a tlu lt falla
Wlthln the lines i I cn ice c< url as in teiuiia,
0n,l ele r of tlu c! ropea and poata I tlie et
it touelied in tbe gervice and the "I'nd" falla
ovor. the Btroke ia ealled a, "lot" and docs not
connt -.r- ki er.
Iii p|ay, be wi vi i tbe touchintj ol the :i by the
glitiitlri tt g ea over counta aa a o -1
ati.. II the i ichi I I tlie racqui
nel with
tbeir racqueta, tlie st
JVo i..nli. p U hand out," and in all
?birdB lallin- upon boundary linea re re
?arded as "faulta, both iu acrvice and in play.
fifteen point* eonatitnte the game. No over
liain! -i:. ia all iwcd ii the eervice. ln ja-l_
Ing wbether pl yei I re i ied over the net,
it is ajwi noticcd il the bird ia st: ick be
lote ii haa eroaaed Ihe nel aml merel> been foi
lowcl over by the raequel <>f player. Iu
this eaae il li i t ud stroke, bul il the racquet
itsolt tou il ea the nei tbe pl ia cotinti i a miss
The game ol b dmini >u introdu ed In thia
country .luiin. the xx.i.t.-r 1-1- b I.y
ar.l t larke aad E. Langiton Wilks, and ihe nu
eleua ot the Im New-York liudunniou Club w_?
then formed.
THE OEEST OF THE CI.l'B.
The Badminton Clah was 1I10 pioneer. nnd its
luoeess has iicn much greatei than Ife</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn97065075/1891-06-19/ed-1/?sp=1&q=badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Badminton was invented, or origin
ated, whichever you please, in England,
but owes its present rules to the Ah
medabad Badminton club of India,
Which has practically revived the sport.
It is a modification of lawn tennis, with
some important differences, as will be
seen further on, and has the advantage
that it can be, and generally is, played
in-doors. This make3 it both a suramet
and winter game.
Tho dimensions of the court must be
decided in a great measure by the capa
bilities of the room in which the game
is played. Tho best size Is one twenty
eight feet long by twenty feet broad.
The courts should bo marked off by
means of pegs and strings, or better,
when possible, by white chalk lines oe
the floor, and divided in the following
way: At each end ol the ground are
two courts, ten feet square, while the
center is formed by a piece of neutral
ground eight feet broad by twenty feet
long. On each of these outer lines of
the neutral ground and in the center
are placed tho posts which support tho
net The net, which is two feet to two
feet six inches deep, is suspended at a
height of six feet from the ground, and
firmly held by guy ropes attached to
posts.
The racquets used in Badminton, to
be easily and quickly Wielded, should
be lighter than those used in lawn ten
nis, and consequently smaller. A shut
tlecock is used instead of a ball, and
may be large or small, according to tho
wish of the players.
In its general line, Badminton is a
game played in the same fashion as
lawn tennis, with tho exception that
from one to four persons may play on a
side, and that tho shuttlecock must be
returned on the volley. Tho shuttle
cock is served and returned under tho
same provisions, except that, of course,
if the shuttlecock falls on the ground,
it Is counted as a miss to the player
missing it, and to his side. The servico
shall be from the "service-corner," tho
server and receiver each standing with
both feet within their respective quad
rants until the shuttlecock is struck.
The divisions of the respective courts
are only observed in the serve or first
hit; after that, the partners may stand
where they please, on their side of tha
net The shuttlecock must be served
in such a way that it falls clear over the
net, without touching the net, ropes or
posts, and falls inside the lines of the
service-court If the net Is touched in
service and tho shuttlecock falls over,
the stroke is considered as a "let," and
does not count as a fault against the
person serving. In play, however, the
touching of the net by the shuttlecock,
when it falls over, is counted as good
stroke. If the net is touched by the
racquets of the players, or if they reach
over the net with their racquets, tho
stroke counts against them. Two faults
puts "hand out" In all cases a shuttle
Cock falling on any of the boundary
lines Is regarded as a fault, as if it had
fallen outside Of the boundary lines,
both in service and play.
Iifteen points constitute the game.
In service no overhand stroke is allow
ed. The shuttlecock is judged by where
it strikes and not by where it lies after
striking. In judging whether a player
has reached over tho net, the umpire
should bo careful to note if the shuttle
cock Is struck before it has crossed the
net and not by the racquet of the play
or, which is naturally carried forward
by the impetus of the stroke and which
might arrive at a slight angle over the
net, although the shuttlecock itself was
struck on the correct side. If, however,
the net is touched by the racquet the
stroke counts against the player, wheth
er the shuttlecock was struck on the
right side of the net or not
As will be seen from the description,
Badminton requires agility and a quick
eye, rather than great strength, and it
will be found to be a game at which
girls can play with pleasure and profit
Golden Days.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045604/1891-05-31/ed-1/?sp=9&q=badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>badminton Has Not Driven
Tennis From Favor.
BOSSIP OF THE CHAMPIONS.
I y Mabel Cahill, the John L. Sullivan
•f the Xew York Club, and Other
i Great Flayers.
1
i jriw YORK. May 25.—[Special Corre
jpoodence.J—The tennis season of 1891 has
fairly begun, and from present appear
ances it will be the liveliest one that has
aver been known in this country. There
was a prospect earlier in the season that
badminton might supplant the older game
in favor, but every one concerned now
scouts the possibility of such a result. No
one, naturally, takes a keener interest in
the question than the makers of tennis
goods, and they report the largest advance
tale* on record. It is one of the not to be
forgotten consequences of the popularity
of lawn tennis that the manufacture and
nleof neta, rackets, lawn markers, shoes
and uniforms has become a great industry.
It is only a few years since all these goods
were imported from England, the home of
fee game; now they are practically all
Bade here, and th» business amounts to
something like $10,000,000 a year to the
trade. This is looking at the other side of
the sport, but the point of view is not an
unimportant one.
The clubs in and about New York are in
nnmfctr almost legion, and they are pre
paring busily for championship events,
mcticaliy the season begins with Decora
tion day, the month of fine weather before
that date being given np to practice play
ing. Of course, play begins earlier South.
The Washington City tournament for the
championship of the Southern states was
held in the middle of May. Tomorrow
the New York Tennis Club will hold its
spring games, and from now to the end of
the season in October there will be a
tournament every day—for not a summer
hotel of any size is without its tennis
courts, the smaJlest villages have their
clubs, and matches and return matches
t are shrewdly relied upon to keep up the
interest in the game.
Undoubtedly the success of tennis is
OLLIE CA MPBELL.
largely due to the fact that men and
women can play it together. For flirta
tion purposes it may not quite eoual the
sedate and sluggish game of croquet,
but for a judicious combination of
sport and opportunities for tete-a-tetes
its equal has never been invented.
Indeed, tennis is the ideal ladies' game.
As it requires agility rather than strength
to play tennis, there is no reason why
women should not play quite as well as
men, if it were not for the perpetual haudi
cap ot skirts. As it is, an active young
woman is about a match for a stout and
middle-aped man, with equal practice, and
some of the lest women players can hold
their own with any but the very best men.
i his is a test not to be recommended,how
ever, as the practice of playing with one of
the other sex rather tends to break a man
up. as he is divided between his gallantry
and his desire to excel. Thus it may easily
happen that a man will show tip in better
form at the end of a season with compara
tively little practice with men than if he
had considerable careless playing with
women. Championship games are, of
course, always between players of the
•tne sex.
•Since Scars, of Boston, who was an ex
fi.ordinary tennis player, met with a dis
cing accident, the honors of the game
Jwe rested with the Brooklyn players
Henry \V. Stocum, jr., son of General ll!
W. Slocum, the champion of iw, and Oli
"Ollie" Campbell, the present
bolder ot the championship, both having
park in past years,
though Mr. Slocum is ;IOR a member of
P:. George's Club, of New York. There is
perhaps no place in the country where bet
ter provision is made for tennis playing on
large scale than at Prospect park, and
there are few days in spring or summer
when a considerable number of games are
lot going on there simultaneously.
The frequency of va ant lots in the resU
yace sections of Brooklyn rather favors. Badminton came to the front last winter
as an indoors game, for which it was well
adapted by the smallness of the court re
quired. A tennis court is 78 feet by 27
wider than an ordinary city lot and nearly
as deep. The badminton court is only 44
feet by 20, and can be recommended for a
home game where spare is verv limited.
The net is shorter and higher. The short
service line is 6 feet 6 inches from the net.
The base line is 15 feet t inches farther
back on either side. The net itself is 16
feet long and 5 feet high in the middle.
In the play a shuttlecock is used in
stead of the white ball used in ten
nis. This is made of rubber and
feathered to steady its light. Ordinary
tennis rackets are used instead of the ola
faehioned "battledores." The game is, in
fact, a sort of cross between lawn tennis
and the older game, and is said to be the
invention of an English officer in India,
who found the climate too hot for ten
nis. Perhaps that is the reason why old
tennis players call badminton a lazy peo-
Sle's When such sturdy at hletes as
[amihon Cary and .Stanley Mortimer and
such clever tennis experts as Miss Annie
Webb, Miss Turnure, Miss Minturn and
Miss Elsie Mitchell play and enjoy thgame, however, it can safely he assumed
that, there is plenty of exercise in it.
The rules of badminton are so simple
that they can be summarized in a para
graph. There is no authoritative Ameri
can body like the National Tennis Associ
ation, but the English rules are used:
The sides toss for choiceof ends or service
before the first game of a match, and change
to the other sideof the netafter each game.
The single-handed and double-handed
game consists of fifteen ares. At "13 all,"
the side which first reaches thirteen has
the option of "setting^'five; at 14 all, of
setting three. In three-handed or four-
handed jrames the game consists of twenty
one aces. First set is at 19 all; second at
20 all. A fault made by a player whose
I side is in puts a baud out; if made by a
j player whose side is out it counts an afe to
i the in side. It is a fault if the service is
I "overhand"; if the rirs-t part of the path of
the shuttlecock is inclined downward ;if the
service falls into the wrong court; if the ser
vice falls short of the service line or outside
the bounding line; unless both the server's
teet are in his own court; if the shuttle
cock falls outside the bounds of the court;
if the shuttlecock does not pass between
the posts, or if it pass under or through
tiie net or touch anything except the bat
of the striker, or the top of the net if the
shuttlecock !e hit twice intentionally by
tiie same player; if the shuttlecock be
struck before it crosses the striker's side of
i the net; if the striker touch the net or its
supports with his racket or otherwise,
i The player in the right-hand court com
mencea the game by serving to the plaver
in the adverse right-hand oourt; if tfiat
leaver return the shuttlecock, it must be
hit ack by the in side and then returned
by the out side till a fault is made by one
j side or the other. The game is continued
in this manner, count being chanced after
j each ace ;s made. The service lines nre
disregarded alter the serve is returned,
j Iho innings always begin with the player
j in the right-hand court, and serves arc
i made alternately from each court into the
one d. t.; iia.lv opposite. In two. three
and tour-handed games, the side begin
ning a game has only one hand in its nrst
innings if there are two a side, and only
two hands if there are three a side. Inatwo
h and el game only the ptrson served to may
take a serve; not so in a three or four
handed game. The service must not begin
till the opponent is ready, but any attempt
to return is taken to indicate readiness.
Any unforseen or accidental hindrance
may be given by a "let" bv the umpire on
appeal from either side "before the next
service commences or before the players
have changed sides at the end of a game.
A "let" cannot be claimed it" an attempt
I ha* been made to strike the shuttlecock
Pitiably the next winter there will be a
badminton association iu this country r or
the new game may he taken under the
l government of the tennis association.
PLAN OF A BADMINTON OOt'P.T.
A GAME OF BADMINTON
Fightint for Ills Hi. t
New York Sun</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1891-10-04/ed-1/?sp=8&q=badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Th Badminton lawn tennla axpert yesterday mo
eeeded In capturing both of the sterling silver trophies
In th recently formed Inter-Club Tennis Association of
King county. The scoresi
Gentlemen' Single Flnt round: B, IV Booecek,
Knickerbocker Field Club, forfeited to A. 8. Mertam,
Badminton Tennis Club; Dr. W.N. Fraser. King County
Tennis Club, beat B. 8. Ueltcamp, Altlora" Tennis Club,
e 8, ft 0; E. L. Heltrarap, Altlora T. C, beat A. Fransl
ola, Knickerbocker Field: Club, 82, 84: C. E. Mao
Mabon, Badminton T. C, beat A. G. McGowan. King
County T. C, 84. 80; A. 8. Merlam, Badminton T.
C, beat Dr. B.O. Fraser, Kings County T. C, 03, 08,
78.
Second Round K. L. Ileltkatnp, Altlora T. 0, beat O.
E. MacMabon. Badminton, T. O. 76. 88: A. 8. Mer
lam, Badminton. T. C, beat Dr. B, 0, Fraxer, Kings
County T. C tt-4, 68. 7-6.
Final Round A. 8. Merlam, Badminton T. C, defeated
L. lleltkamp. Alt.ora T. C. 0-0. 7-6, 82.
Gentlemen' Double, First Round E. H. Payne and
H. E. McGowan, King County T. C. beat E. L. llelt
kamp and H. B. lleltkamp. ARortaT. C, 8-8, 6-3: A.
8. Merlam and C. E. MarMahon. Badminton T. C. beat
K.H.Lou and Harry Wall. Knickerbocker Field Club,
fl 01; Harry rranclola and William Boocock.
Knickerbocker Field Club, beat J. 8, Jones and John U.
Rollins, Altlora T. C..H-0. 68,81; Dr. R.O. Prater
and F. M, Pendrelgh. Kings County T. C beat Dr. V. A.
Griffiths and O. N. Hchmtdt, BadmlntonT. C, 8-2, 8-0.
Heeond Round E. M. Payne and II. E. McOowan.
Kings County T. C were beaten by A. S. Merlam and C,
R. MacMabon. Badminton T.C., O 2. 2-fl, 0-4: Harry
Pransclola and William Boocock, Knickerbocker Field
Club, were defeated by Dr. W. N. Fraser and F, M. Pen
drelgh, Kings County T. C, 8-8, rt-O.
Final Round Dr. Prater and F. M. Fendrelgb. King
County T. c., were beaten by A. 8. Merlam and c E.
MacMabon, Badmldton T. C 13-11. 810, 67, 0-1,
68.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1907-11-10/ed-1/?sp=45&q=Badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>GAME OF BADMINTON
I Copyright by James Elver son
ITTS^~ ADAITNTON was invented,' or orig
|J Ij inatcd, whichever you please, in
I !*•"*_ England, but owes its present rules
RtjlSSSfj to the Ahmedabad Badminton Club,
Mvlfilr" o f India, which has practically re
vived the sport. It is a modification
of lawn tennis, with some important differ
ences, as will be seen further on, and has the
advantage that it can be,- and generally is,
played indoors. This makes it both a sum
mer and winter game.
The dimensions of the court Imuit be de
cided in a grjfat measure by the j capabilities
of the room in, which the game lis played.
The best size ii one 28 feet long- by 20 feet
broad. The courts should be marked off by
means of pegs and strings, 'or better, when,
possible, by white chalk lines jon j the floor,
and divided in the following way: At each
end of the ground axe two courts. L jlO feet
square, while the centre is formed by a piece
of neutral ground 8 feet broad by 20 feet long.
On each of the outer lines of the neutral
I ground and in the centre are placed the posts
which support the net. .C-
The net, which is 2 feet to 2l2 l feet 6 inches
deep, is suspended at a height of 6 feet from
the ground, and firmly held by. guy ropes at
i tached to posts. ,y L
1 The racquets used in Badminton, to be easily
and quickly wielded, should be lighter than
those used in lawn tennis, and consequently
smaller. A shuttlecock is used instead of a
ball, and may be large or small, accorum" to
the 'wish of the players. .7 .1
In its general; line, Badminton is a game
played in the same fashion': as lawn tenni*,
with the exception that from one to four
persons may play on a side, and that the shut
tlecock must be returned on the volley. -_•
The shuttlecock is served and returned
under the same provisions, except that, of
i course if the shuttlecock falls on the ground,
it is counted as a miss to. the player missing
it and to his side." The service shall be from
the "service-corner," the server I and receiver
each standing with both feet within their
respective quadrants until the shuttlecock v
struck.
The divisions of the respective courts are
only observed in the serve or first hit; after
that the partners may 1 stand where they
please, on their side of the ¦net....
The shuttlecock must be served in Mich a
wav that it falls clear over the net. without
touching the net, ropes or posts, and falls in
ide the lines of the service court.
If the net is touched m service and the
shuttlecock falls over, the stroke is oonsid
i BOYS AND GIRLS MAGAZINE SECTION
At tltc first tfelfOi ' J fyr/ff£ Jttf/a 38 a "let," and does not count us a fault
against tbe person serving.
In play, however, the touching of the net
by the shuttlecock, when it falls over, is
counted as good stroke.
If the net is touched by the racquets of the
players, or if they reach over the ne£_ with
their racquets, the stroke counts against
them.
Two faultf puts "hand out." In all cases
a shuttlecock falling on any of the boundary
lines is regarded as a fault, as if it had fallen
outside of the boundary lines, both in service
and play.
Fifteen points constitute the game. In ser
vice no overhand stroke is allowed.
The shuttlecock is judged by where it strikes
and not by where it lies after striking.
In judging whether a player has reached
ever the net, the umpire should be careful to
note if the shuttlecock is struck before it
has crossed the net and not by the racquet of
the player, which is naturally carried forward
by the impetus of the stroke and which might
arrive at a slight angle over the net. although
the -shuttlecock itself was struck fairly on the
correct side.
If, however, the net is touched by the
racquet the stroke counts against the player,
whether the shuttlecock was struck on the
right side of the net or not.
As will be st%n from the description, Bad
minton requires agility and a quick eye, rather
than great strength, and it will be found to
be a game at which girls can play with pleas
ure and profit.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1909-05-23/ed-1/?sp=29&q=badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text><BADMINTON TENNIS CLUB
HOLDS FIRST DAYS PLAY
SANTA MONICA, May 22.—The
newly formed Badminton Tennis club
held its Brit play today on the Third
street courts. The club is the offshoot
of the Badminton dub, which held
sway last season, and Includes some
of the best racquet wlelders of South
ern California.
Among thus,- who will bi seen on
id, i club milts this season are Mrs.
i; i,. Warring, the Mlssea Archer,
Miss Ryan, Miss Marshall, Miss Rower,
lliss Nettleshlp and Mrs. Bruce./text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1920-03-28/ed-1/?sp=23&q=badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Will Boom Badminton
j The Badminton Club, of New York,
an organization established in 1878,
I which has continuously since that time
I tried to foster and develop the game of
I badminton in this city, will hold 07;
I Saturday, March 27, an intercity tour?
nament with Caines Badminton Club.
I of Boston. There will be four matches
of men's singles, three women's sin-j
gles, two men's doubles, one women's
doubles and three mixed doubles.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1907-08-04/ed-1/?sp=12&q=Badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Badminton is the modem form of ahuttlecock
tlecock and besides the tournaments of thoNew
New York Badminton Club It Is an established
lished winter indoor game in many of thelargo
largo cities In England there are badminton
minton courts in many of the clubs andcountry
country houses In India ball badmintoni
u played In large outdoor courts ColK
K F ftcddome of the Indian Army believeshat
hat this game should become a popularsummer
summer postimo In Oreat Britain and theI
I nitol Staten In a late ieUCoLBeddomofives
fives a description of the game from whichthis
this summary ia condensedThe
The correct size of an outdoor badmintonrotjrt
rotjrt is eighty feet by forty feet but forn
obvious reasons It ill more generally played
n a full sized lawn tennis pourt whlc laonly
only a little smaller A line down the centref
fir the ground divides it into right and leftfourtfl
courts and a cross line is marked two yardsrom
rom the net on each aide as a servingTeano
Teano over which the ball must be servedserver
or he server is out The net la five feet ninewhen
when against five feet for the shuttlecockB
Im but six feet is sometime playedlie
I ltter
lie siiltbdnjc longer rallies but this latterneiabt
heIgsit is not favored by good playersThere
There are five players on eaoh sideTim
Tim right and left fronts stand about twovnnJs
Verde beyond tho serving crease and havenot
not much moving about but they haveto
to 1m on the look out for all short or sneakingKfrvicea
Kfrvicea as well as for outs down from theirfront
front opponents or low driving from thehook
hook players opposed to them The frontirntre
irntre stands about three yards or rathermore
more beyond the crease and has a greatrally
rIlll of the play this pet la therefore genrally
rally taken by the best player The rightnd
And left backs have a good deal of runningshout
bout but should be welt able to coverwe
we whole of their respective areas Whenw
N feet bya fcgt rgtlrts are UMaJoblee backIt
VJultt 1ffTtl1 tTn t rl I
UiI Rl
1 t I I I
layers aro sometimes put In I e six aside
but with courts of lawn tennis size three
bark players are rather apt to get in oneanothers
anothers way
The game II 20 up The first service
of each player la from the right court Into
the opiwnentH right court then from the
loft Into the left each player going In in
turn While serving the right and left
front can change places for the time being
with tho front centre but If they are Indiffermoro
Nit player and the front centre good It 1Mmoro
moro unual for the change to bo betweenthemselves
themselves only the back players shouldchange
change places far the alternate servesback
The service has to bo underhand Expert
back Players can Indulge in n rood dealof
of hard hitting without ever hitting but of
bounds very high service to the backof
of the court and low sharp serves or returns
turns just over the pet aimed at the frontplayers
players In India some players had a very
effective screw service to the back of hitcourt
court but those serve do not puzzle unexpert
expertLawn
Lawn tennis racquets are used by tliemen
men but the women prefer badminton
bats With good plovers the ball In rarely
missal ut tho beck of the oourt and seldom
killed from that quarter When a frontplayer
player nets u fairly high ball he triM tocut
cut It down for n kill but with expert playerstneao
these cuts are very often returned as easilyas
as they are In the shuttlecock game hongrnllifw
rallies are frequent and marked by fiiiocutting
cutting by the front players lawn tennisand
and Bhuttlerock players noon become cxpert
pert but they are apt at first to hit outnf
boundsHie
The women players make the ballH used
In India a requisite being that they shouldnot
not only fly easily to the end of tho oourtbut
but be easily hit out They make the ballson
on two round cards cut to the size of asherrv
sherrv glass with u circular holt in theiti
middle the size of 0 sixpence Berlin woolill
ill then wound round and round until it canno
no longer grass through the iviitre holethe
the wool la then out all round and a Ionicpiece
piece of whipcord lnnerted between thecards
cards This Is drawn very tight and doubly
knotted wound round again several timesand
and knotted niriiin several times ThisKives
gives weight to the centre of tho ball whichhas
has then to III clipped with a sharp sciiworsto
to a circumference of 6K Inches Ordinarybadminton
badminton bulls Mill not do as they willnot
not flv to the end of the courtWith
With ten good players ball badmintonIH
IH really a splendid game and very exciting
to watch to again quota the ColonelThe
The difficulty Is to get together ten goodplovers
plovers the chief drawback being that aduffer
duffer or two on either side spoil the gameIt
It would lie a splendid game for all out doorclubs
clubs and for large garden parties as eachgame
game only lasts about twenty minutesoften
often lena and taken in BO many playersIt
It may be mentioned that any attempt toplay
play In a full sized or even lawn tennis sizedfnnrt
fnnrt without a front centre result In afailure
failure There must I e three front playersA
A game of four u side can however beplayol
played In a narrower court and In U stillsmaller
smaller court games of two a side onefront
front and one back or even singles can beplaved
played but in these smaller courts greatskill
skill and practice are required to keep theball
hall within limit tyros always hitting outHadmlnton
badminton teams have to practise a littletogether
together before they really excel This Ishowever
however only the question of a few gamesThe
The game may be claused as an easy oneand
and mon learned Elderly jxsonle who arenot
not active enough to attempt lawn tenniscan
can occupy tho position of right or leftfronts
frontsIn
In the dearth of pastimes at the countryclulm
clubs as a change from golf and lawn tennisthere
there may be a place for ball badminton Inthis
this country If it Is introduced there willnoon
noon be no lack of good players men andwomen
women Aside from India it Is now onlyployed
played on the lawns of a few old Indianwho
who have returned to EnglandJAPAX I1tPA</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/2023271000/1945-03-30/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Badminton Flashes
The Depot Officer’s Badminton
Tourney, entering its final stages,
is predicted to vind-np in true
■ports-novel fash:on. Leading con
tenders toward the coveted Depot
Championship are: Lt. Comdr.
Salters (who, be-ause of his clev
erness. covers less ground than is
normally traveled in palying); Lt.
TTakan (young, fast and astute
placing); Lt. (jg) Van Burkirk
(cunning and a terrific smash);
Lt. (.jg) Fmery fartful employer
of tricks and strategems). The
overall Badminton make-up of
Lt’s. Emery and Van Buskirk
'cads vour sports scr'be to believe
that the championship game will
find one and the other face to face
m one of the fastest and shrewdest
badminton plays ever staged at
the Depot. Championship game
will he played Monday. April 2nd
at the Perm. Rec. (1700).
NOQ-PT. Not to be out-done
and. a medium of exercise and rec
reation for themselves, the pretty
little madir'ens of NOQ too have
enlisted their athletic abilties
toward effecting a Badminton
Tourney. The month of April will
find NOQ Badminton Tourney en
thusiasts in full combat regalia
contesting for top position in a
Badminton Ladder Tourney.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1891-10-04/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Champion Badanlatoa Tennla Playara,
Th Badminton lawn tennla axpert yesterday mo
eeeded In capturing both of the sterling silver trophies
In th recently formed Inter-Club Tennis Association of
King county. The scoresi
Gentlemen' Single Flnt round: B, IV Booecek,
Knickerbocker Field Club, forfeited to A. 8. Mertam,
Badminton Tennis Club; Dr. W.N. Fraser. King County
Tennis Club, beat B. 8. Ueltcamp, Altlora" Tennis Club,
e 8, ft 0; E. L. Heltrarap, Altlora T. C, beat A. Fransl
ola, Knickerbocker Field: Club, 82, 84: C. E. Mao
Mabon, Badminton T. C, beat A. G. McGowan. King
County T. C, 84. 80; A. 8. Merlam, Badminton T.
C, beat Dr. B.O. Fraser, Kings County T. C, 03, 08,
78.
Second Round K. L. Ileltkatnp, Altlora T. 0, beat O.
E. MacMabon. Badminton, T. O. 76. 88: A. 8. Mer
lam, Badminton. T. C, beat Dr. B, 0, Fraxer, Kings
County T. C tt-4, 68. 7-6.
Final Round A. 8. Merlam, Badminton T. C, defeated
L. lleltkamp. Alt.ora T. C. 0-0. 7-6, 82.
Gentlemen' Double, First Round E. H. Payne and
H. E. McGowan, King County T. C. beat E. L. llelt
kamp and H. B. lleltkamp. ARortaT. C, 8-8, 6-3: A.
8. Merlam and C. E. MarMahon. Badminton T. C. beat
K.H.Lou and Harry Wall. Knickerbocker Field Club,
fl 01; Harry rranclola and William Boocock.
Knickerbocker Field Club, beat J. 8, Jones and John U.
Rollins, Altlora T. C..H-0. 68,81; Dr. R.O. Prater
and F. M, Pendrelgh. Kings County T. C beat Dr. V. A.
Griffiths and O. N. Hchmtdt, BadmlntonT. C, 8-2, 8-0.
Heeond Round E. M. Payne and II. E. McOowan.
Kings County T. C were beaten by A. S. Merlam and C,
R. MacMabon. Badminton T.C., O 2. 2-fl, 0-4: Harry
Pransclola and William Boocock, Knickerbocker Field
Club, were defeated by Dr. W. N. Fraser and F, M. Pen
drelgh, Kings County T. C, 8-8, rt-O.
Final Round Dr. Prater and F. M. Fendrelgb. King
County T. c., were beaten by A. 8. Merlam and c E.
MacMabon, Badmldton T. C 13-11. 810, 67, 0-1,
68.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/2023271000/1945-04-06/ed-1/?sp=7&q=Badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Officers’ Badminton
Flashes!
The Depot Officers’ Badminton
Tournament, dosing in at the
home-stretch, finds Lt’s. Hakan,
Van Buskirk and Emery vying for
top honors. The extenuating cir
cumstances of annual leave, etc.,
effects a brief postponement of
the semi-final and championship
games which will be played the
11th and 13th of April instead of
the pre-designated date of April
2nd. The winner of the April 11th
Badminton game, played by Lt’s.
Hakan and Van Buskirk, will de
ploy, employ and decoy his Bad
minton generalship against the
well “seasoned” Lt. Emery April
13th, Perm. Rec. (1700) to deter
mine the Depot Officer Badminton</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/2023271000/1945-03-16/ed-1/?sp=7&q=Badminton</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>OFFICERS’ BADMINTON
TOl'RNEY
The Badminton “craze” is in the
air—strong indication of this is
the wholesale and constant use of
the Badminton facilities provided
in the Perm. Rec. Participants in
the Officers’ Badminton Tourna
ment—beginning today—1630, at
Safety match? with ex
plosives! -Don't be silly!
the Perm. Rec., approximate more
than tiie anticipated number.
More than 20 Depot Officers will
compete during the month of
March, to determine the Depot
Officers’ Badminton Champion.
Lost and Found</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-building-titanic/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1908-04-23/ed-1/?sp=1&q=White+Star+line</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1908-10-02/ed-1/?sp=9&q=White+Star+line&st=text&r=-0.22,-0.072,1.44,1.44,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>spective 80000 tonn tonnars the Titanic and andOlympic andhmpfc andt
Olympic OlympicThe t ilympicThe hmpfcThe
The Mauretanla and Lusitania of not notmuch notmuch notmuch
much more than half ha1 the proposed proposedcrafts propo proposedcrafts ed edrafts
crafts tonnage have no more room roomthan roomtllan roomthan
than they need to get through the theAmbrose theAmbroee theAmbrose
Ambrose channel and Into the Mersey Merseynt
nt tt t Liverpool LiverpoolThe LiverpoolThe LiverpoolThe
The popular opinion here Is that a avessel afssel avessel
vessel of 0600 tons would have to todo tod tolo
do d Its loading and unloading at sea seaMarine 3eLlarlne seaMarine
Marine statisticians stati tJdans have figured that thatthe thattite
I
the t he tonnage of the e entire Spanish ar arnada armada armada
mada of 129 l ships ships which tried to land landan landn
an n army In England in Queen Eliza Elizabeths EJlzahetbs Elizabeths
beths reign was only 50139 50139Considerable 58139Considerable 13 13Considerable
Considerable progress is being made madewith madewith madewith
with construction work on the Olym Olympic Olympic Olympie
pic In Harland Wolffs yard at atBelfast atBElrut atBelfast
Belfast but the Titanic keel blocks blockswill blockswill l lwill
will not be laid until January JanuaryFIREMEN JanuaryFIREMEN i</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1909-01-03/ed-1/?sp=59&q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>his aantry cost $\COO,COO. It was erected fop the express purooie of corstructinn the two new
White Star steamships, Olympic and Titanic.
first day he en
lists with a big wrecking
j bi
r fai
all the professions 1 v T
hnman Hf
making, is aa dang roue aa the one o!
n wno
brave storm ;randed "liner," I I
greyhound." to rescue the ship Imi I
if nothing else, to salv what val
n iy be removed from h
wrecks meet death by the score. Many of 1
often for d ys and :::chis to
blasts to driving blizzards ana
irmt that bit< to the marrow.
at wo

.r..,i rations of rei
masts or of slinging wrecking pumps oi
_. s that v., i others have
ii hai these mu?l
amputated And I tp nrr- wiped out of
told agony
a; .1 Kposure b* >tp the a of 0 elr I
8. -Applet The steamers whose keel blocks haT»
I been laid side by side in this the biggest gantry
j In the world are the Titanic and th« Olympic, of
the White Star Line, and within a year or two
I these leviathans will b« running between New Tori*
and Southampton.
Soon after the two fast Cunarders. too Lusl-
I taria and the Mauretania, had demonstrated that
I one could travel in luxury and at a very high
i speed through tha agency of turbine engines. th«
White Star X-in» announced that it would build
two steamers to beat the Oinarders la length and
breadth, and perhaps In other ways also. It was
reported at the tim» that th« new Whlta Star
liners would be a thousand feet in length, but sub
sequently it was officially announced that they
i would bo 900 feet lons, with a beam of ninety feet.
j When It was decided to build them it was found
that there was no gantry In thm world big enough
to accommodate such monsters, and It was then
that H&rland Wolff began to rip up three of Its
largest gantries and build the hug* steel and con
crete cradle that Is now ready to bold th* Olympic
and the Titanic.
Before th* steel structure which supports th*
i powerful electric travailing cranes was erected a
big concrete base, twenty fret thick, was built upon
sp!le3 driven fifty fe«t into tha ground. The con
crete foundation, in addition to being more firm
than the regular earthen base, has the advantage
of cleanliness, an 1 tools and materials which mar
fall from the cranes la the course of construction
may be found more readily. Parts of deck fittings
end tools have fallen into the ground la gantries
with earth bases and have not been recovered
until the vessel has gilded from Its cradle into the
water.
The construction of the Olympic has been started.
The keel of the Titanic will be laid soon, and
visitors to the shipyards at Belfast will have an
opportunity of seeing the simultaneous csnstrcs
tion. side by side, of the largest two steamers tn
the world. The gantries are so built that any
piece of material, however heavy or awkward, may
be placed and held In whatever position the con
atructora desire. The gantries themselves are more
than a thousand feet in length. 3C3 feet high and
something more than two hundred feet la -KiX
T</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1909-05-30/ed-1/?sp=59&q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Titanic and the Olympic W3l
lie Largest Steamships in World.
Although what will be the largest two steamships
In the world, the Titanic and the Olympic, of the
White Star Line, are mere skeletons just now in
their Lie million-dollar double gantry at Belfast,
Ireland the marine architects know exactly bow
they are going to look when they start on their
maiden passage to this port. From the plans and
specifications the designers have made a wush
drawing showing bow 'he monsters will look when
In the water and ready to sail. Although at nrst
glance the illustration suggests the Isauretania and
Lusitania. with their four gigantic funnels, there
Is something in the appearance of the new levia
thans that Is typical of a White Star steamship.
The great height of the new liners and the broad
sweep of the bridge elves some idea of their 80.J80
tons displacement. The builders have almost elimi
nated the old cusr im of carying masts, «nd In this
respect the targesi ships in the world resemble the
Old Dominion steamers, tha smallest passenger
carrying vessels in the American coastwise service.
All the old Dominior Mners have only one mast.
g the 1
;i' i Titanic.
Thrse two vessels are being built simultaneously
sid* by side In a steel gantry that was begun a
year before the keels were laid, and which cost
over a million dollars. The new liners will each
n«» S» feet long, with 92-foot beam. The unusual
beam la equivalent to the length of some of the
fast utenrn yachts of this port. The Olympic and
Titanic will iw» read] for the New York. South
ampton an.i Cherbourg *»*r\ im of the White Star
IJne in 1911. The builders are Harland a Wolff.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn93063916/1910-01-08/ed-1/?sp=1&q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE WORLDS LARGEST VESSEL VESSELTHE VESSELTHE ESSEIJTHE
THE TITANIC NOW NO BEING BUILT
Here la an architectural picture of the steamship Titanic which Is being beingbuilt beingbunt beingbuilt
built for the White Star line at Belfast also a view of the giant steel cradle cradleiu
iu which the ship Is being constructed The keel of the steamship Is seen in inthe inthe inthe
the lower photograph The White Star company Is to have two of these theselaviathans theselebtthans theseleviathans
leviathans and they will be In commission early in 1911 Their launching launchingwill
will UI signalize a most important era in marine achievement for they will be bobyc beby beby
byc byctil by all odds the largest vessels in the world The Titanic and Olympic will willench wUlh willeach
each h be SCO feet f t in length 92 feet beam 45000 tons register and GOOOO tons tonsdisplacement tonsdl tonsdlstixccnwnt
displacement dl Ilem nt These enormous dimensions are best expressed In comparl comparlS
30115 S The Washington Va hlngton monument is r x55 55 5 feet high and the Metropolitan tower towerlit
lit New Xt York rliy r f ity rises TOO feet Tbe combined tonnage tonnn e of tbe Olympic Olympicand OIrJ11pllukl
and Tlrxink k far fn r exceeds the tonnage ton n e of all It II the vrbs vessels tssl els ls engaged pn n ngld tM1 on both bothskies bothkles bothskies
skies In the hlsi hI Irlt rl conflict of the Spanish armada HfuJ dn Hud nd It Is even more In Interesting Inttresrln inttirestinx
teresting to know ihir t t the Santa Maria was only em I rIt ii 0 feet fi Plat i t Ions IOll a and d 233 tons tonsvet tonhtnhn tonelnirien
htnhn t vet tat nn thl visw yf f 4r1 1 Columbus Journeyed TO th thp new UP world</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1910-01-23/ed-1/?sp=14/&q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86058226/1912-04-10/ed-1/?sp=1&q=titanic+titantic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TITANTIC SAILS ON
HER FIRST VOYAGE
White Star Liner the Largest
Vessel that Ever Sailed
the Seas.
(National News Association)
LONDON, April 10. Carrying 1400
passengers the liner Titanic of the
White Star line, than which there is
no larger vessel afloat, sailed from
Southhampton today on her maiden
voyage bound for New York. The Tt
tanic which is of 45,000 tons displace
ment Is sister ship to the Olympic.
All the special suites of rooms in
stituted as an innovation in the Titan
ic were occupied when the passage be
gun. These suites consist of bed
rooms, sitting room, bath room, and
servant's room and have their own
private deck promenade isolated from
the rest of the ship and not overlooked
by any other passengers.
The Titanic also possesses another
new feature in its Louis XVI. restaur
ant. Her sister ship the Olympic, also
has this feature but on a smaller
scale. It proved so popular, however,,
that the White Star company decided
to have Jhe one on the Titanic greatly
enlarged. Adjacent to it is a special
reception room for the use of passen
gers taking meals in the restaurant.
The Titanic while its engineering
principal is the same as that of the
Olympic, is expected by experts on
navigation to make faster time than
the Olympic because of a slight dif
ference in the curvature of the propel
ler blades.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1910-07-11/ed-1/?sp=3&q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Titanic Will Be Handsomest
Vessels Afloat.
LiOMSTER.S OF 45.000 TONS
tvrert Says There Is No Reason
'•'■■7 They Should Not. Be
x Ha-^ ec Praise
fin Americans.
Vs rt r VT ah!*' "Alexander M Car
'~*r r*""e^2^ 'Tir'l— Of the big shipbuild-.
i r-r Z Harlassd Wolff, at Belfast.
r%r^*£T.d probably the most prominent
|g!Swj) constructor in Great Britain, ar-
T^an yesterday en the .Whit* Star
»T^ r, of the vessels "which grew
*F, o^servatioti in the Belfast yards.
i-T^ •"s-i-t bssb Bf about sixty, and has
.**^i-v tie Crsa he represents for forty;
**^~~ezzs According c his friends he is
f: _.."- talks little, but. thinks much.
s .rCl crpt-ired —1? yesterday when he
j^**^v V about the new-, theusand-fect
c t2.r eiants that are seen to leave
Kr^,;^ Vt Belfast
-vT~s -=thir.g at all to say." said Mr
fejjsie iSraptly. tm not S" c to talk
S-TsSlps What "have" I com© over- for"
W--V2 SStle trip and the salt baths.
rcirg right back en the Oceanic on
VfeSaai
jri-ec t-"- e £e2 waase at Belfast was
J.. r -«t £5 coed se the salt water of the
r, J^ r of Vfeew York, Mr Carlisle replied
s'-spese S! But you see I came over to
2*iitt2s» at sea: to get the sea air
%i tie salt t-stis or. board the Celtic"
Cr tie tie bay Carlisle clung
v^c^v remark that he -would not
T ,v ajjsst ships, but he asksd many ques
.j.,., ibbct tie harbor and the cutters that
aX tie Celtic By degress v,«, warmed up
7. -_;* cibject o* stear^ship construction, to
•rt^zz. he hsi obßd his life, and declared
£2* Clynplc and Titanic would but*
p^serSsenr ark -"--er- they cams here in
3£-
..-tv, -»--rk or these big Etfiaisshlps is
rilTor. right and day," he "said,
-j "wd have the Olympic ready for
jssciis October Nothing can com
t--c with zs.ezz. in si;* and beauty You
rZI zit z. reflation. In rocm a^d decoratics
xtn. tbese -'cssels cc=s to >*e-v York."
BiiMd bet PsMio Wants.
yz- bs^evs *-ii:<*iz.r BBC* iarjre
£-=silps-
-Te. I SJ:- reascr Thy great liners
£oulc zct be Mscstreeted if the travelling
jcil;c is Tilling tc pay for transpertaticn
~ij?e they net aswSeSfiy lather hard to
-t-A »r v PT» retti g 1 pert?"
v. _.. replied >Xr. Carlisle, with
••c r-■"■;'---"r of a. frown. '"With --i
*—c~j'^ rzzszes can s^'ir.^ big liner
jj-mrfl ""rtth ease. Quadruple screws are
zz rrzzztr advantage As long as you
izTr ewe big propellers 90s can hand:?- s
blr siip. is net a a-uestior of the num
ber of prrpeilers. bat the depth they are
the waxes They must have solid water
w •'•ori In You know- 1 cannot always
-_..- £i:ps as we would like to build
r-.err. We ia--e tc b-uild the^n according to
*i£ depth cf the harbors they are re enter
I ■_-...-.: good ark has been done with the
■sr.:r:: Channel at ..this port. You
Ancri;ar:s are able people, and you can
"Ct--arythi^g yoa set your minds upon.- If
ysc wsat ships, are will build them

'"To ywa believe in high speed like that
cf the Ururetar-ia 1 the Losaftaals
"That again is a Question for Che travel-
Utg pibSc If people. "want to travel
fist they rinst expect to- pay for travelling
::_r. The Olympic and the Titanic will
zzve 2. sp^ed of ti ■cue knots That
is rzzi iced for large ships. Ycu will
rse sc~e rc-sm those vessels The
rt^tfcrsoms -'-'111 be unusually large, ezsd
tier will te as abundance of room every
■"•isre. Fir example, we win have an ex
c^zzzliy large room off the. dining Bar
tons T-ie-r* people may meet before din-
Sar bold receptlcns. The decoration?
Till be unsurpassed They will be the
frsr tliit money can buy They will not
s^rc bs the most magnificent, bui they
Tin i« th most substantial and solid that
«-ver -J-ere put tote a steamship."
If- Carlisle laughed when asked -what
isiarii cf the big Huropa. which the Hsm
lur?-American Lin© had contracted for
ti-rtly bifcirp- the recent financial panic in
Tiev 2.r^ to have s. Sn? new vessel,"* he
f-ii* Kf an exceptionally big typ* Hsrr
Altrt Eallin. of the Hamburg-Am«*rican
lise, is 'd. marvellous nan He know? the
Ft^cnsiir. business He has done big
"rlrps, ar.d vQ] continue to fin big things.
-fe 'Z th© best, ■ad I understand one of
Tzzrt profitable and popular, BtaMneb*ns
"tf~The Hamburg-American L'r:"=- is the
-a-hich -i-ec. built several years
in cur yards st Belfast.
Ciyrrcic Launching in the Fa!!.
Aricfci when the Olympic and the Titanic
"•xeli visit tbea»«atan Mr C^rliEl* said.
win launch The Olympic in October
tzi she should be in service in tbe middle
r ISCi. The vessels are so large and there
t'j much to be done an them after the
hww^fag that they car.not be sent out be-;
f-.-* that time the Titanic will probably
ft ready MSI three or four months after
Olympic sails on her maiden passage
"*-'.i6 is the first vacation Mr Carlisle has
h;f in three years. The work at th*- yards
its kept him there constantly since his
rir!t here res years ap» He pointed to
t-.'j Brooklyn Bridge on the way -up bay
remarked that he went across it on
th. strands while it was in ceur?e
c! ccrstricticn. He expressed great Inter
the railroad terminal facilities in this
fcty, tnfl stewed much praise on the 3c
*«ssraLtton and ability of Americans He
f *Slss oat .IP Morgan as on* of -Assert-.
c ?reir men, who invariably did that
"^iJcS hf. kd planned to do
rz'r* raofat than 7*i,V^ tons in ccurs*
wtstructtoji at Belfaßt,*" he said, "and
.t Ere -r- unusually busy ICe one
lies ths great amount of work required
bc!ld such big steamships 5? the
zr.i the Olympic. rbere only
European
Visitors
npiran Columns
\i -York Tribune
a reliable £uidc to the best
Ebops, hotels and resorts.
Consult These Columns
Before Sailing
much valuable time will
be "saved for sightseeing.
sea ■"•a- q r£t 6ve 2 fairt rr3 of it,
that Is for one to visit the yards.
To. Be Things of Bsauty.
too. the average person cannot
understand the tremendous amount of
ac-sey put Into ta« decoration Only an
■TOM or an architect can know the real
fceautv or understand the time and the
money required to make the interior* of
the big ships. Thus far there- I? hardly
anything that caa surpass the decorations
OB the Mauritania Be patient and watch
few the decorations on the. Olympic."
air. Carlisle -was employed at the Eel
35- yards when the first Oceanic of the
hit* Star Line was launched. When the
second Oceanic, now in port, was launched
MS left the -ways under hi? direction.
The Olympic and Titanic -will be 4S*V
ton vessels. They in called "thcusand
foof ships, but their length win be MO
fee* The new Hamburg: American liner
hot- under construction at Stettin will be
S?6 feet, -with a tonnage of 45. W. The
Msure-tar.ia. and the LuEitania are each
feet in length with a tonnage of 32.500
When it was announced last month in
London that the great docks -would be
constructed en the Mersey the Ctmard
L;?.!, it is said, planned to construct new
liters of 60.060 tons.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1911-05-31/ed-1/?sp=5&q=titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MONSTEB LINER LAUNCHED.
Steamer Titanic Slides Into Water
at Belfast.
BELFAST, May .11.?Enthusiastic
crowds lined the banks of the River
lStar line's great steamer Titanic was
launched with appropriate ceremonies
this morning.
The Titanic will enter the White Star's
New York-Soutl^ampton service late in
the year, but her sister vessel Olympic
steams from Southampton two weeks
hence for New York, and these two sea
monsters, each 45,000 tons register,
882Vt feet long and 92 H fo*t broad,
boast the distinction of being the
largest and finest, vessels in the world
These massive ships are also notable
for the enchanting beauty and the un
usual spaciousness of their passenger ac
commodations, and in first, second and
third class the greatest comfort is prom
ised. On both steamers swimming pools,
tennis and hand ball courts, and Turkish
and electric bath establishments ars
among the Innovations introduced for the
pleasure of the passengers.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86086633/1912-04-03/ed-1/?sp=1&q=titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TITANIC'S MAIDEN TRIP.
Sister Ship to the Olympic of White
Star Line Snls Next Week.
Lorn! on, April The gigantic new
st Mam-ship Titanic of thr White Star
line arrive. todoy at Setithamptt n
from the MinN of her bulkiers at H-l-
fast. She is to be marie re.iriy for herj
maitlen trip across the Atlantl the
atnri al ertotch la scheduled for sVed.
Oaaday af next week. The Titanic is a
sister ship to the Olympic. 8he Is 0
leet hmg and has a d b placement of
r.o 000 tons. The travellmr Ust n the
bb ship will have coo names "Hi its
brt lass roll, in addition to 500 BOO
ot l i lass and third cabin oa
sengt ts. To this will be adder, the
n v oi sua makina a t ui tlo.tiiiK
pojsilatlon of mir1y t.ooe.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014248/1912-04-18/ed-1/?sp=12&q=Titanic&st=text&r=-0.223,-0.072,1.447,1.447,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>name appeared anion;:
the list of Titanic passengers, but was
missing from the list of survivors, wa
u native of this city and f.t* years old.
He is a nephew of General A. B
Fainhi.m of Bangor. He is a brother of
William Kent, a New York architect.
Mrs. Harry K. White of Brookline,
Mass., and Miss Charlotte Kent of
Buffalo.
Now York, April 17.—That Henry B.
Harris, the theatrical manager, is not
among the Titanic survivors in th
Carpathia, is shown by a message re
ceived. late today, at the Hudson thea
ter from Mrs. Henry H. Harris, his
wife, who, with Mr. Harris, was on
board the Titanic. Mrs. Harris' name
luis appeared on the list ot the saved.
The message came from the steamer
Carpathia by way of Halifax and said:
■•Am safe. Praying that Harry has
been picked up by another steamer.
Arrive Carpathia. Rena."
New Bedford, Mass., April 17.
Frank D. Millett, the artist, who was
aboard the Titanic and whose name
does riot appear on the list of surviv
ors. had been engaged to paint the
mural decorations for the new publii
library in this city. The painting
were to depict scenes of the days when
the whaling industry of New Bedford
was at its height. Mr. Millett had no
tified the library trustees ttiat his
sketches were complete and that he
would bring them back from Kurop
on the Titanic. The artist fomierl;.
lived in Mattapolsett, a few miles from
New Bedford.
New York, April 17.—An investiga
tion has been made of the report cur
rent, yesterday, that Charles M. Hays,
president of the Grand Trunk Rail
way, was among the survivors of the
Titanic. The name of Mr. Hays does
not appear in any list of survivors
The dispatch in question saying Mr
Hays was among the survivors was
first published in Montreal.
Mrs. Charles M. Hays and her
daughter Margaret. are reported
among the survivors on board the Car
pathia.
London, April 17.—The list of pur
vtvors of the Titanic disaster, as giv
en out by the White Star offices here,
contains the names of both Mr. am
Mrs. Jacques Futrelle of Boston. Pre
vious lists published here contained
the name of Mrs. Futrelle only. An
other new name appearing on the list
of second class passengers is that ol
Miss Finney. The name of Charles M
Hays, president of the Grand Trunk
Railway, does not appear on the list
here.
New York. April 17.—A wireless was
received, today, bv relatives of -Mrs.
Kdgar Meyer, daughter of the late
Andrew Saks, reporting that she is
among the survivors on board the Car
pathia. Her name has not been in
cluded in the list of survivors. Her
husband, who is vice president of tlu
Braden Copper Co., was not rescued.
The wireless message from the t'ar
pathia, via Halifax, is not signed and
reads.
"Leela safe, well cared for. Kdgar
missing.”
Mrs. Meyer’s father died a few days
ago and she was coming to New York
to be with her mother.
Among the first cabin passengers on
the ill fated Titanic wnose name has
not been accounted for is R. W. Smith
who was connected with a large tee
importing firm in London, Eng. Mr
Smith had made many trips to the
1'nited States and had many friendt
in the tea business in this country.
Niles, Ohio, April 17. -William f’lerk
of this city, today, received a messagt
forwarded from Halifax, telling him
that his wife, who was returning from
France on board the Titanic, was safe
on board the Carpathla. Mrs. Clark
was accompanied by her one-year-old
boy.
Cleveland. April 17.—Another version
of the message received by H W.
Honnell at New1 York from his sis
ter, Miss Caroline Honnell, a Titanic
survivor, was received here It read:
“All women saved on board Carpa
thla. George lost.''
This was understood to mean that
Miss Honnell, her aunt. Mrs. George
Wick, another aunt, Miss Elizabeth
Donnell, and a cousin. Miss Mary
Natalie Wick, were safe and that an
uncle. George Wick, went down with
the Titanic. Caroline Honnell and
Maly Wick had previously been ac
counted for. All are from Youngs
town, Ohio.
San Antonio, Texas. April 17. 1C.
H. Reynolds, a theatrical mun, here,
reports that his only sister. Miss
Edith Doris Reynolds was among the
Titanic's passengers. Shi was engaged
to marry H. C. Jones, secretary to
the British ambassador to China Her
name does not appear in the list of
refugees
Montreal, April 17. Arrangements
are being made hen- for a joint me
morial service for the victims of the
Titanic by the various denominations
of the Protestant churches here. The
dates of the set vice have not been
fixed yet.
*u!t I.uke City, L'laii. April 17.
Mrs. Irene Corbett, who was a pas
senger on the Titanic, is the daugh
ter of Bishop Devi A. Colvin of Provo.
I’tah. Her name does not appear
among the survivors. Her father re
ceived a letter from her. yesterday
saying she would be home, next
week
Baltimore. April 17.—A wlrelesf
message received, today, from ihi
Carpethla. to her mother in this city
announced the safety of Mrs. Wil
liam E. Carter, her husband and two
children, w no were passengers of tie
T tanic The Carters live In Philadel
phia.
ertej City, April 17 Frederick
o To Your Doctor
T? Want more hair? An elegant dressing?
iiir. Glycerin. Quin in. Sodium Chlorid.
cum. Sage. Alcohol. Water. Perfume.
li% or wc would not put it up.
LOR THE HAIR
My, Lowell, Maws.
Myles of this city received a tele
pram, today, from his sister, .Mis.
Jertrude Myles, at Cambridge, Mass
which says: Papa sailed on the Ti
tanic. Safe on the Carpathia. All
well. Their father, Thomas F Myl.i
of Cambridge, has been in the em
ploy of the White Star Idne years
On account of poor wireless condi
tions, the process of sending was slow,
and the names had to be repeated
many times. After a portion of th
list had been sent, the Salem was
heard transmitting a message to the
Chester directing her to stop sending
for a while. This was understood to
be on account of the Interference I
the Chester's wireless apparatus with
the efforts of the Carpathia to com
municate with shore stations.
CONGRESS TAKES ACTION.
(Continued from Page One.)
inittec.
The House committee on merchant
murine will speedily take up the many
bills and resolutions which have been
introduced bearing on the Titanic dis
aster. Representative Alexander of
Missouri, chairman of the committee,
introduced two resolutions, today.
One would direct the President to in
vite the maritime nations of the
world to appoint members of an in
ternational commission to definie ship
lanes an 1 routes and to minimize the
dangt r of collisions at sea The other
would extend a similar invitation to
nations interested in North Atlantic
steamship travel to form a commis
sion to arrange for a patrol of North
Atlantic waters to warn ships.
Rep. Sulzer of New York, chairman
of the foreign relations committee, of
fered a Joint resolution Identical with
the Senate resolution introduced by
Perkins. The Perkins-Sulzer provis
ions would require one life preservt r
for each person aboard. They would
also make it a felony for any cap
tain, executive officer or resident gen
eral agent of a corporation actual!
charged with control, management,
operation, equipment or navigation of
ocean vessels knowingly to permit a
vessel to sail from any part of the
I nited States without full life saving
equipment. The penalty would be im
prisonment at hard labor for let
more than lu years.
spector general of the steamboat in
spection service, expressed the vie"',
today, that much good could be ac
complished by ap. international con
gress to consider life-saving ap
pliances. He suit! that there was it"
action that his department could take
in the Titanic case in view of the fact
that the vessel was of foreign reg
ister complying with the British nav
igation law s.
List of the Third
Class Passengers.

Portland, Me., April 17.—The follow
ing list of third elass passengers and
crew rescued from the wrecked steam
ship Titanic by the Carpathia was re
ceived by wireless, tonight:
The list of survivors among the third
lass or s teerage pass "lgers was sent
from the Carpathia to the scout cruis
er Chester, which relayed the names
to the Salem to lie relayed again to
the commandant of the naval station
at Newport, R. 1. It was picked up by
a wireless operator here as the Ches
ter sent it. The list:
THIRD CLASS PASSENGERS.
Arno Ludguis, Nora Murphy, Katie
Muliin, Katie McCarthy, G. D. Mcs
semock, Anna Messemock, Mantera
Yusefa, Buros Moubarck, Halin Mou
barck, Glros Moubarck, Amina Mussul
inona, Fatuea Submaket, Hannah Mun,
Krikorean Muhum, Delia McDelmolit,
Karl Mathyo, Bertha Mallieoilla. Mag
gie Merrigan, Bertha Maran, Kristol
Madsen, Albert Moss, Mary McGovern,
Margaret Marigan, Elleonch Bare.
Maggie J- Murphy, Afina McGowan,
Agnes McKoy, Ernest McKoy, Alice Me
Jvoy, Thomas McCarmlck, John Nickaran,
Adele Naraon, Bertha Nelson, Mary Nek
et. Hclminu J. Nelson, Anna Nyhen,
Helena Ongulen, Anna Kolshuttel, Nora
O’Lerry, Arthur Olsen, Ooterina Patras,
Nobesa Patras, Genoit Picard, Ernest
Person, Nat as Both, Anna Heir bon, John
Chuensson, Nicola Sulici, Juho Strinder,
Jan Sehurbint, Jules Sap, Anna Solia,
Beirice Sinde, Hose Sibelrome, Agnes Si
belrome, Amy Stanley, Johan Sumdman,
Falla Smythe, Axel Shine.
Florence Keaorny, Croft Hedvig,
'ledvig Turkula, William Turkgest,
Vartauon, 10lien Wlckes, Siline Yes
burg, Hanna Yousef, George Yousef,
Marian Yousef. Scurly Oumson. Philip
Zenrt, Nicola Eliase, Nicola Oanb, Au
gust Abrihamson. Bedngijra Aloun,
Mariania Assim, Carlo Nelson, Cander
son Osplumd, John Charles. Rosa Ab
bott. Erna Aneerson, Selma Astlund,
Lillian Aatlund, Felix Astlund, Aklsesp
Abelseph, Leak Aksaks, Filly Aksaks,
Lee Bing, Marie Boklin, Eugene Hoklin,
Haline Boklin, Latefe Boklin, Nassif
’avern. Boyam Casern.
Emily Batman, Marla Bockstrom, Dan
iel Buckley. Bridget Bradley, Thing Hip.
Einure Barlson, Beatrice Sande, Gus Co
hen, L. M. Cribb, Minnie Conto, Nevelle
Ton to, Will (’onto, Katie Connolly. Ellen
Carr, Theodore Demueder, Jos. Krigesne.
P B. Daly, Charles Daly, Marsola Daly.
Mrs Ettie Dean and two children, Mar
garet Devanev, Hose Bridget.
One hundred and eighteen names
had been relayed to Newport to Salem
when static conditions became such
’hat it was practical!v impossible for
the Newport operator to get the names.
For this reason the operator on the
cruiser suspended tor a time to resume
later it conditions became better, it
D understood that the Salem has prac
tically a complete list of the third
abin passengers, as well as the mem
bers of the erew, who were saved.
All on the Carpathias
Montreal, April 17.—Manager Han
nah *,t tAllan Line received, this
afternoon, the following message from
the captain of th« Parisian.
far »*s I know, all the survivors
of the Titanic are aboard the Tar pa
th ia.”
RECOVERY IMPOSSIBLE.
Expert Says Bodies of the Victims Are
In the Deep Forever.
Baltimore, April IT.—The bodlrs <>f
the victims of the Titanic disaster are
at the bottom of the deep, never to
leave t, said Prof. Robert \Y Wood,
of the chair of experimental physics at
Johns Hopkins University, today.
"It is altogether improbable that any
of the corpses will ever return to the
surface of the water, as is tiie case
with bodies drowned in shallow water.
"At the depth of two miles, the pres
sun of the water is something like
fiiVki pounds to the square inch, which
is far too great to be overcome by
buoyancy ordinarily given drowned
bodies by the gases that are generated
in time.
“That the bodies sank to the bottom
of the sea. there is no question." he
continued. "The Titanic's victims who
wire not carried down with the boat
followed until the very bottom of the
sea was reached. There was no such
tiling as their stopping in their down
ward course a half mile, a mile or at
iov other point. Great changes have
never necessarily been wrought in the
vessel itself by the enormous pressure
to which it has been subject. No ef
fect was produced on any portion, or
compartment or room to whose inside
as well as outside walls the water had
access in such instances the pressure
from one side neutralises that from
tiie other.
"Rui where there was an airtight or
watertight compartment. the WOO
pounds to a square inch pressure of
water had crumpled those walls of
the vessel as if they were tissue pa
per.”
PLANNING DETACHABLE DECK.
Naval Architects in London Now Busy
With Problem.
London, April IT.—"Naval architects
are already busying themselves with
the problem of designing a deck
which can be slipped from a sinking
liner," said John Harvard Biles, vice
president of the Institution of Naval
Architects, during the course of an
interview, today. He continued:
“The problem is chiefly that of the
expense of tiie apparatus which would
be used only once in 50 years. An un
sinkable ship is a fiction of the trans
Atlantic ticket sellers. All things con
sidered even in case of a collision with
an iceberg, a vessel of the size of the
Titanic ought to be safer than a
smaller liner. A head-on collision
would leave more compartments un
(hiiliiged while a side swipe could be
better resisted.
It is passible Pi tarry sufficient
boats to save eo iv soul on board of t
liner 1 cannot account for the failure
of the v. irelcss apparatus on the Ti
tanic almost two hours prior to her
foundering as a supplementary dyna
mo was carried 15 feet above the wa
ter line."
r igures 11*ivi iu»* iusmcsi
source supplied, today, by one of the
most prominent British naval desigit
eis. show that 960 souls was the great
est number that could possibly be
saved with the apparatus carried on
board the Titanic. That vessel’s fa
cilities were just within the Board ot
Trade regulations which specified that
a ship must be equipped with wooden
or metal boats sufficient to carry j.Vi
passengers from a 10,000 ton vessel.
Collapsible boats, rafts and other ap
paratus not carried, davits must be
supplied to accommodate three-fourths
as trianv, making the total it would
be possible to save under the Board of
Trade rules. The plans show that
the Titanic carried lifeboats to accom
modate 060 persons. Each of the Is
lifeboats was capable of taking 9:1 pas
sengers. Tin re is no evidence on t!v
plans to show that the Titanic carrie
any collapsable boats, putting he
barciy within the Board of Trade reg
ulations. Comparisons with the reali
se and 'ampania, which are mm'
smaller, show that they carry ’JO boats
each, while the Lusitania has only If.
The Board of Trade rules lav) down in
19011, took as their basis 10,000 ton
ships and apply only to ships with
water tight eompartmeniu. It does
not appear that in the big ships of bit
er date any attempt to increase tic
life saving apparatus beyond that re
quired by the regulations was made.
WANTS WIRELESS ZONES CLEAR
Marconi Co. Asks United States Gov
ernment to Make Effort.
New York, April 17.--The Marconi com
pany lias called upon the United Stale
government In an endeavor to clear the
Atlantic wireless zones from interrup
tions. The following telegram was sent
liy the company to Joiin W. Griggs, tlie
company's new president, at Washington,
D. C.:
"Believe all interests best served f
government will instruct all government
wireless stations, north of Norfolk, cease
sending, excepting cruisers or cutters im
mediate vicinity Carpathla. We to pro
hibit transmission all United Wireless
and Marconi ship and shore stations ex
cepting South Welllleet, Slasconset, Sag
aponack and Sea Gate, allowing these
stations, which are unaffected by ama
teurs, control entire wireless situation
This will avoid any chance confusion due
excitement and allow transmission gen
eral news to relatives and friends of Ti
tanic passengers. Also prompt efficient
handling by our trained force, thousands
urgent personal telegrams to survivors
on Carpathia. Would be willing to have
naval stations do this, but we are posi
tive our men can handle three messages
to one by the navy, owing expert tele
graphers trained our method work. Pos
itive first named arrangement will pro
duce lies! results for public. Our re
i|Uest strictly unselfish. Our only desire
best possible wdreless service to those
immediately interested. John Wanamaker
also agrees close his stations few days.
Please Ilia tills officially with Washing
ton officials."
GOVERNMENT WILL INVESTIGATE
Sweeping Inquiry to Be Made Into the
Titanic Disaster.
Washington, April 17.—A sweeping res
olution of inquiry into the Titanic disas
ter was presented to the Senate, today,
by Senator Smith of Michigan. The res
olution follows:
"Resolved, that the committee on com
merce. or a sub-committee thereof, is
hereby authorized and directed to inves
tigate the causes leading to the wreck of
tlie White Star liner Titanic, with its
attendant loss of life, so shocking to the
civilized world.
j “Resolved, further, that said committee
or sub-committee Is hereby empowered to
summon witnesses, send for persons and
papers and to take such testimony as
DON'T FAIL TO READ
-ABOUT OUR
Silk and
White Goods
ORDER BY MAIL
We Have Purchased a
$45,000.00 Stock of Silk ami
White Goods way below the
cost of the manufaeturer. We
will sell these goods so that
you may order tty mail and yet
the benefits of this great pur
chase.
Look for our advertisement
in this paper Saturday and in
the Hoston Sunday papers,
ORDER BY MAIL.
Houghton Dutton Co.,
(The Great Cash Store of New
Kayla nd.
Boston, Mass.
may he necessary to determine the re
sponsibility therefor, with a view to such
legislation as may be necessary to pre
vent as far as possible any repetition of
any such disaster.
"Resolved, further, that the committee
shall inquire particularly into the num
ber of lifeboats, life rafts and life pre
servers and other equipment for the
protection of the passengers and crew;
tile number of persons aboard the Titan
ic, whether passengers of crew, and
whether adequate inspections had been
made of such vessel, in view of the largo
number of American passengers traveling
over a route commonly regarded as dan
gerous from Icebergs, and whether it is
feasible for Congress to take steps look
ing to an international agreement to se
cure tlie protection of sea traffic, includ
ing regulation of the size of ships and
designation of routes.
"Resolved, further, that in the report
of said committee it shall recommend
such legislation as it shall deem expe
dient.”
it was referred to the commerce com
mittee and a resolution by Senator Mar
tin of New Jersey looking to an interna
tional agreement for a change in the
trans-Atlantic route was sent to the for
eign relations committee.
GETS CALL FROM TITANIC.
Steamship Cincinnati Receives Wire
less at Midnight, April 14.
New York, April 17.—Captain Schulke
of the steamship Cincinnati, which
reiched port, todaay, from Naples and
Genoa, reports that at midnight on April
14 he received a wireless call for help
from the steamer Titanic. Although 550
miles away the Cincinnati was headed
for the scene of the disaster and would
have continued had not another message
from the Titanic been received half an
hour later. “Olympic coming;-not need
ed. This was followed by silence and
the Cincinnati resumed her course.
Although he took the southerly course
Captain Sclntlke says he saw no ice
bergs.
TITANIC’S BULKHEADS FAULTY?
Electrical Control Comes in for Large
Amount of Criticism,
London, April 17.—The electrical con
trol of the bulkheads installed in the Ti
tanic is coming in for much criticism. It
is stated here that they are a pet idea
of Lord I’irrie, who insists on introduc
ing them in ships built at Belfast, despite
the condemnation of many well-known
constructors, who pin their faith to hy
draulic power as being far more reliabl-.
These constructors point out that even a
small mishap is liable to render the lec
tric Installation useless.
Cable Ship to
Search for Bodies.
Halifax, X. S., April 17.—The cublesh-j
Mackay iienneCt, which has been char
tered by I lie White Star Line to go to
the scene of the Titanic disaster, was be
ing loaded, today, for departure. Jn the
hope that some bodies inay be picked up,
coffins are being included in the cargo,
and several undertakers and enibaliners
will co alone
The cs le ship Minia, which was in the
vicinity of the disaster, lias arrived here
with no survivors on hoard.
It tiad been hoped that she might have
picked up a few stragglers floating on
rafts or among the wreckage.
The steamer Mackay Bennett, going in
search of tiie Titanic victims, sailed, at J
o’clock this afternoon. In addition to
the undertakers, Rev. K. C. Hind, Church
of Kngiand clergyman, went on the ship
to perform the last rites on any bodies
that may not be brought to port.
In addition to 100 coffins the Mackay
Bennett is taking over 100 tons of ice.
Long lines of teams were filing down the
pier, today, and the coffins were piled up
10 feet high.
NOT HEAD-ON COLLISION.
Believed That Titanic Struck Iceberg
from an Angle.
San Francisco, April 17.—Tliat the Ti
tanic was sunk by a lateral tearing, and
not by a head-on collision, is the opinion
of Hugo r. Freer, designer of the battle
ship Oregon and among the experts in
naval construction on the Pacific coast.
“The sides of a vessel are the most
difficult to protect,” said Frear. "They
are the most vulnerable points in a
steamship’s hull, and it is my opinion
that tiie Titanic struck the Iceberg from
an angle. A head-on collision could
scarcely have done the damage necessa
ry to sink the vessel.”
TO HAGUE TRIBUNAL
Should Be Referred Question of Safety
on Ocean Steamers.
New York, April 17.—In a statement
issued, today, Charles Von Helmuth.
general manager for Oelrichs Co.,
tiie general agents of the North Ger
man Lloyd Steamship Co., expressed
the belief thut the laws of nations
concerning tiie safety of passengers on
steamships which now are at variance
should be referred to The Hague Tri
bunal, which might adopt such regu
lations as would insure as near agso
lute safety as is possible and under
which all steamship companies would
he compelled to operate.
.Mr. Von lli'lmulh says that his com
pany's ships on a trip from Germany
to New York must conform to the
inarutime regulations of four different
countries—Germany, Great Britain,
Franco and the United States—all of
which are variance.
All the steamship companies obey to
tile letter all tlie legal requirements
and in most cases exceed them, Mr.
Von Helmuth said, but nevertheless
tlie situation requires an international
agreement.
BOATS FOR OCEAN LINERS
Not Impracticable to Carry Enough for
All Passengers Aboard.
Liverpool, April 17.—"It is not altogeth
er Impracticable for tlie largest oceun
liners to carry sufficient boats to accom
modate all on board." according to Prof.
s. Abell, professor of naval engineer
ing at tlie Liverpool University. “Spe
cial arrangements," ho said, "would have
to be made and these would necessarily
involve considerable curtailment of deck
spaces and deck houses.”
TOTAL OF 1312 LOST.
(Continued from Page One.)
fate of relatives and friends.
Tim hopes of the persistently san
guine few atn mg relatives and friends
of passengers rested, tonight, on tlie
bare possibility that tlie list of named
survivors, sent by wireless from tlio
Car patina, might not, after ali, be
quite complete.
Tlie fact that one new name came
through, late today, in a private mes
sage from the Carpathia was tlie ba
sis of what was a desire more than a
hope that there were slips enough in
tho wireless list of survivors to ac
count for a few, at least, of these for
whom the worst was feared. At the
best, however, it appeared that it could
be only an occasional one w hose safety
was not reported owing to some error
of compilation on the liner or of trans
mission by her wireless.
From the Carpathia, which was ap
proximately 600 miles from New York,
this morning, it is expected if she
keeps her rate of Li knots an hour to
reach the entrance of the harbor by 8
o’clock, tomorr w night, came a new
report during tne day as to the num
ber of survivors on board.
The Cunarder Franconia, which es
tablished wireless communication with
her sent a message which included
this statement:
"She has a total of 703 survivors
aboard."
i ne previous statement irom tne
Carpathia had been that she carried
*8 survivors. It may he that the re
port received through the Franconia
included a count of rescued passen
gers only, disregarding the lot) or more
members of the crew who must have
been in the boats which the Carpathia
picked up. their presence being neces
-ary for tile safety of tin passengers.
T hrough the Chester there began com
ing slowly, tonight, the names of saved
steerage passengers of the Titanic.
The very sending of these could not
help confirm the sorrowful belief tli.it
there ware no more names of first and
'eeond cabin passengers to send. And
thus there was left hardly a doubt
that the names of well-known men
‘Ik ii as John Jacob Astor, William T„
Siead, fsador Straus and the others
of the now familiar list of notables
could have been omitted in the trans
mission of names from the Carpathia.
"''hat these men went down with the
ship is very certain. Authorities on
conditions off the banks agree that the
rescue of passengers not taken on the
liner by the boats would have to be
made speedily as exposure and exhaus
tion would quickly sap the life of hu
man beings forced to take to any oth
er means of keeping afloat.
During the early evening hours the
wireless communication of the Car
pathia with Siasconsent was devoted
to the most part, it appeared, to send
ing private rAessages of reassurance
from passengers to friends on shore
and to transmission of anxious inquir
ie from land to steamer. Momentarily
the chance was awaited for communi
cation of greater moment to the world
Jit large—the opportunity to learn the
long awaited recital of the Titanic's
fateful last hour afloat.
That every chance might be af
forded for free communkaftion witli
the slowly approaching liner, practic
ally all other wireless business jtlong
’he coast, tonight, was suspended.
i ne .Marumi i u. said early in tne
evening tliat it had notified its sta
tions at South Welltieet. Siasconset
and Kagaponak, and Seagate to han
dle to and l'rom the Carpathia exclu
sively.
"All other commercial and govern
ment stations" the message reads,
"will cease transmitting while the
Carpathians business is being ex
changed with the above mentioned
stations. No other work than llie Car
pathian business from the govern
ment ships going to meet the Car
pathia will he permitted.”
These instructions, it was explained,
were sent out in conformity with the
suggestion made to the I’nited States
government by the Marconi t o., and
was agreed to.
Despite appeals that wireless com
munication with the Carpathia he re
stricted to authorised messages from
recognised wireless stations, the criss
cross of wireless waves over the sea
toward the rescue ship continued dur
ing tile gieater part of the night to
interfere with legitimate attempts at
transmitting messagi s to and from
the liner. Around midnight an appeal
was made to Secretary of the Navy
Aleyer to see if something could not
be done to reduce the congestion, in
reply, the following message was re
ceived from the secretary:
"Replying to your telegram, orders
have been issued to all ships at sea
and at tlie navy yards not to attempt
to cell the Carpathia. The Chester will
relay a list of third class passengers
saved when convenient. Have noti
fied Newport not to interfere.”
SYMPATHY IS UNIVERSAL.
(Continued from Page One.)
their deep sympathy for the victims of
the Titanic disaster and have asked to
lie informed of the details of the wreck
and the names of the survivors. Among
tlie passengers were several American
citizens who were known personally to
the King and the Pope, as they were re
cently received them in private audi
ences.
“All Women Saved
On the Carpathia.”
Now York, April 17.—"All worn -n
saved. On the Carpathia.'’ This wire- i
less dispatch was received, today,
from Mrs. Caroline Donnell, one of the I
Titanic's rescued passengers, now
bound for Xcw York on the Cnrputhia i
Ttie message came to H. \Y. Bonne!!
of Youngstown, her brother, stopping
at the Waldorf-Astoria, from Mrs.
Donnell's uncle on the Olympic.
Before sailing it was agreed that
Mrs. Bonneli on the Titanic was to
get in touch with her uncle on tile
Olympic as soon as possible on the
voyage.
The message from the Carpathia
was caught by the Olympic and re
layed to New York.
The Shock Caused Her Death.
Brockton, Mass., April 17.—Mist
Katherine K. Maguire, aged 50. heart
broken by the news that her nephew.
John E. Maguire, was among those
probably lost on the Titanic, was tak
en violently ill. tonight, and died with
in a lew moments. She had been in,
the best of health but was much at
tached to her nephew and the shock
of the tragedy was more than she
could bca'.
The Parisian Brings No News.
Halifax, N. S.. April 17. -Tile steamer
Parisian, the Allan liner which, last
Monday, was near the scene of the Titan
ic disaster, u Idcli fact aroused hopes of
her having survivors of the Titanic on
board until a denial was received from
her. entered Halifax harbor, at 7 o'clock
this evening. The Parisian was visited
upon iier arrival by the port physician,
whon on landing shortly afterward
brought the information that the steamer
had no further details of the Titanic dis
aster.
Flags Half-masted at Boston.
Boston, April 17.—Flags on all the city
buildings will 1)0 placed at half mast In
Boston as soon as it is otticially learned
that the missing Bostonians were lost
aboard the Titanic, according to a state
ment issued by Mayor Fitzgerald, to
night. Some nine Boston people were on
the White Star liner and have not been
accounted for to date.
EMPEROR WILLIAM GRIEVED
Sends Touching Message of Sympathy
to White Star Line.
London, April l,. tlie text of the ;or
man Emperor's message of sympathy
sent to the White Star Line is as fol
lows:
“Achilleion, April 16.
"Deeply grieved by the sad news of the
terrible disaster which has befallen your
line, 1 send you the expression of my
deepest sympathy and also with all those
who mourn the loss of relatives and
friends.
(Signed) "WILLIAM I. R.”
The President Anxious for the News.
New York, April 17.—The following
wireless dispatch which was being sent
from the scout cruiser Salem to the Car*
pathia was read at the Brooklyn navy
yard, tonight:
"President of the I'nited States Is very
anxious to know if Major Butt. Mr. Mil
lett and Mr. Moore are safe. Please in
form me so I can transmit to him.
Chandler.”
Toronto Gives $5000 for Relief.
Toronto, Ont., April 17.—The board
of control, this morning, voted $5000
toward the relief fund for the families
of the officers and crew of the Titanic.
ENORMOUS ICE FIELDS
Reported by Steamers Arriving,
Wednesday, at St. John.
St. John, N. B., April 17.—Three
trans-Atlantic liners which arrived
here, today, reported ice IJelds off the
New Foundland Banks as the worst j
ever encountered.
The arriving vessels were the Allan
Liner Corsican from Liverpool, the
Hamburg-Amerlcan Line steamer Pisa
from Bremen, and the Canadian Paci
fic liner Montrose from London and
Antwerp. The Corsican reported that
she and four other big steamers in
cluding the Hamburg-American liner
President Lincoln were all forced to
stop in an immense lield of ice. Thurs
day night, so thick was tho pack ice
and so cloge were several monster ice
bergs. The Pisa experienced difficul
ties navigating the fields and passed
several icebergs which were 200 feet
high. The captain of the Pisa said
several large bergs were seen to the
south.
uapt. WeDSler or me .uoiurons
there was more ice further south than
lie hail seen in his sea experience of more
than 40 years. He said that the depth of
the sea where the Titanic went down
was probably 2000 fathoms. He was at
a loss to understand why so great a.
steamer as the Titanic should have been
sent to the bottom by running against
the ice. He said he was in collision with
Icebergs three different times while sail
ing under the flag of the Elder-Dempster
Line several years ago and once his
steamer’s bow was crushed in 25 feet,
but the vessel kept afloat.
All three of the vessels reported hav
ing sent wireless warnings of the pres
ence of the ice field at the time they
passed through It.
On Tuesday, the Montrose received
word by way of the steamer Prlnz
Friedrich Wilhelm to the effect that the
tank steamer Deutschland was drifting
about, short of coal, in Lat. 40.52 and
Long. 5510 W. The tank steamef was
bound for Philadelphia and asked to be
towed.
IMPACT OF TITANIC TERRIFIC.
Struck Iceberg With an Estimated
Force of 1,000,000 Tons.
Washington. April 17.—A graphic
comparison of the terrible impact of
the Titanic against the iceberg that
destroyed her with the projectile force
of the guns of a modern battleship was
made, today, by Capt. Charles A. Mc
Allister, engineer-in-chief of the reve
nue cutter service.
•The impact of the Titanic against
the iceberg was probably eyual to the
simultaneous force of 80 12-inch pro
jectiles or tiie concentrated discharge
of three such Dreadnoughts as the
Florida,'’ said f’apt. McAllister. The
fire of 10 12-inch guns such as the
Florida carries is supposed to be suf
ficient to put any battleship atloat out
of business, if the projectiles would
strike simultaneously. The force ol
the Titanic striking the iceberg mce-t
TOO LATE FOR GLASSIFICATIO N
Wanted—Girl for housework.
A GIRL FOR HOUSEWORK. AP
Piv ut once, Good wugeH. Mrs. Oliver
Moulton, 176 River avenue, Randolph.
_ _aprlL’dlu
have been approximately 1,000,110 tons,
equivalent to her being struck by 30
such projectiles.
It is a wonder, In the light of such
a comparison, that she floated so long.
It Is inconceivable that the ingenuity
of man can ever devise a floating
structure to withstand such a terrific
collision.”
AMATEURS SERIOUS HINDRANCE
To Steamship Carpathia in Attempts
Mt Wireiess Communication.
Boston April 17.—Hurrying to Now
York with the only known survivors of
the Titanic, the steamship Carpathia.
today, came within the zone of wire
less communication of nearly a score
of stations aJloat and ashore, along
the N'• w England ci ast. The operators
uf most of these had been straining
their ears and propelling their me
chanical voices for two days in an ef
fort to learn something of the story
which the survivors are bringing to
shore of their experiences.
Atmospheric conditions during Lite
day were good,, but as the Carpathia
more closely approached the coast,
and was able to reach shore stations
directly, instead of by relays, the amu
teurs combined with the elements to
prevent clear communication. Sias
onset station on Nantucket, with
which the Carpathia came into direct
communication, late in the day, re
port'd, tonight, that the activity of
the amateurs was seriously interfer
ing with an exchange of messages
with the Carpathia, and further, that
the large amount of static electricity
in thv air was also operating against
their efforts to converse- A northeast
storm which was in progress in the
immediate vicinity of the Carpathia
was partly responsible for the poor at
mospheric conditions.
The wireless operators and the op
erators at commercial and prtvate sta
tions whose activities were interfering
with the conversation between the Car
pathiu and the Slasconset station,
were asked to "Stand by,” meaning to
stop sending, in order that the Car
puthi.i might lie able to send messages
so urgently sought on many sides. But
although the amateurs were told by
the Carpathia operators that unless
the messages were disposed of soon
it might lie impossible to communicate
further, if the interference continued.
Jilt" l trpUlllUlH I [ilfM e III [III 1C11 L
allows of direct transmitting of only
150 miles. During tlie forenoon and in
the early afternoon she had several
metsages relayed by other vessels, in
the course of which she communicated
with Cape Sable station, 1000 miles to
the north, with the Chester, estimated
to be less than 100 miles away and at
the station at Siasconset. The opening
of communication with Siasconset was
followed by a lengthy exchange of
radiogram messages between the siiore
station and the Carpathia. Survivors of
the Titanic notified anxious relatives
and friends of their safety. Many of
these relatives and their friends had.
learned from published lists of res
cued of tiie safety of those dear to
them and messages of congratulations
were sent by them. Steamship officials
e nmnunicated details connected witli
i he 'Itanic's loss and the disposition of
her rescued.
Meantime, the scout cruisers Ches
ter and Salem were sending a list of
the third class passengers saved,
which had been sent to the cruisers by
the Carpathia during the day.
Throughout the night, there was the
same criss-cross of radiograms.
Toward midnight wireless condi
tions became better and the Siascon
s t station made efforts to pick up
the Carpathia, but without success.
The Siasconset operator called re
peatedly, but received no answer from
'the Cunarder. It was not known
whether the Carpathia had passed out
of range or whether her wireless op
erators, thinking there was little hope
of communicating with land, were
snatching a few hours’ sleep. The
Siasconset station had large num
ber of personal messages addressed
to the Carpathia and persons aboard
awaiting delivery.
In order to assist the Siasconset
station in getting Into communica
tion the navy department ordered all
naval stations and vessels of the de
partment to “stand by" and send:
nothing but official business. Similar
orders were issued by the Marconi
officials to their stations on the coast.
Just before midnight the scout
cruiser Salem commenced repeating
the names of third cabin passengers
to the Newport naval station.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014248/1912-04-16/ed-1/?sp=12&q=Titanic&r=-0.709,0.089,1.685,1.096,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The steamship Carpathia
with several hundred passengers of
the Titanic is now en route to New
York.'’
The text of the message received
from Capt. H. J. Haddock of the
Olympic as made public, by Mr
Franklin. reads:
"At 2.20 A. M. Titanic foundered.
Carpathia proceeding to New York
with passengers.”
There was reason to believe, how
ever, that the message was consider
ably longer than the above and that
the White Star officials had not deem
ed it wise to give out the lull text un
til the reports of loss of life had been
confirmed. One of Mr. Franklin’s as
sistants in announcing earlier that
the Titanic had gone down, said that
the Carpathia was proceeding to New
York "with survivors.” So far as
could be ascertained at the White
Star offices, it was not known there
whether there were any passengers
aboard the Virginian and Parasian.
Vice President Franklin said that Capt
Haddock's message was very brief and
neglected to gay that all the crew were
saved. It is said that the Carpathia had
600 or "00 of the Titanic’s passengers
aboard, including all of the saloon pas
sengers. and that the vessel should reach
New York, Friday morning. No infor
mation had been received from the Vir
ginian or Parisian at the White Star
offices, although it was said to be
"known" that many of tlie Titanic pas
sengers were on board these vessels.
Vice President Franklin, at 8.40. con
ceded that there had been “a horrible
loss of life” in the Titanic disaster, lie
said that he had no Information to dis
prove the Associated Press report from
Cape Race to the effect that only 675 of
the passengers and crew had been res
cued. He said that the monetary loss
coudl not be estimated, tonight, although
he Intimated that It would run Into the
millions. "We can replace the money,”
he said, “but not the lives, it is hor
rible."
Mr. Franklin continued:
"As far as we know, it lias been ru
mored from Halifax that three steamers
have passengers on board, namely: The
Virginia, the Carpathia and Parisian.
Now, we have heard from Captain Had
dock thut the Titanic sank, ut 2.20 this
morning. We have also learned from
him thut tlie Carpathia had 675 surviv
ors on board. It is very difficult to learrv
if tiie Virginian und the Parisian have
any survivors on board. We have asked
Capt. Haddock and our agent at Halifax
to ascertain if there an- any passengers
aboard the two steamships.
“We very much fear, however, that
there lias been a great loss of life, but
it is impossible for use to give furthe
particulars until we have heard from th
1 atisiau and Virginian. We have no |n
formation that there ate any passenger
aboard these two steamships.”
Mr. Franklin euid there were sufficien
lifeboats to take all the passengers fror
the Titanic. He said he was confldem
today, alien lie made the statement Ilia
"the Titanic was onsinkalile" that th
steamship was safe and that there wool
la- no loss of life The first definite new
received came in the message from apl
Haddock lie said, was given to Tile -\s
sociated Press at once.
News of th, probable terrible loss or
f" i’1 the inking or the Titanic was
limited in its Circulation in the early
OANTHROX MAKES
LOVELY HAIR
Mrx. Mac Martin. the prominent
authority on beauty topics, savs:
"At present beauty seekers are per
hap* mest c»jncern«fd about their hair.
Increasing baldness among women,
preceded by thinning locks and lulling
hair, is largely responsible for this
unusual interest. The biggest mistake
ho many wpinen make is in washing
their hair with soap, the alkali in
which dulls and streaks the hair, mak
ing It coarse and brittle.
"To shampoo properly use a tea
spoonful of canthrox dissolved in a
cup of hot water. This mixture will
cleanse the scalp perleotly of dirt and
dandruff and leave the hair lustrous,
fluffy and easy to do up. It makes the
hair dry tjuickly, evenly and simplifies
shampooing greatly. t’anthrox cannot
be recommended too highly for putting
the hair and scalp in a healthy condi
tion and keeping U so.’ -Hiu-inmento
I'osC
evening, but by It o'clock, it had
brought u great crowd of persona to
the White Star Line offices near the
foot of Broadway. Women were in
tc..rs .nd men were frantic after their
plea for assuring news was met with
the frank admission that very little
was known of the fate of passengers
who were not in the tirst or second
saloons.
All of lie' White Star Line officials
and subordinates available were on
duty at the offices and planned to
make a night of it under siege by re
porters, relatives of passengers and
others.
TWO BRUNSWICK MEN.
Percival W. White and Son, Richard
F.. Bowdoin Senior, on Board.
Brunswick, Me., April 15.- Percival
w. White, a Massachusetts cotton
manufacturer who was a passenger on
the Titanic, makes his home in this
town. Friends lure say that lie is ac
companied by his son, Richard I4.
White, a Senior at Bowdoin College,
and not by Percival 55 bite, Jr., as
was first reported. No word has been
heard from Mr. 5Vhite since the acci
dent to t!i<4 liner.
Some of the Peo=
pie on the Titanic.
Youngstown. Ohio, April 15.—Mr.
i.n Mrs. Opurge 1. Wick and their
daughter, .Miss Natalie; Miss Caroline
Uonneil and Miss Idly ISonnell. Birk
dale, lnd., her cousin, were among the
Titanics passengers. The Wicks and
Connells are among the most wealthy
people in Youngstown.
Buffalo. April 15.—Edward A. Kent,
whose name appears on the passen
ger list of the Titanic, was one of th.
h ading architects of this city. He had
offices In Elliot square and lived at
the Buffalo Club.
Rochester. N. Y., April 15.—It is be
lieved that three residents of this city
were passengers on the Titanic: How
ard B. Case of Ascot. England, who
went from this city, 10 years ago, as
I.ondon manager of the Vacuum OH
Co.; Stanley Fox, traveling man for
a Rochester machine company, who
sent a letter to the firm saying he
would sail on the Titanic, and Miss
Lily Duncan, who was visiting abroad.
Morgantown. W. Va., April 15. Mr. and
Mrs. Lucian Smith of this city were pas
sengers on the Titanic. They were com
pleting a honeymoon trip around the
world. Mrs. Smith is a daughter of Con
gressman Hughes of West Virginia.
Providence, It. I., April 15.—Four Prov
idence persons are known to have been
passengers on tHe ill-fated Titanic. They
Include E. C. Ostby and ids daughter
Helen, who were returning from a tout
of Egypt; St. James Lamb, a theatrical
man who had been on a three-months
trip abroad; and Harry Sullivan, who
was coming to make his borne with his
father in this city. Relatives have re
ceived no word from any of the four.
PART OF THE RESCUED.
(Continued from Page One.)
Bruce Isniay.
Mr. and Mrs. Ed Kimberly.
F. A, Kenymau.
Miss Emiiie Kenchen.
Miss G. F Longley.
Miss A. F. Leader.
Miss Bertha Lavory.
Mrs. Ernest Livess.
Mrs. Susan P. Itogerson.
Miss Emily B itogerson.
Mrs. Arthur Itogerson.
Master Aldson and nurse, Miss K. T.
Andrews.
Miss Ninette Panhart.
Miss E. W. Alien.
Mr. and Mrs. D. Bishop.
Mr. H. Blank.
Miss A. Bassina.
Mrs. James Baxter.
Mr. George A. Bay ton.
Miss C. Bonnell.
Mrs. J. M Brown.
Miss G. C. Bowen.
Mr. and Mrs. It. L. Beckwith.
The above list was received by wireless
at Cape Race station from the steamer
‘urpathia. in spelling and initials it
does not correspond with the list as ca
bled from London, today.
Mrs. K. M. Warner.
Miss Helen A. Wilson.
Miss Willard.
Miss Alary Wicks.
Mrs. George D. Wldoner and maid.
Miss Mary Clines.
Mrs. Kingrid Lindstrom.
Mr. Gustav J. Lesneur.
Miss Georgietta Antadill.
Madame Melieard.
Mrs. Tucker and maid.
Mrs. T. h. Thayer.
J. B. Thayer, Jr.
H. Wooimer.
Miss Anna Ward.
Rich M. William.
Mrs. J. Steward White.
Miss Mary Young.
Mrs. Thomas Potter, Jr.
Airs. Edna S. Roberts.
Countess of Rothes.
Airs. C. Roimane.
Mrs, Jacob p waird missed».
Among tIn- names of survivors of
the Titanie picked up Ijy wireless
l oin steamer Carpal ilia were the
following:
Mr. arid Mrs. 1.. Henry.
Mrs W. A. Hooper.
Mr. Mile.
J Flynn.
Miss Alice Fortune.
M rs. Robert Douglas.
Miss Hilda Slayter.
Mrs. P. Smith.
Mrs. lira ham.
Miss Lueile Carter.
Mr. William carter.
Miss Roberts.
-Miss Cummings.
Mrs. Florence Mare.
Miss Alice Phillips.
Mrs. l’aula Munge.
Miss Rosie
-Mrs. Jane-.
Miss Phillis-.
Miss Bertha-.
In the Iasi four names the operator
hero was not.able to Ret the full names
because of interference.
Paul Ceverc, the well-known French
sculptor, who made the Champlain
monument was in the first cabin on
his way to Canada to complete mem
orial.
Mr, and Mrs. William K. Carter and
their children. I-ucille and William re
side near Bryn Maw, R. I., Pa. Mrs.
Walter B. Stephenson, was formerly
Miss Martha Kustis of Brooklyn,
Mass.
.tunics Clinch Smith, a brother-in-law
of the late Stanford White, is well known
in New York society circles. He mar
ried Miss Bertha Baines of Chicago.
Mistakes were due to the married wire
less transmission and relays. In one in
stance Mrs. L. Y. B. Harris is given in
the wireless list, hut on the passenger
list as announced here there was only a
Mrs. B. Harris. There are a number of
similar discrepancies.
ANXIOUS THOUSANDS
Clamor for News—The New York Po
lice Reserves Called,
Now York, April 15.—By midnight.
Bowling Green, in front of the White
Star Line offices, was the parking place
of a large number of automobiles of
prominent residents of the city who had
driven down town for the first hand in
formation. Wealth and society rubbed
elbows with poverty and democracy in
tlie crowd which besieged the steamship
lino officials and both classes were In
deep grief.
There were many instances of fashion
able gowned women going into hysterics
when the hopeful reports of tlie after
noon were blasted by the news that only
675 persons had probably been saved.
Vincent Astor, only son of Col. John
Jacob Astor, accompanied by A. J. Biddle
of Philadelphia and Col. Astor’s secreta
ry, were among the crowd at the offices
and left with tears in their eyes after
a 15-minutes talk with Vice President
Franklin. Relatives of lsador Straus and
of a number of other prominent passen
gers had similar talks with Mr. Franklin
and came away equally dejected.
Police reserves had to be called to sev
eral sections of the city, tonight, to gov
ern the crowds which congregated around
newspaper bulletin boards for news of
the Titanic. The disaster stunned the
gay Broadway district, for many of
those who poured out of the theatres
had friends on the steamer. The news
paper district was crowded till long after
midnight.
Prayers for the safety of the passen
gers aboard the Titanic were said, today,
at tlie afternoon conference of the Men
and Religion Forward Movement in this
city. William T. Stead, the journalist,
and the Rev. J. Seward Holden of Lon
don, who were among the Titanics pas
sengers, were on their way here to make
addresses before the conference.
THE BURIAL PLACE
Of the Titanic Is 500 Miles from Hali
fax, Near Grand Banks.
Halifax, April 15.—The deathbed of the
$10,000,000 steamer Titanic and of tin
many who must have gone down with
her is two miles, at least, below the
surface of the sea.
The calculation was made by an offi
cial of the government marine depart
ment. who finds that the depth on the
marine chart at a point about 500 miles
from Halifax and about 70 miles south or
the Grand Banks, where he believes the
Titanic went down. This location is mid
way between Sable island and Cape Race
and in lint with those dangerous sands
which, however, might have proved a
place of safety hud there been time to
run the Titanic there and beach her.
The Canadian warship ,\iobe, which
has one of the most powerful wireless
equipments of any vessel in this vicinity,
was unable to get. in touch with any of
tlie ships in the vicinity of the dlsastei
and the government station at camper
down heard only fragments of messages
1 .heeds’ agent here had not received
late tonight, any official notification of
tlie loss of the Titanic.
the president
Anxious as to The Fate of His Aide
Major Butt.
Washington, April 15.—President
latt was greatly anxious, tonight, lot
news <>l his aide, Major Archibald W.
Butt, one of he four Washington folk
on the Titanic. The President had
frequent inquiries made of the news
paper offices and the steamship
agency. No word had been received
tl it late hour at the homes of Frank
l>. Millett, the artist: or the other
Washingtonians aboard.
New ork, April 15.—The following
message from President Taft was ro
eeived by Vice President Franklin ot
the International Mercantile Marine:
Have you any information concern
ing Major Butt? If you will com
municate with me at once would
greatly appreciate."
The answer was:
Sorry to say I have no definite in
formation. As soon as received will
notify you."
BOSTON STAGGERED
Dy the Terrible Disaster, If Reports
from the Titanic Are True.
Boston, April 15. Boston was stag
gered, tonight, by the news of the re
ported loss nl life in the Titanic di
saster, man) Bostonians being among
the passengers.
Many ol tlie evening and morning
papers issued extra editions and tlie
streets were thronged with people who
talked of nothing but the disaster.
Newspaper offices were besieged with
telephone calls.
Tiie While Star Line offices were
kept open until late in the evening
giving out such information as they
had.
Easily
Proved—
POST UjM
is the way out of
Coffee troubles.
THERES A REASON
Read The Road to VVellville, in
OVER 1500 LIVES LOST.
(Continued from Pape One.)
near the scene of the disaster, send
ing the welcome news that $66 of the
Titanics passengers, mostly women
and children, were being brought to
port by the Cunarder Carpathia. Oth
er messages late, tonight, brought con
firmatory tidings.
First reports were that tlie Carpathia
had saved but 675 persons. The new
figmiK reduced the list of those for
whose fate fear was felt by more than
200, and as seems probable, practically
ail those saved were passengers, it
would appear that all hut approxi
mately 150 of the vessels passengers
are accounted for. A partial list of
tlie survivors received from the Car
pathia contains the names of many
women ot prominence who were on
the steamer.
After the first desperate calls by
the Titanic for help had been sent
living through space and brought
steamers for hundreds of miles around
speeding to the rescue, what seems
to have been an impenetrable wall of
silence was raised between her and
the anxious world. The giant liner,
so far as last nights advices appear,
went to her fate without so much as a
whisper of what must have been
scenes of agony and tragedy upon her
decks.
Other than the early news, last
evening, that 675 persons, largely
women and children, had been res
cued from the liners boats by the
Cunarder Carpathia, more than six
hours of the night passed without a
word as to the fate of the remainder
of those who were on board her at
the time of the fateful collision.
Along the entire Atlantic coast wire
less antennae were tuned to catch
from any source the slightest glim
mering of hope that possibly on board
the many steamships which went to
the assistance of the stricken steam
ship were other survivors of the sunk
en vessel.
Hut from none of the ships reported to
be at or near the scene of what, viewed
in the light of the probabilities, may be
recorded as the worlds greatest marine
horror, came the slightest sylable of en
couragement to the anxiously waiting
world until the message added nearly 200
to tlie first reported about the Carpathia.
Last night, there was a possibility that
any moment might bring word of relief.
Anxiety deepened and many friends and
relatives of those who sailed on the Ti
tanic began to despair as hour after hour
passed and tlie night grew old without
word from either of the Allan liners.
Parisian or Virginian, believed to be,
with the exception of tho Carpathia, the
vessels nearest the Titanic when site
made her fatal plunge.
As the Titanic sank before 3 oclock
in the morning and it was not hoped
during the day that the Virginian
could reach the scene before 10 a. .\i
at the earliest, while the Parisian was
supposed to be some distance further
away, it was feared even by the White
Stcr lofficinls, trying their best /to
calculate differently and yet accurate
ly. that they would not have reached
tiic scene to be of service.
The steamer Virginian was final
heard from at 2.15 O’clock, this morn
ing. She did not report the presence
of any survivors on board, the nios
age from her saying only that sh
would bring to St. Jones, N. such
-.urvivors of the Titanic as she ma>
rescue." The fact that the Virginiai
was to go out of her course to put in
*o St. Johns on her voyage to Liver
cool was taken as a favorable indi
cating arousing the hope that after al
she might have picked up some
the victims of the wreck and wa
bringing them to port.
Tlie Titanic herself lies buried twi
miles beneath tlie ocean's surface
between Sable island and Cape Ran
Tor position when she struck the ice
berg was given as Lilt. 41.46 North
Long. 60.14 W. According to tile Car
pathla’s services, the liner whicl
ttruck the icebergs at 10.25, on Sundaj
night, sank at 2.20 o'clock, Monda.x
morning, nearly four hours later, ir
La t. 41.16, Long. 50.14, or not mon
han half a degree south of the poin!
where the collision occurred. It seem:
improbable from this that after tin
iccident the liner made much head
way under her own steam.
It seems to be established tha
there'were about 2100 persons on tin
iost liner. Tins was the estimate ot
I he company officials in New York
which gave the number of passenger:
is 1320. Tlie remaining number, 860
made up the crew.
lu addition to a valuable shipment
>f diamonds aboard the Titanic, it is
said that among almost priceless
Jewels carried by the passengers art
tearls belonging to an American wo
man, valued at $600,000. The steamei
iso carried a large amount in bond1
ind a very valuable registered mail
t is stated that the owners were un
able to insure the Titanic to the full
amount because the British and
Kuropean markets were not big
enough to swallow the sum.
more man lanu persons, it is I cured
link to their death, early yesterday,
vhen within four hours after shi
rushed into an iceberg, the mam
nouth White Star Line steamer
Hattie, hound from Liverpool to New
'ork on h< r maiden voyage, went to
he bottom oft’ the New found land
auks. Of the nearly 2200 persons or;
■oard the giant liner, some of them
f world wide prominence, only 67;,
re known to have been saved. Al
hough the White Star line ofllee in
vew Yohk kept up hope to the last, it
as free to admit that there hat
been “horrible loss of life."
Accepting the early estimates of th
atality list as accurate, the dlsastei
s the greatest in the modern marine
history of tiie world. Nearest ap
iroaching it in magnitude were the
loss ol the steamer Atlantic in 187.!.
when 574 lives were lost and that of
La Hourgogne In 1S148, with a list of
fatalities of 571. Should it prove that
>ther liners, notably the Allan liners
’arisan and Virginian, known to have
been in the vicinity of the Titanic,
early yesterday, picked up others ol
her passengers the extent of the ea
arnitv will fortunately he great ly re
duced. This hope still remains.
News of ihe sinking of the liner and
the consequent loss of life reached
New York early, last evening, with a
much greater snook because hope had
been buoyed up, all day, by reports
that the steamship, although badly
damaged, was not in a sinking condi
tion. that ail her passengers bad been
safely taken off. The messages were
mostly unofficial, however, and none
cam? direct from the liner, so that a
lurking fear remained of possible
bad tidings to come.
Shortly after 7 o'clock, last night,
there came flashing over the wires
from Cape Race, within 400 miles of
which, in the treacherous region of
the Newfoundland banks, the huge
liner struck tho berg, that at 2.20
o'clock, Monday morning, hours and
5f minutes after receiving her death
blow, the Titanic sank. The news came
from the steamer Cnppathia and it
was relayed by tho White Star Inner
Olympic, and it revealed that by the
time the Carpathian outward hound
from New York, and racing for the
Titanic on a wireless call, reached
the scene, the ill-starred vessel had
disa ppeared.
Left on the surface, however, were
lifeboats from the Titanic and in
them as appears from the meagre re
ports received up to a late hour, were
some 675 survivors of the disaster.
These, according to the advices, the
Carpathia picked up and is now bring
ing them to New York.
For the rest, the scene as the Car
pathia came up was one of desola
tion. All that remained of the $10,
O'lO.OOO palace, on which nearly 1400
passengers were luxuriously traveling
to this side of the Atlantic were some
1 its of wreckage. The biggest ship in
the world had gone down, snuffing
out in her downward plunge, it ap
peared. hundreds of human lives.
A significant line in the dispatch
from Cape Race, was the statement of
those saved by the Carpathia, nearly
ell were women and children. Should
no other vessel have picked up any
other passengers of the sinking steani
r, it may mean that few of the men
on board were saved, the proportion
of women and children among the pas
sengers was large. This would almost
certainly mean practically the whole
of the crew. In the two saloons were
to women and children, but it is not
known how many there were among
tho 4K0 third class passengers.
In the first saloon there were 1-8
women and la children and in the sec
ond 79 women and S children.
Notable persons, travelers on the
Titanic, whose fate was in doubt in
the lack of definite advices as to the
identity of the survivors were Mr. and
Mrs. John Jacob Astor. Major Archi
bald Butt, aide to President Taft;
Charles M. Hayes, president of the
Grand Trunk Pacific of Canada; his
wife and daughter; \V. T. Stead, Ben
jamin Guggenheim. I\ D. Milet, the
artist; and .1. Widener of Philadel
phia; Mr. and Mrs. Isador Straus;
J. B. Thayer, vice president of the
Pennsylvania Railroad; J. Bruce 1s
may; Henry B. Harris, the theatrical
manager; Mrs. Harris and Col. Wash
ington Rootling, builder of the Brook
lyn bridge.
A ray of hope appeared shortly be
fore it o'clock, last night, in a mes
sage to New York from the operator
at the Marconi wireless station at Sa
ble island, near the scene of thi dis
aster. To an inquiry regarding the de
livery of wireless messages to the
passengers of the Titanic lie replied
that it was difficult to deliver them
"as the passengers are believed to be
dispersed among several vessels.”
The Wldte Star Bine officers en
deavored from 8 o’clock until 11
o'clock to get further word from the
Olympic about the Titanic. Vice Pres
ident Franklin said, at 11 o’clock, they
were still hopeful of getting another
message front her. The company was
also trying to get into wireless com
munication with Carpathia and get
:t message asking that if possible the
entire list of the names of the 675
survivors said to be on board the Car
pathia be sent by wireless. Such a
list. Vice President Franklin believes
is ol the utmost importance for hope
was waning among the White Star
Line officials, tonight, that any others
than those 675 persons had survived.
Arr.id confusion at the offices the
situation was studied as calmly as
possible. Mr. Franklin figured that
notwithstanding his fervent hope to
tiie contrary, the Allan Line steamers
Virginian and Parisian could hardly
nave reai lied the scene of the disas
ter in time to have been of assist
ance. When the Virginian received
the distress signal, late last night, she
laid she was not likely to be able to
reach the scene before lu o'clock, to
lay. This hour would have been near
ly eight hours after the Titanic sank.
It was equally doubtful that the Par
isian ci ulil have reached tiic scene in
tim.
Mr. Franklin said that from ids
knowledge of Capt. Smiths bravery
and heroism on other occasions, the
veteran navigator must have stuck
to his bridge and gone down to his
leath.
There was discussion as to whether
nil the male passengers had sacrificed
opportunity to save themselves by
giving women and children the first
chance at the boats.
“There is no rule of the sea” said
Mr. Franklin, “which requires such a
sacrifice. It is a rule of courtesy on
land as well as sea that gallant men
lave often observed in time of dl
laster.”
It was generally true, he added tiial
nen made this vital sacrifice at sea to
tie women of the steerage as well as
hose of wealthier elass in the first
nd second saloons.
The White Star Line officers reck
iicU from their data that tho Olympic
vas 470 miles from the scene of the
Iitallie s loss when she sent the news
t 7 o’clock.
The officers <>i the Titanic are:
Captain K. ,1. Smith, commander;
urgeon, VV. E. N. O’Loughlin; assist
mt surgeon, ,1. E. Simpson; purser,
i. W. McEJroy; second purser, R. E.
'rocker; chief steward, A. Latimer
The presence of an unusually large
lumber of icebergs in the path of
rans-Atlantie liners was Indicated by
vlreless, last week. Twelve hours lie
ore the news of the Titanic’s accident
cached the world, the serious menace
if the icebergs was pointed out by
he arrival here of the Cunard line
'learner Carmania. which reported
laving dodged 2,"i big bergs, some of
hem more than 250 feet high. The
'armania reported that the French
steamship Niagara had had a worse
■xperience, having bumped into two
small bergs which punched holes in
ler hull. The Niagara had this ex
lerience on Thursday, and unless she
ms greatly reduced speed should
•each port sometime, today.
The message from the steamship
Mympic reporting ihe sinking of the
Titanic and rescue of (ITS survivors.
Why Salves Can’t Cure Eczema
Since the old-fashioned theory of cur
ing eczema through the blood has been
given up by scientists, many different
salves have been tried for skin diseases.
But it has been found that these salves
only clog the pores and cannot penetrate
to the inner skin below the epidermis
where the eczema germs are lodged.
This—the quality of penetrating—
probably explains the tremendous suc
cess of the well known liquid eczema
remedy, oil of wintercreen. thymol, gly
cerine, etc., as compounded in D.Il.D.
Prescription.
We have sold other remedies for kin
froubios hi none that wo can recotn
i lend as highly as tins for \yo know that
IVP.I). stops the itch at once. We can
give you a trial size bottle for 115 cents
that will be enough to prove it.
Of course all other druggists have
P.D.O. Prescription—go to them it you
r m't come to us—but don't accept some
big profit substitute.
Hut if you come to our store, we are
so certain of what O.P.P will do for you
that we offer you a full size bottle on
this guarantee:—Tf you do not find that
it takes away thejifeh AT ONCE, it
costs you not a cent.
tsowditch, Webster Co., Druggists opauiamg urug store, nauoweu;
Jackson 6ros., Gardiner.
which readied here, late tonight, end
ed with these words:
“Loss likely total 1 soo souls."
It Is hoped and believed here that
this is an error unless the Titanic hail
more passengers on board than re
ported. The list as given out showed
1310 passengers and a crew of 660 or
2170 persons in all. Reducing 675, the
known side would indicate a loss of
M;i5 persons. The text of the Olym
pic's dispatch follows:
“Carpathia reached Titanic posi
tion at daybreak. Found boats and
wreckage only. Titanic sank about 3.20
A M„ ill tl.lfi n; 50.14 w. All her
boats accounted for containing about
675 souls saved, crew and passengers
included. Nearly all saved women and
children. Let-land Liner Californian
remained and searching exact position
of disaster. Loss likely total 1600
souls.”
liven the survivors to the Titanic
disaster have done true hardships of
exposure and peril which may have
left many of them in a serious; condi
tion.
A dispatch announced at the White
Star office, late, tonight, said that
those rescued by the Carpathia were
picked up from a 'small fleet of life
boats. at 10.30 o'clock Monday morn
ing. It was eight hours before that
the Titanic is reported to have gone
to tlte bottom.
In the opinion of Vice President
Franklin the Carpathia will hasten
with all possible speed to this port,
in order that those survivors suffer
ing worst from oxposure may be ahle
to obtain proper medical attention.
The dispatch accounted for 675 sur
vivors on the Carpathia.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014248/1912-04-20/ed-1/?sp=12&q=Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Charles Herbert laghtholder, second of-
(leer of the Titanic, followed Mr. Marco- J
nl on the stand.
2d Officer Lighthollder.
Mr. I.lghtholder said he understood the
i maximum speed of the Titanic was shown
by her trial tests at 22J to 23 knots. Sen
ator Smith asked if the rule requiring
life saving apparatus shall be in each
room for each passenger was complied
with. "Everything was complete,” said
Digit tholder.
"Sixteen lifeboats, of which four were
collapsible, were on the Titanic," he add
ed. During the tests, he said. Capt.
Clark of the British Board of Trade was
aboard the Titanic to inspect the life
saving equipment.
“How thorough are these captains ol
the Board of Trade in inspecting ships?"
asked Senator Smith. “Capt. Clark is so
thorough that we called him a nuisance."
Dightholder said he was in the sea with
aJM#belt on one hour and a half.
“What time did you leave the ship?”
■T didn't leave it."
“Did it leave you?’ "Yes, sir.”
“Was the suction a deterrent in making
progress from the scene?” "It was hard
ly noticeable."
“\Vhwe were you when the Titanic
fegnKT” "In the officers' quarters."
“Were all the lifeboats gone then?”
"All but one," said Dightholder. "I was
about 15 feet from it. It was hanging in
W>« tackle and they were trying to get
it over the bulwark* the last time 1 saw
’'it. The first officer, Mr. Murdock, who
lost his life, was managing the tackle.''
i "Did you see Mr. lemay then?" "No."
,'ivvhen did you see him?" "When we
started to uncover the boats. He was
standing on the boat deck."
"What was lie doing?” “Standing
ktlil."
"Talking with anyone?” “No.”
“Was lie fully dressed; "1 couldn't
say for sure. It was dark."
"How long did you see Isrnny there
.•rfrtne'.'" -Just us I passed."
“When you saw Mr. Ismay 20 min
utes after the collision, were there an.
*nh*r passengers near him?” I did
rK)t see any one in particular" said
'Tight holder. "hut there might have
lipcn some."
Alter the im[tact l.ighthoUler said he
went back to ills berth. "Why?" ask
ed Smith in astonishment. "Because
sdfiefe sei tiled no cull for me on deck.
"Cull or cause?" “Neither call nor
^»llse
The witness described the impact a
a ,“slight jar followed by a grinding
pound,"
Tests of the temperature of water.
Liglitholder suld, were made on the
trip at the usual two hours intervals.
He was asked how colder the water
was on the fateful Sunday.
"It was very much colder when 1 was
in it," he suld. lie estimated the watt t
was a little above freezing, hut wa
unable to tell what th" tests showed
the temperature to lie. After a series
of questions said lie saw a message
“from some ship" about an iceberg
Ahead. He did not know the Ameriku
gent the message, he testified.
“go you say that Sunday you were
advised by the captain by word of
mouth of icebergs in near proximity
and when you were relieved at 1 1’ M
as officer of the ship by First Officer
Murdock, you passed the information
to him and he said: 'All right'."'
"Yes, sir."
The ship was making shout 21 to
£1V* knots, l.ightholder testified. He
understood this was not the best the
ghip could do.
"Did you have an ambition to see
what the ship could make?" "Natural
ly. at some time"
Again from 6 to 10 P. M l,!gtltholder
gsid he was on duty on deck.
"What was the weather that night?"
queried Smith "Clear anil fair."
"Were you anxious about ice?" "No,
fir.”
"And you put on no additional look
out?” "No, sir.”
"When Capt. Smith came on tlie* bridge
at live minutes of nine, what was said""
"I think probably one of us said good
evening lirst—1 don’t remember who said
it lirst," said l.ightholder. “Then We
talked together generally for 20 or 2a min
utes about when we might expert to get
to the ire fields, lie left the bridge, I
think, about 25 minutes after It o’clock
and during our talk he told me to keep
the ship on her course, but that if I was
the slightest degree doubtful, as condi
tions developed, to let him know at
once.”
“Did you keep the Titanic on her course
then?” Senator Smith asked. "Yes."
“Whep did* you next see 'apt. Smith?”
"When 1 came out of tile officers’ quar
ters after the impact."
“Then Capt. Smith did not return to
the bridge before your watch expired?"
"1 did not see him.”
"What time did you leave?” “I turned
over the watch to hirst Officer .Murdock
at ,0 o’clock."
"Do you recall now just what the
Titanic’s position was when you turn
ed over the watch to Murdock?" "I do
not, now, sir, but 1 did know tit the
time. We talked about the ice that
we had heard as alloat and t remem
ber we agreed we should reach th
reported longitude of the ice floes
about 11 o’clock, an hour later. At
that time the weather was calm and
clear. T remember we talked about the
distance we could see. We could see
stars in the horion. It was very clear."
“Was it cold’"' "The temperature,
sir, was 31 above, not an abnormal
temperature for that region."
“Did you see Murdock after that?”
“Yes when 1 came tit of the officers'
quarters after the impact, Murdock
was on the bridge, he on one side and
Capt. Smith on the other. 1 never
spoke to Murdock after I turned over
the watch to him. 1 saw him later
working over the last lifeboat as the
shin went down."
“Wliert did you last see Capt
Smith?" the senator asked. Lightholl
det- said he saw him several times on
the boat deck, but his last recollec
tion of Capt. Smith was walking
across the bridge of the Titanic. "I
was busy at my own work, .about 50
feet away and have a recollection of
seeing the captain walking across the
bridge. 1 did not then hear him give
any orders. I was too far away.”
"When the Titanic sank were her
decks intact?" “Absolutely intact.“
said Lighthnllder.
He Obeyed Orders.
Kenatoi Smith asked what was the
last order he heard Capt. Smith give.
"Wht n 1 asked if 1 should put th
women and children In the boats." re
plied Lighthollder, "he responded,
’Yes, and lower away.'"
"Whet did you do?” ‘beyed orders."
The last boat to put oft was a flat
collapsible one, was the one on top
of the officers' quarters, Lighthollder
s til. Men jumped upon it on deck and
waited for ihe water to float it off.
nee at sea it upset. The forward fun
nel fell into the water, just missing
the raft and turning ii. The funnel
probably killed tersons in the water.
“This was the boat I eventually got
on." said Lighthollder No one was on
il when 1 reached it. Later about .’HI
men clambered out of the water onto
it. All had on life preservers.”
"Did any passengers get on?" asked
Senator Smith "J. It. Thayer, tile sec
ond Marconi operator, and Col. Oracle
I recall," said the witness. “All the
rest were firemen taken out of the wa
ter. Two or three died that night and
slipped off into the water. I think the
senior Marconi operator did that."
"Died from cold?” “Yes, sir."
The witness was not positive that
I the dead were not passengers.
"Was there any effort by others lo
I get on board continued Senator j
Smith. "We look till we could."
"There must have been others in the
water"" "Hut not near us."
“How far away?" Seemed half a
mile."
■Wasn’t this the only raft?’ “It was
dark, sir There was wreckage.”
“Who took command?" ’I did as far
i as necessary."
"When you left did you see any wo
men or children on board?” "No, sir."
“Any on so-called boat deck?” “A
number.”
An error in the morning testimony
was corrected by the witness saying
there were 20 lifeboats aboard, four
of which were collapsible. One boat
stuck in Us tackle and never got off.
"How were the passengers selected
t" fill the boats?” asked the chair
man. ’’ft sex
"Who determined who should go”"
“I did."
How." “Whenever I saw a wom
an 1 put her in, except stewardesses
tinned those back."
"Did you see any attempt to get
women to go who would not?" "Yes.'
"Why would they not go?" "1
hadn't time to learn."
"Did any ask for their family to
go?- "Yes, one or two.”
"Did any families go?" "No."
Dightholider said that when the first
life boats were lowered he did not be
lieve the danger was so great, in the
rirst boat he put 24 persons and two
men of the crew.
"How were those men selected?"
"By me."
"Who were they?" "Can't tell."
"Hoy, did you happen to niim»
them''" "Because they were standing
near."
Did they want to go?” "I didn't
ask them; they went by my orders.”
How many passengers did the sec
ond boat take’:.About 30." said
Highthollder, "two men as far as f
remember, sir
Dili you see that boat again?"
"Not to my knowledge."
"The third boat?" "By the time I
came to the third boat all these on
the port side—I began to realize that
the situation was serious and I began
to take chances."
'How long did all the work of lov,'
ering e lifeboat take?" "It is difficult
to sav. but I think about 13 to 20 min
utes.”
"How many passengers did the last
boat contain?" "1 filled her up as full
as 1 dared, sit, then lowered her, about
33 I think."
"Hon many seamen?" "Two.”
Keopie were uuiet.
"\were ouiei. I had no trouble. The wo
men and children couldn't have stood
quieter it they’d been in church.”
In the fourth lifeboat Lighthollder
said h< was running short of seamen.
"1 put two seamen in and one of them
jumped out. That was the first boat I
had to put a man passenger in; that
boat. He was standing nearby and
said lie would go if 1 needed him.
said: Are you a sailor’” and he re
plied that he was a yaehtsman. Then
1 told him that if he was sailor
enough to get out over the bulwarks
to the lifeboat to go ahead. He diil
and proved himself afterward to he
a very brave man.”
"Who was he—did you know him?”
"I didn't know him then, but after
ward 1 looked him up. He was Major
Peuehen of Toronto," said Lightholl
der.
"Mod you ever seen him before?"
"Never.’’
Of the fifth boat Lighthollder said lie
bad no particular recollection. “The Iasi
boat 1 put nit, mv sixlh boat." lie said,
"we had difficulty finding women. I
had called for women, i had called for
women and none were on deck. The
men began to get in and then women
appeared. As rapidly as they did the
men passengers got out of the boat
again.”
The Titanic by the time the last boat
was lowered by Lighthollder was rap
idly sink:ng.
"The boat's deck was only 10 feet from
the water when I lowered the sixth boat.
When we lowered the first the distance to
the water was 70 feet. All told, Light
holder testified, 210 members of the crew
were saved.
"If the same course was pursued on
the starboard side as you pursued on the
port In filling boats, how do you ac
count for so many of the crew being
saved?” asked Chairman Smith. “I have
Inquired especially and have found that
for every six persons picked up five weie
either firemen or stewards.”
Lightholder declared some lifeboats
went back after the Titanic sank and
picked up men from the sea. The wit
ness described how the ship went down.
He said the ship tilted to the fore as it
was going down. The “crow’s nest’ was
described as being level with the water
when the bridge was entirely submerged.
“Was there any demonstration?" asked
Senator Smith. "No, sir.”
"There must have been 1500 people
aboard, and yet no lamentation?" "1
heard none. Not a sound."
Blown Out of the Sea.
Lightholder declared lie stood on top
of the officers' quarters and as the ship
took the dive he faced forward and took
a dive also.
"I was sucked against a blower and
held there," testified the officer.
"Head above water?" "No, sir. A ter
rific gust came up the blowers, the boil
ers must have exploded, and I was blown
clear."
“How far were you blown?” "Barely
clear. 1 was sucked down again, this
lime on the fidley grating.”
"Did anyone else have a similar ex
perience?" "Yes, Col. Grade."
"How did you get loose?” "I don't
know; may be another explosion. All
I know we came up by a boat.”
‘Were mere any water tight com
partments on that ship?" the senator
asked. "Certainly, 40 or 50."
"Were they known to passengers and
crew?” "Must have been—by the plans
distributed about the ship."
“Do you know whether any of the
crew or passengers took to these wa
tertight compartments as a last re
sort?" "It is quite impossible for me
to say, sir."
"Is it at all likely?" "I think very
unlikely."
“As for yourself, you preferred to
take to the open sea?” "Undoubtedly.”
"What other officers besides yourself
survived?” "The third, fourth and
fifth officers, sir."
'Their names?” "Mr. II. .T. Pittman,
third officer; .T. G. lloxhall, fourth of
ficer; Lowe, fifth officer," Lighthollder
said.
At this point the hearing was halted
at 7.12 U. M., to be resumed at 8.30,
when the surviving seamen from the
Titanic will he examined.
Marconi Operator Cottam.
New York, April 19.—Thomas Cot
tam, aged 21, of Liverpool, the Mar
oon! operator on tin* Carpathla, was
tlie llrst witness at the evening ses
sion.
He denied himself some glory by
saying he had no stated hours of
work on the Carpathla. Previous wit
nesses had testified he was not “on
duty" when he received the Titanic's
sputtering signals for help. He was
decidedly uncertain whether he was
required to work at night, hut finally
said that it depended upon whether
he had commercial or ship’s business
to get off."
“What were you doing last Sun
day evening, about 10 o'clock?" asked
Senator Smith. “Receiving news from
Cape Cod,” said Cottam. He said hr
I had also hern sending "a little ot
messages for the Titanic."
“What had you been doing just pro
eedltig ihe message from the Titan
ir?” "Keporting the day's communi
eatfon to the Bridge."
Had you closed your station for
the night'*” ‘No.”
“What do you do when you close
your station?" “Switch the storage,
battery out.” sa.d Cottam.
"Does that prevent receiving or
sending messages?” the senator con
tinued. "No.”
“Does it lessen the likelihood of
your getting a signal of any kind?"
“No, not in the least,” Cottam re
plied.
“You say the Carpathia’s wireless
instrument would send a message
about 2eO miles with accuracy?"
Yes, sir.”
"Well, how did you happen to catch
the Titanic's message of distress?” 1
was looking out for a confirmation by
the steamer Parisian of a previous
message from the Parisian—a message
that came some time in the afternoon.
“Did you hear the captain of the
C’arpathia testify here, today?" “No."
"He said you were about to retire
and caught this Titanic distress mes
sage, rather providential?” "Yes, sir.'
"How far had you gotten along in
your arrangements to retire" Had
you taken off your clothes?" “Yes,
my coat.”
“Did you have any instruments
then?" "Yes, the telephones were on
my head—I was waiting for the Paris
ian’s answer—I had just called her."
"How long would you have waited?’
"Several minutes.”
would you nave retired pretty
soon, you think'..Yes.”
"Well, what did you hear?” "1 didn
hear anything from the Parisian, just
then, hut first picked up Cape Cod
again sending Marconia news,” Cottam
said. "The Cape Cod relay service
kept up for several minutes. There
were messages for the Titanic which
I hoped to transfer the next morn
ing."
"When did you first hear from the
Titanic?" "Sunday afternoon, I had
a commercial message from the Ti
tanic for a passenger."
"Who was it for?” "A Mrs. Marshall."
"Was It answered?" asked Senator
Smith. “Yes, sir.”
"How far was ttie Titanic’s position
from yours, then?" "I don’t know, sit
"Weil, when you got the distress mes
sage from ttie Titanic, Sunday night, how
did you get It?" "I called lie Titanic
myself, sir."
“Who told you to call the Titanic?”
"A’o one, sir—I did it of my own free
will. I asked the Titanic operator if lie
was aware Cape Cod had been sending
messages for the Titanic.”
"Did you get an answer?” "Yes.”
“What was it?” Senator Smith asked.
‘Come at once,’ was the message, sir,”
said Cottam.
"Was that all of it?" “No. The opera
I mr said, I think, ‘Come at once—this is
a distress message. C. Q. D.,‘ Cottam
testified.
What did you do then?" "1 con
firmed the distress message by asking
the Titanic if I should report the dis
tress message to the captain of the
Carpathia.”
"tiet an answer?” ‘‘Yes, right away."
"What prompted you to confirm the
message before delivering it to the
captain? Do you always confirm it?"
"No.”
Are you Instructed to do that or U
it a matter of discretion?" “Matter oi*
discretion," said Cottam.
“Have you ever been misled by
messages that were without founda
tion?" "No, sir.”
“What would you have done if the
Titanic had not confirmed her mes
sage.’’ “I would have reported tit
message to the commander,” said Cot
tam.
“How much time elapsed after you
received the Titanic's distress messag
before you reported it to Capt. Ros
tran?" “About a couple of minutes.”
Cottam (answered.
When word of the Titanic's distres.1
was received, Operator Cottam said l.e
immediately sent the position of the Cai
pathia and added that they would hurty
to the rescue.
“Get any reply to that?” asked Senator
Smith. “Yes, sir, immediately. They ac
knowledged receipt of it.”
The witness said the next communica
tion from the Titanic was four minutes
later when he confirmed the positions of
i both vessels. At this juncture the Frank
I furt of the North German Lloyd Line
I broke in on the communication, bavin
heard the Titanic's call for help. I-ator
the steamship Olympic also replied.
“What did you do then?" asked Sena
i tor Smith. “I called hie attention of the
i Titanic to the Olympic’s efforts to raise
it," answered the witness. "The Titanic
replied site could not hear because of me
rush of air and the noise made by the
escaping steam."
lmmeriately after telling the Titanic of
the Olympic’s effort to get. in communi
cation with her, the former, the witness
said, sought the Olympic's aid, reporting
that she was "hold down” and giving
her position. The Baltic broke in at this
time, but its efforts to reach the Titanic
were wit In) lit avail.
"I was In communication with the Ti
tanic nt regular intervals until the final
message,” said Cottam. "This was 'Come
quick; our engine roam is filling up to
the boilers.’
Senator Smith asked Cottam whether
he answered these messages at his own
discretion. “No, sir,” said tile witness,
“I always reported .them personally to
the captain
"Where?” “On the bridge.”
"Then you left your post each time a
message was received?” asked the sena
tor, in surprise. “Yes.”
The witness said the last message
he sent to the doomed Titanic telling
of the Carpathla’s rush to the rescue,
probably never reached the ship. He
was asked why he so believed. “I
don’t know," he replied. "I received,
no acknowledgement and thtii, to my
mind, was significant.”
Cottam said that when the Titanic's
survivors were picked up he worked
practically continuously until Tues
day, when lie fell asleep at his post,
lie could not tell when he dropped,
from exhaustion nor when he awoke.
“What was your condition?" asked
Senator Smith. “I was desperately
tired; I was worked out," answered
Cottam, who was then excused.
Refused to Leave Husband.
How Mrs. lsndor Straus refused to
leave her husband and live was told
the committee by Alfred Crawford of
Southampton, bedroom steward on the
Titanic. He said she told her maid
to get Into a lifeboat at which Craw
ford was assigned to help man. “Mrs.
Straus put rnc foot into the boat and
then changed her mind. Mr. Straus
was standing away back from her.
She said to him: ‘We have been living
together a number of years; we are
not going to separate now.’ Ho added
that the maid was saved.
Crawford said that lie saw ,t. Hruce
Ismay on tlie boat deck with First
Oliicer Murdock lowering a lifeboat.
”i think it was the third Dost on the
starboard side of the ship that they
were lowering.” said Crawford. "I
saw Mr. Ismay helping ladies into that
boat and then saw him and First Of
ficer Murdock lowering- the boat into
the sea.”
"Did you see Director Ismay get into
any of the lifeboats?” Senator Smith
asked. ”1 did not, sir," Crawford an
swered.
The committee adjourned at 1.20
o’clock to meet at 10 o'clock, tomorrow
morning.
DEAD LIST UNCHANGED.
(Continued from Page One.)
sented him with a loving' cup.
Although several consistent accounts
of wlmt happened aboard the Titanic
have been obtained from survivors, it
was manifestly impossible for any one
fully to take account of all that oc
curred on her great decks, four city
flocks in length. Thus, there are those
who maintain that there were one
or more suicides among the officers,
'apt. Smith, it would appear from
the consensus of stories, went down
with iiis ship, but several passengers
say that First Officer Murdock shot
himself through the head before she
sank. Among others who hold this
view is Mrs. George D. Widener of
Philadelphia, whose husband and son
were drowned.
The 200 rescued members of the Ti
tanic’s crew were still in New York,
tonight, sheltered on the Red Star
liner Lapland. With few exceptions
they are silent as to what happened
aboard the sinking liner. They will
lie returned to England, but not until
they have been held long enough to
permit some of them to testify before
the Senate committee.
The greatest problem confronting
the committee appointed to provide
for tlie survivors has been the steer
age passengers. Speaking no English
and in many eases ignorant of their
destinations, frightened, without
friends or relatives, their plight was
acute until Interpreters from the In
ternational Institute for Young
Women, a branch of the Y M A
circulated among them, today. and
apportioned them as befitted their na
tionality among tile vast foreign ipiar
ter in New York.
More than $211,000, including $0000
from Andrew Carnegie, has already
been subscribed for the sufferers, amt
a series of benefits to raise more mon
ey has been arranged.
Most of the wealthy and more
prominent survivors have left the city,
among them Mrs. Charles M. Hays,
wife of the late president of the Grand
Trunk Railway. He met death in the
disaster, but Mrs. Hays and her
daughter were saved. They left for
Montreal, tonight, on a special train.
Mrs. John Jacob Astor remained se
cluded in the’ Astor residence, hero,
too ill, according to her physicians, to
make any statement. No word from
her husband has come to the outside
world since Col. Astor kissed her good
live and placed her in the life boat.
PROBING TO THE BOTTOM.
(Continued from Page*One.)
one Berthon boat had not been
launched, it having got jammed, mak
ing 1G liteboats and four Berthon boats
accounted for. By tfie time we had
cleared first boat it was breaking day
and i could see all within an area of
four miles. We also saw that we were
surrounded by icebergs, large and
small, and three miles to the northwest
of us a huge field of drift ice with
large and small bergs in it, the ice
field trending from northwest round
west and south to southeast as far
ar, we could see either way.
At 8 A. M. the Beyland steamship
Californian came up. I gave him the
principal news and asked him 1o
search and 1 would proceed to New
York.
At S.50 we proceeded at full speed.
While re-searching over the vicinity
of the disaster and while we were get
ting people aboard I gave orders to
get spare hands along and swing in
al! our boats, disconnect the fall and
heist up as many Titanic boats as pos
sible in our davits; also got some on
fo-castle heads by derricks. We got
13 lifeboats, six on forward deck and
seven in davits. After getting all sur
vivors aboard and while searching, I
got a clergyman to offer a short prayer
of thankfulness for those sav»>d and
also a short burial service for their
loss, in saloon. Before deciding defi
nitely where to make for I conferred
with Mr. Ismay and thought he told
me what 1 though best, I informed
him. taking everything into consider
ation I considered New York best. I
knew we should require clean blank
ets, provisions and clean linen, even
If we went to the Azores, as most of
tile passengers saved were women
and children and they hysterical, not
knowing what medical attention they
might require, thought it best to go to
Now York. I also thought it would be
better for Mr. Ismay to go to New
York or England as soon as possible
and knowing T should be out of wire
less communication very soon if 1 pro
ceeded to the Azores, it left Halifax,
Boston and New York, so I cliose the
latter.
"Again passengers were ail hysterical
about ice, and I pointed out to Mr. Ismay
the possibilities of seeing Ice if 1 went to
Halifax.
“Then I knew from the gravity of the
disaster that it would be best to keep In
touch with land stations as best I could.
We have experienced very great difficul
ty in transmitting news, also names of
survivors. Our wireless is very poor and
again we have had so many interruptions
from other ships and also messages from
shore (principally press, which we ig
nored). I gave instructions to send first
all official messages, then names of pas
sengers, then survivors’ private mes
sages.
"We had haze, early Tuesday morning,
for several hours; again more or less on
Wednesday from 5.30 P. M. to 6 P. M.
strong south-southwesterly winds and
clear weather, Thursday, with moderate
rough sea.
"I am pleased to say that all survivors
have been very plucky. The majority of
women, first, second and third class, lost
their husbands and, considering ull, they
have done wonderfully well. Tuesday,
our doctor reported all survivors physi
cally well. Our first class passengers
have behaved splendidly, given up their
cabins voluntarily and supplied the la
dles witli clothes, etc. We all turned out
Hale’s Honey
Of Horehound and Tar
r'The most reliable remedy of its kind. Contains no^B
opium nor nylhing injurious. Nothing better for
Coughs and Colds
Your druprj?»*t sells it
When It Aches Again
Try Pike's Toothache Drops
of our cabins anors: saloon, smoking room, library, ate.,
also being used for sleeping accommo
dations. Our crew also turned out to
let tile crew of the Titanic take their
quarters. 1 am pleased to state that ow
ing to preparations made for the comfort
of survivors, none were the worse for ex
posure, etc. 1 beg to specially mention
how willing and cheerful the whole of the
ship's company behaved, receiving the
highest praise from everybody. And I
can assure you 1 am very proud to have
such a company under my command.
iSignedi "A. H. IlOSTltON.
"Captain of the R. M. ft. Carpathta.”
The Southern and Safe Route.
Washington, April 19.—('apt. Charles
A. McAllister, engineer-in-chief of the
revenue cutter service, said, today:
"The hydrographic reports show
that the distance from Queenstown
to New York by the southern and
safe route is 2939 miles; by the north
ern route, the one taken by the Ti
tanic, the distance is 292:; miles. In
the desire to have the time cut down,
only five hours on tho maiden voyage
of tiiis, the greatest steamer ever con
structed, 1 fifth souls have been sent to
eternity."
TAKING DUE PRECAUTIONS.
Some Naval Men Cannot Feel to Deep
ly Blame Capt. Smith.
Washington, April 19.—Other persons
than thi naval hydrographer. Capt
Knapp, are of :':e opinion that it is
premature to attach Homo to Capt.
Smith, the commander of the Titanic,
for striking an iceberg against which
lie had been warned.
ope high government ollu-ial, himself
a veteran trans-Atlantic passenger,
who Inis been analyzing the oUicinl re
ports of the disaster, asserts that as
a matter of fact after being warned
of tin presence of an iceberg ill his
piith, Capt. Smith as an extra precau
tion look his vessel southward and
was fully 40 miles in that direction
from the point where the berg was lo
cated, when he struck another, the
existence of which no one knew.
The same official says that the hy
drographic charts and reports show
that criticism of the Titanic's com
mander for not taking the southern
course Is entirely misplaced, tiecause
the Titanic was actually CO miles
south fcf the regular course at this
season, and was even in danger of a
head-on collision with steamers east
bound, entitled to right of way by
the- rules of the sen.
Baseball Benefit for Survivors.
New York, April 19.—President John.
Brush of the New York National
League Baseball Club, announced, to
day, that the Giants would play an
exhibition same with the New York
American League club, next Sunday
afternoon, April 21, at the Polo
grounds for the benefit of the desti
tute survivors of the Titanic. The
game will be called at 3 o'clock.
CAPT. SMITH’S DEATH.
Seaman Says “Was Washed Over
board, But Refused Assistance.”
New York, April 19.—At the Ameri
can Seaman's Friendly Society's In
stitute, where 151) members of the res
cued crew of the Titanic are being
fed, clothed and housed, G. A Hogg,
able seaman, told, tonight, of the last
of Capt. Smith. Hogg says that as the
Titanic sank a big wave washed him
over the side and he landed on a raft
carrying 35 persons.
"The next moment I saw Capt.
Smith in the water alongside the raft.
'There’s the skipper,' I yelled, ’give
him a hand,’ and they did. But he
shook himself’free and shouted to us:
•Good-bye, boys, I'm going to follow
the ship.' That was the last we saw
Of our skipper."
Hogg said that laicr they were trans
ferred to a lifeboat in which there was
a woman stark naked. She was numb
with the cold, and some of the men took
off their clothes and wrapped her up in
them, but she died soon after.
A. Schiiss, a fireman, said: “The ti
tanic was going 22 1-2 knots an hour, at
top speed, when she struck the Iceberg.
I know, for 1 was in the engine room. 1
saw Murdock, the first officer, shr t down
eight or nine Portuguese in tile steerage
for pushing women back and trying to
get into the lifeboats ahead of them.
OPERATOR PHILLIPPS A HERO.
Sticks to Post on Titanic—Then Loses
His Life.
New York, April 19.—Phillipps. the
first Marconi operator aboard tHe Ti
tanic, stuck to his post until the last,
jumped from the sinking ship, was
tailed aboard tlie life raft and died be
fore rescuers reached him, according
to tiie story told here, today, by
Thomas IVliitely, who was a waiter in
the “uloon of the Titanic.
Whitely is in St.. Vincent’s hospital
suonng from a fractured leg and nu
merous bruises.
"Phillipps was on the overturned
lifeboat with me,’’ said Whitely. "He
was dead when taken aboard the Cal'
pathia. They tried to revive him with
brandv and all that, hut it was too
late. There were four burials at sea
one sailor, two firemen and Phillipps.
It is believed flint Whitely’p stories
clear the doubt surrounding the iden
tity Carpnthia.
It was at first believed that this man
was a cabin passenger, but Whitely
declares it was Phillipps.
“I helped fill the boats with women,"
Whitely said. “Collapsible Boat No. 2
on the starboard jammed. The second
officer was hacking at the ropes with
a knife. 1 was being dragged around
the deck by that rope when I looked
up and saw the boat, with all aboard,
turn turtle. In some way I got over
board myself and clung to an oak
dresser. I was more than GO feet from
the Titanic when she went down.
Her big stern rose up in the air
and she went down bow first. I saw
all tile machinery drop out of her.
"Dunns the half hour I was in the
water I could hear the cries of thou
sands of persons, it seemed, although
there must have been only hundreds.
I drifted near a boat wrongside up.
About 30 men were clinging to her and
they retused to let me get aboard.
Someone tried to hit me with an oar,
but scrambled aboard.
“There was a bit of panic when tt
first iiapjiened. The officers had to use
their revolvers. The chief officer shot
one man—1 didn't see this, but three
others did—and then he shot himself.
But everybody, pretty much, behaved
splendidly, especially the firemen.
"It was a black berg we struck and
although the night was perfectly clear,
it was impossible to se>‘ that color. I
saw another like it when we were
drifting on the overturned lifeboat."
PITIABLE SCENES
Again Witnessed. Friday Morning, at
London White Star Offices.
London, April 19.—Pitiable scenes
were again witnessed at the White
Star odices in London, this morning
One woman who had kept vigil
throughout the day and most of the
night since the first news of the dis
usti r eatne, found in the list posted at
tile olhee the name she had been wait
ing for and rushed Into the street
shrieking: “He is saved
Memorial services for the dead were
held at noon, in St. Haul's cathedral,
and were attended by.the members of
the enldnet nml of the diplomats'
corps, among whom were Ambassador
Whitelaw Hold and Mrs. Reid and
other distinguished personages. The
W hite Star Co. and the International
Mercantile Co. were also represented.
A memorial service is to be held iti
St. Patrick's cathedral, Dublin, Suh
da y.
The lord mayor and sheriffs of the
city of London were present at the
service at St. Paul’s. Thousands of the
public were unable to gain admittance
te the cathedral. The wjtole congrega
tion stood while a military band
played the “Dead Match'' from Saul.
Hundreds of women and men broke
down and sobs were audible through
out the edifice. Alexander Carlisle, the
designer of the Titanic, who was
among the congregation, was so af
fected that he fainted and had to be
carried out.
MANY SHOOT THEMSELVES.
According to Reports, Rather Than
Freeze or Drown.
Providence, R. I., April 19.—That
many of the men passengers on the
Titanic shot themselves rather than
he drowned or frozen, is a statement
contained in the story of Howard M.
Chapin, a correspondent of the News,
who was a passenger on the Carpathia.
There was no confusion, however, he
declared, and many of the passengers
who were taken from the boats by the
Carpathia regarded the matter very
lightly until the last.
Few of the lifeboats were full but
those in them would not go back to
hel; nick up others for fear of being
swa.oped, although the officers in
charge ordered the men to row back.
Mrs. Walter Clark in one of the
boats wanted to go back but the other
women objected and it is said they
offered their jewels to the sailors if
they would not row back but Mrs.
Clark turned to Mrs. Astor and begged
her to help and together they persuad
ed the men to go back and so succeed
ed in saving eight persons.
Bieriot, the aviator, was on the Ti
tanic but was saved.
SAVES HER DOG.
Woman Succeeds in Safely Landing
Pet on Board Carpathia.
New York, April 19.—A narrative of
the disaster to the Titanic is prepared
by one of the stewards of the rescuing
ship Carpathia contains the following:
"One of the earlier boats to arrive was
seen to contain a woman tenderly
clasping a pet Pomeranian. When as
sisted to the rope ladder and while the
rope was being fastened around her
she emphatically refused to give up
for a second the dog which was evi
dently so much to her.”
The steward further says that a stir-,
vlvor told him that one woman de
clined to leave the Titanic because
they would not take o a pet dog be
longing to her.
WILL CONTROL WIRELESS.
Government Will Enact Legislation
With That End in View.
Washington, April 19.—Tho govern
ment's inability to get early informa
tion regarding the loss of the Titanic,
through the wireless outfits of the
cruisers Chester and Salem or the
naval shore stations, has confirmed the
'navy department in its decision to
press for legislation by Congress which
will enable the government to assert
control over all agencies, whether pri
vate or corporate, which may seek to
restrain or interfere with the govern
ment offifflcials In such cases as this.
Secretary Meyer, who was one of the
parties to the conference recently heldl
at tiie White House on the subject-of
wireless control, is giving the subject
much attention and either from the
navy department or the department of
commerce and labor a bill will soon
emerge which it is hoped, will be' ac
cepted by Congress as a basis for Its
action.
Guido Mazzareltl, a local leader of the
Industrial Workers of tho World, was
arrested, Friday night, at Lynn, Mass.,
I on an Indictment charging him with con
spiracy, which was returned with other
indictments against persons prominent in
the Lawrence strike by the grand jury at
Newburyport, Thursday. The indictment
upon which lie was arrested was secret.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86075094/1912-04-19/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Titanic Meets Terrible
Disaster-1350 Lives Lost
World*» Largest Ship Goes Down— Strikes Iceberg-Dis
tinguished Men Die in Tragedy of Deep.
7 Survivors Go Insane.


I
I
i
Sinking of Titanic, world's greatest
vessel, on maiden voyage across At
lantic appalls two continents. Dis
tinguished men die in tragedy of deep,
Colonel John Jacob Astor, President
Taft's military aide and other noted
persons unaccounted for. The magni-,
tude of the wreck of the liner Titantic
has been but little mitigated by the
fragmentory information which has
drifted in today. The rescuing steam
ship Capathia has S 68 survivors ac
cording to the latest notes received
at the offices of the White Star lines
In New York. This increases the list
of deaths abc it 200 from the number But except for this the
favorable details are insignificant
compared with the fact that the Ti
tanic is at the bottom of the Atlantic
and that the shattered wreck took
with her about 1,350 victims. The
first reports giving the total surviv
ors at 675 were varied by favorable
news early today from Captain Ros-
tram of the Carpathia who gave the
number at about 800 and later by the
positive announcement of the White
Star line that there are 868 survivors
of the Titanic on the Carpathia. But
with these revised figures there re
main 1,350 persons, passengers and
I
crew of the Titanic, who now are un
accounted for, apparently. Hope clung
desperately to the belief that the
steamships Virginian and Parisian of
the Allen line may have picked up
survivors in addition to those on the
Carpathia, but this was dispelled with
the wireless station yesterday when
they reported that the Parisian had
no survivors and when the officers of
the Allen line in Montreal issued a
statement that the Virginian had sent
them a wireless message saying they
"had arrived at the scene of the dis
aster too late to be of service." The
Parisian has proceeded on her way
for Europe and the Carpathia is com
ing in slowly to New York. All hopes
for details of the tragedy and its ef
fects are centered on this ship; she
will he within wireless communication
with Sable island tonight, with Nan
tucket on Thursday and will reacli
New York some time Thursday next.
Greatest Marine Disaster.
The Titanic catastrophe Is the great
est marine disaster in time of peace
in the history of the world; the loss
in lives and money, according to the
best authentic reports, is as follows:
Lives lost, about 1,400. Cost to build
Titanic, $13,000,000. Estimated value
of jewels carried by women passen
gers placed at $5,000,000. Value of
baggage and mail, $2,000,000. Loss
from probable lawsuits and litigations,
$5,000,000.
$1,000,000,000 of Wealth.
New York, April 16.—The combined
wealth of the first class passengers
who are believed to have gone down
with the Titanic will easily reach one
billion dollars. The fortunes of six
of the male passengers alone aggre
gates more than half a billion dollars.
If these men have met death vast
business interests in America and in
England are sure to be affected. The
six men are: Colonel John Jacob As
tor, $150,000,000; Colonel Washington
Roebling, $25,000,000; Isadore Straus,
$50,000,000; George B. Widener, $50,
000,000; Benjamin Guggenheim, $95,
000,000; J. B. Thayer, $10,000,000. The
men mentioned are interested in some
of the biggest corporations in the
world. In addition to being one of
the world's largest real estate holders
C olonel Astor is connected with nearly
a score of corporations. Benjamin
Guggenheim of the American Smelting
Securities company comes next in fi
nancial importance. Besides his hold
ings in the smelter industries he is
interested in a number of other West
ern corporations as dierctor. Isadore
Straus is one of the world's best
i known merchants, while George B.
j Widener is connected with the Wide
ner-Elkins society. Colonel Washing
is
j
ton Roebling, with his father, design- 1
ed and built the Brooklyn bridge and
is president and director of the John
A. Röchlings Sons company. I. B.
Thayer is well known in railroad cir
cles, being vice-president of the Penn
sylvania railway.
Titanic Deathbed Is Deep.
Halifax, N. S., April 16.—The death
bed of the $13,000,000 steamer Titanic
and of boats dragged down with her
is two miles beneath the surface of
the sea. This calculation was made
by officers of the government marine
department here who find that depth
on the marine chart at the point where
the Titanic went down. The location
is midway between Cape Race and
Sable Istnnd and in line with those
dangerous sands
might have proved
which, however,
a place of safety
had there been time to run the Titanic
there and beach it..
Montreal. April 16.—The last hope
that additional Titanic passengers are
saved was dispelled here today when
Captain Ganbell of the Virginian re
ported to the Allen line agents here
that the Virginian's efforts at rescue
were fruitless. His message read, "we
arrived too late to rescue anyone and
are sailing to Liverpool." This is ac
cepted as meaning that all the passen
gers went down except the survivors
aboard the Carpathia.

New York, April 16.—All New \ork
is stunned today by the appalling loss
of life to passengers aboard the
wrecked White Star liner Titanic
which was supposed to have been un
sinkable. Along the line of docks
men, women and children seized the
officers of the White Star line begging
for some definite information.
Photos at Fairchild's Studio.
Seattle Plage to be at Half Mast
Seattle, Wash., April 18.—Seattle
will lower its flags to half mast to
morrow when the rescuing steamer
Carpathia will land tlié widows and
orphans of the greatest sea disaster
in history. Mayor Cottrill this morn
ing expressed the hope that the big
gc-st city in the northwest would show
this token of deep sympathy. "It is
very little to do," the mayor said, "yet
if this note of sympathy from all over
the country should lighten the burden
of the grief-laden it will have accom
plished much."
Order 250 Coffin«.
New York, April IS.—A bulletin in
the Wall street offices today says the
Carpathia has wired for 250 coffins to
meet them at the dock for survivors
who have since died. Congress has
appointed a committee to board the
Carpathia before any one else is al
lowed to do so, for the purpose of In
vestigating. Ismay is severely criti
cized for not allowing wireless opera
tor to furnish a more detailed report.
Young Astor Thinks Father Alive.
New York, April 18.—"I know dad
is still living; I feel It," declared Vin
cent Astor, 20 years old, heir to the
Astor millions, today. Young Astor
positively refuses to believe that his
father, Col. John Jacob Astor, w'ent
down with the liner Titanic. He is
spending his time closeted with a few
intimate friends, alternately giving
way to violent bursts of grief and
rushing to the telephone to set in mo
tion some new resource of the Astor
millions in an attempt to learn his
father's fate.
ISMAY TRYING TO
ESCAPE TROUBLE
New York, April 18.—It is reported
about the White Star line offices here
today that J. Bruce Ismay, director of
that line, who was taken aboard the
Capathia with the passengers rescued
from the Titanic, sent a wireless to
the captain of the steamer Cedric,
which is scheduled to sail from this
port at noon today, to wait at the
lower end of the bay until the Carpa
thia arrives tonight and take Ismay
aboard and sail with him to England.
Officials of the White Star line say
that the report is unconfirmed. It is
reported that Ismay planned this move
to escape any trouble when the Carpa
thia docks at New York.
Ismay Guarding the Reports.
Newport, R. I., April lb.—Code mes
sages from the liner Carpathia to the
White Star line headquarters were
picked up here today. The messages
are believed to contain the details of
the Titanic disaster; the fact that he
messages are in code shows that J.
Bruce ismay of the White Star line
who was taken from the Titanic to
the Carpathia with the rescued is care
fully guarding all reports of what hap
pened after the Titanic struck.
j Titanic Sunk Soon After Striking.
Halifax, N. S., April 18.—It is re
ported here that Captain Hanes of the
liner Carpathia received a message
from the liner Olympic that the Ti
1 tan j c g t j oom was expected immediate
j y a ft er s h e struck the iceberg, mak
ing a hole in the vessel which caused
it to founder. Captain Hanes is also
credited with saying that the Titanic's
wireless was put out of commission
fifteen minutes after the smash.
OFFICIALS GIVE
OUT FULL NEWS
New York, April 17.—Vice-president
Franklin of the White Star line was
criticized yesterday for his definite re
assuring declarations of Monday which
tended, it is alleged, to mislead the
public. Franklin yesterday afternoon
gave to the public the full text of the
message received from Captain Had
dock of Olymphia Monday afternoon.
The reason I did not give it out Mon
day night," Mr. Franklin said, "was
because it was so discouraging that I
felt it would not be right to alarm
,j, e p U tjj C unnecessarily. Now that the
worgt j s known 1 am willing to give
t out Here j t j s; "The Carpathia
reac h e d the Titanic's position at day
break; found boats and wreckage only,
Titanic had foundered about 2:20 a.
m in position 41 degrees and 15 min-
utes nor th, 50 degrees and 14 minutes
wegti boats accounted for. About
675 souls have been saved of the cerw
and passengers. Latter nearly all are
wojnen a nd children. Lealand line
j gteams bip California remaining and is
searching exact position of disaster,
j ar p a tj,ia returning to New York with
j gurvivorB please inform Cunard.
Signed,
H. Y. X. HADDOCK."
Girl wanted to
Commercial hotel.
work in kitchen
WILL REACH
N. Y. TOMORROW
New York, April 18.—Late this after
noon the situation as to the sinking
of the gigantic liner Titanic and the
rescue of a minor part of the passen
gers is about as follows: The Carpa
thia probably will not dock before to
morrow morning in New York because
of a heavy fog. Director Ismay of the
White Star line has been requested
to give out all details of the wreck.
Carpathia Nears New York.
New York, April 18.—The Carpathia
reported by wireless at 10 o'clock this
morning that she was then 75 miles
east by south of Block Island and 140
miles from Ambrose Light at the en
trance of New' York harbor.
Seven Survivors Insane.
New York, April 18.—The first offi
cial information indicating that some
of the survivors of the Titanic were
sick and may be in a serious condition
caused from exposure and by being
tossed about in life boats before being
rescued by the Carpathia. Today
when the officials of the White Star
line accepted an offer from St. Luke's
hospital to set aside its new hospital
addition for the use of the sick sur
vivors of the Titanic. It is reported
that seven of the survivors of the ship
are insane from the exposure and a
number of others are seriously ill.
The White Star officials positively re
fused to discuss the condition of the
survivors.
None But Those on Carpathia Saved.
New York, April 18.—The Wall
Street News press today posted copy
of a message purporting to have been
received from Captain Rostrom of the
Carpathia by wireless to Highland
Point, declaring that no one was saved
from the Titanic except those on the
Carpathia and that of these survivors
100 are in the ship's hospital. The
message stated further that the body
of Colonel John Jacob Astor is not on
board the Carpathia and that Mrs.
Astor is dangerously ill.
Mrs. Astor Reported Dying.
New York, April IS.—Insistent re
ports prevail here today that Mrs. As
tor, girl wife of Colonel John Jacob
Astor, who went down on the Titanic
is dying on board the Carpathia. The
Astor family declared that they have
received no such report.
TO SUMMON SUR
VIVORS TO WASH.
Washington, April 17.—Survivors of
the Titanic disaster will be summoned
to Washington to tell committee of
Congress the facts concerning the in
ability of steamship officials to save
the lives of all passengers on the
liner. Representatives Alexander of
Missouri, Chairman of the House com
mittee on merchant lines and fisheries,
today announced an investigation in
which the passengers will give chief
testimony. The action was adopted in
the Senate this afternoon directing
the committee or a sub-committee to
make a thorough probe of the Titanic
ragedy and to empower the committee
to summon witnesses and take any
necessary steps in the investigation.
The department of commerce and
labor will take up at once with Presi
dent Taft the entire subject of safe
guarding ocean travel by more strin
gent American shipping regulations,
This department has aroused Con
gross, President Taft and the cabinet
to the urgent need for immediate
measures of safety for oceanic travel.
It is believed laws will be prepared
at once in Congress on the advice of
officials of the department of com
merce and labor and American ship
ping experts which will insure safety
passengers and crew in cases like
■■nt. when ample time exist,d
for their removal in life boats.
Wife of Captain Issues Statement.
Southampton, England, April IS.—
The following statement was issued
here today by Mrs. Elanor Smith, wife
of Captain E. J. Smith of the liner Ti
tanic, who went down with his ship:
'To my poor fellow-sufferers; my
heart overflows with grief for you
am laden with sororw for you and am
weighed down by this terrible burden
which has been thrust upon us. Pray
Glji be with us and comfort us all'."
Terrible Scenes at White Star Office.
Southampton, England, April IS.—
Terrible scenes were enacted here to
day at the offices of the White Star
line which are being stormed by the
wives, children and sweethearts of
the crew of the Titanic, who were all
picked seamen, representing South
ampton's seagoing aristocracy. Women
and children pleaded pitiously for a
list of the survivors of the crew.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014248/1912-04-22/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>"What was the last message sent tn
tile Titanic'.”' ashed Senator Smith.
"Wo sent it word to have its life
boats ready.*' said the witness. "W c
told them our lifeboats were ready and
that we were steaming to them as fast
as we could.”
Senator Smith asked the witnraa i.
he had received any message from tin
time the CarpaUtia left the scene o(
the disaster until she reached New
York.
The intention was to discover wheth
er any official was seeking to keep the
news of the disaster quiet.
“No, sir,” answered t’ottani. "1 re
ported the entire matter myself to the
steamship Baltic at 10.30, Monday
morning.'*
"What did you say?" asked the sen
ator.
"I told them we had been to the
wreck and had picked up as many of
the passengers as we could."
The witness said the ship was first
headed for Halifax. Pater, he said,
the captain changed his course and
headed for New York. He could not
remember when the change of course
was made.
At this juncture Senator Reed of
Missouri took a seat alongside Senator
Smith and Senator Newlands, and the
three interrupted the hearing to en
gage in a whispered conference with
Senator Reed, prepared to assist in the
examination. The questioning of the
witness was then resumed.
"Did you send any message that all
the passengers had been saved or that
the Titanic was being towed to Hali
fax?" asked Senator Smith.
"No, sir."
•'Nor any tiling like it?’’
"No, sir."
uuuaiii uiaei lam us tu wiuil
messages he sent to the Virginian or
the Californian, but he denied in mon
osyllabic replies that he said to any
one that the passengers were saved
or the Titanic was in tow.
“Did you know such reports were
being published to the world?"
"No, sir.”
"If the White Star Dine sent a mes
sage, Monday, reading: •llepresenta
tive J. H Hughes, Huntington, W.
Va.—Titanic proceeding to Halifax.
Passengers will probably land there,
Wednesday. All safe.’ They did not
obtain the information on which that
was based from you?"
"No.”
“Nor do you know tlutt it obtained
It from any other operator on the
Carptahia?”
"No.”
"Were you on duty, Monday?”
"Yes.”
"What hours?"
“I don’t know."
Cottam said he was at work until
Wednesday.
Cottam repeated ids testimony of
Friday and said he had been without
sleep throughout Sunday. Monday,
Tuesday and all day Wednesday.
Senator Smith sought to have the wit
ness designate the exact hour when
he was relieved by Operator Bride,
who had been taken aboard the Car
pathia from the Titanic.
”1 don't know, sir,” said Cottam in
extenuation. "I was up continuously
and I lost track of the hours and
days. I had from eight to 10 hours'
sleep from the time we left the wreck
until we arrived in New York.
“Did Bride do any sending during
that time’’" Senator Smith asked.
“Yes. sir. he sent the list of the
third-class passengers to the cruiser
Chester."
“Any other message?"
"Several, I don’t remember what
they were. The records are on the
Carpathla."
Senator Smilli then called what lie
evidently expected to be one of the
must imporiam witnesses, riaroiu s.
Bride, the sale surviving- -wireless op
erator of the Titanic. Crippled as a
result of his experiences he was
wheeled in an Invalid's chair to the
table where the committee sat.
“Contrary to the usual procedure,"
said Senator Smith, rising in his place,
"I must place you under oath. Raise
your right hand.”
Tlie witness, hand uplifted, listened
while the senator repeated the oath.
Then he bowed In assent. Bride said
■he was a native of I»ndon, 22 years
old, and had learned his profession
in a British school of telegraphy.
“What practical experience have you
had?” asked Senator Smith.
'T have crossed to the States three
times and to Brazil twice,’ said Bride
A phalanx of flashlight photogra
phers exploded u powder just after
Bride took the witness stand.
Senator Smith said the interruption
by the photographers was "beyond
toleration."
Bride remembered receiving and
sending messages relative to the speed
of the Titanic on its trial tests. After
leaving Southampton, on the Titanic's
fatal trip, he could not remember re
ceiving or sending any messages for
Isinay. Senator Smith asked particu
larly about messages on Sunday.
“1 don’t renu mber, sir: there was so
much business Sunday,” he said.
He was asked if Capt. Smith re
ceived or sent any messages Sunday.
"So, sir,” was the reply.
“How do you know he did not?"
"Because I see the messages Mr.
Phillips takes when they are made
up.”
“Where these for Sunday made up?'
"No; they never were.”
After testifying he made no perma
nent record of the iceberg warnings.
Bride insisted he gave the memoran
dum of th warning to the officer on
the watch. The name of the officer he
could not tell.
“I knew the officers by sight but
not by name.” h»- said.
The operator said lie did not inform
Capt. Smith.
Bride said he was in bed when the
Impact came. Ho was not alarmed at
the collision and remained in lied
about 10 minutes. He saw Phillips in
the operating room.
He told me he thought the boat had
been injured in some way, and he ex
pected it would have to go back to the
builders, said Bride.
The witness said that according to
arrangements he relieved Phillips. -Im
mediately the captain came in and said
we had better send cut a call for as
sistance,” teslified Bride. “Phillips
asked if he wanted to send a distress
alt The captain said h- did I could
read what Phillips sent—C Q. D.
How soon did he get a reply?
.\k far as I know, immediately; l
ol id not hear what he received, h«w
ever.
The witness told of having intercept
il ii message from the falifornian In
tended for the Haltlc, which told of the
presence of three butte icebergs in the
vicinity of the former vessel.
I gave the message to the captain
personally. he said.
•I would like to know just what the
message said. Senator Smith sug
gested.
Wei. sir, I did not take it down,''
Bride replied. The Californian was
seeking out the Baltic, and I merely
noted that it was tin ice report and
told the captain.”
Under a lire of questions Bride ac
knowledged that a half-hour previous
ly, or at t.30, Sunday afternoon, he
was working on his accounts in the
wireless room when he heard the Cali
fornian trying to raise the Titanic. He
did not respond, he said, because lie
was busy.
You had the telephone apparatus at
your ear? inquired Senator Smith in
surprise.
Yes, sir.
And you did not respond to the
call?”
No, sir.
Then a half-hour later on, about
live hours before the disaster, you
took the message, when it was intend
ed for another vessel, the Baltic?
Yes, sir.
in an effort to determine whether
the signal C. Q. I). might not have
been misunderstood by passing ships,
Senator Smith called upon Mr. Mar
coni.
What is the meaning of the signal?
Mr. Marconi was asked.
The C. Q. said Mr. Marconi. “is
an international signal, which meant
that all stations should cease sending
ece.it the one using the call. The D.
was added to indicate danger. The call,
however, now has been superseded by
the universal call, ‘S. O. S.
Senator Smith then resumed the di
rect rumination of Bride, who has
said the North German Lloyd Liner
Frankfurt was the first to answer the
Titanics distress signal.
Have you heard it said that the
Frankfurt was the ship nearest to the
Titanic? the senator said.
Yes, sir; Mr. Phillips told me that
I he Frankfurt was the nearest ship.
How did he know?
“By the strength of the signals,
said the witness, who added that the
Carpalhia answered shortly after.
The witness said that 20 minutes
later the Frankfurt operator inter
rupted to ask: What was the matt
er?
What did you reply? the senator
inquired.
r Phillipps said he was a fool and
told him to keep out.
Hid Mr. Phillipps try further for
the Frankfurt?
No, sir.
Hid you or Mr. Phillipps ever get
the Frankfurts position?
No, sir.
Time after time Senator Smith ask
ed in varying forms why the Titanic
did not explain in detail its condition
to the Frankfurt.
Any operator receiving C. Q. H.
and the position of the ship, if he is on
the job,” said Bride, would tell the
eaptain at onee.
Ask him if it would have taken
longer to have sent You are a fool,
keep out, than We are sinking, sug
gested Senator Reed,
Senator Smith for the time contin
ued the point he had in mind.
Was your object in dismissing the
somewhat tardy inquiry of the Frank
furt due to your desire to hang on to
a certainty, the Carpathia? inquired
Senator Smith.
The witness said it was.
But under the circumstances could
you not with propriety have sene a
detailed message to the Frankfurt?”
Senator Smitli insisted.
I did not think we could under the
circumstanees.
vv uuki you huh mane mo Harm* n**
ply if you were told that the Frank
furt was 20 miles nearer to you than
the Carpathla?”
Bride replied that the Carpalhia was
then on its way with its iifeboats
ready.
Cottam, the Carpathla wireless op
erator, was recalled and asked if he
heard anything from the Frankfurt at
tills time. He said he had not.
Mr. Marconi again testified to the
distress signals and said that the
Frankfuit was equipped with Marconi
wireless. He said that the receipt of
ihe signal C. Q. D. by the Frankfurts
operator should have been all sufficient
to send the Frankfurt to the immedi
ate rescue.
I’nder questioning by Senator Smith,
Bride said that undoubtedly tlie
Frankfurt received all of the urgent
appeals for help sent subsequently to
the Carpathia.
‘‘Why did you not send the messages
to the Frankfuit as well as to the Car
pathia? asked Senator Smith.
I suppose so, sir, but he would not
have understood.
“Is there uny code word for ‘fool
asked Senator Sntltli. Wouldnt it have
been as easy to send news of your actual
condition?”
The witness made no answer. He said
that before leaving the cabin, 10 minutes
before the ship went down, Phillips sent
out a final y. I). There was no re
sponse, Bride saying the spark was then
so weak that it probably did not carry.
When Bride and Phillips stepped out
oil the boat deck, he said, they found
persons rushing around in confusion.
They were seeking lifebelts.
“There were no big lifeboats aboard at
that time,” said Bride. “There was a
liferaft over the officers quarters, which
later was lost over the side.
The witness then told of his experience
in following with a small boat, beneath
which lie nearly was drowned before he
could extricate himself. With a num
ber of other survivors he clambered on
the overturned boat.
One of these was Phillips,” said the
witness. “He died on the way to the
Carpathla and was burled later at sib.”
Bride described in detail tin- launching
of the boat on which eventually he was
saved. The men were trying lo launch
the boat when it was w reached off and
washed away. When Bride finally man
aged to gain the bottom of the boat he
found between 25 and 40 men already
theie.
I was the last man invited aboard,
said Bride.
Did any others seek to get on?
Yes, sir, dozens. We couldnt take
them.
The witness said he did not see .1.
Hi uce Ismay, and that the last he saw
of Capt. Smith he was in the act of
jumping from the bridge, just as the ship
went down. He said he was swimming
within 150 feet of the ship when it went
down, und that lie felt no suction.
The committee, on excusing the wit*
ness, then took a recess.
Long before the hearing was resumed
in the afternoon crowds besieged the
rooms, but few who hud not been sought
by the committee were admitted. C. P.
Neil, commissioner of labor of the de
partment of commerce and labor, and
Congressmen Levy and Livingston of
New York were among the visitors.
Senators Smith and Newlands con
ferred after luncheon for more than an
hour, and it was exactly 4 oclock when
they reached the committee room.
Is Mr. Bride, the operator of the Ti
tanic, here? Senator Smith asked of Mr.
Marconi and Mr. Sammis of the Marconi
Co. They told him that Mr. Bride had
been sent to a physician, but could be
brought back later. The senator said he
wunted to ask the operator several addi
tional questions, but could postpone it
until later on.
The second officer of the Titanic,
Charles H. Lightholder, was then sent
for by Senator Smith, but he was not
I present, and the third officer of the Ti
tanic Herbert John Pittman, was called
to the stand.
“Do you know of your own knowledge
whether the Titanics ship log was pre
served or taken from the Titanic?” asked
Senator Smith.
“1 do not.”
As soon as Pittman had answered, Sen
ator Smith rose in his place and an
nounced the close of the hearing in New
York and that all the witnesses had
been summoned to appear in Washing
ton, the inquiry to be resumed there at
l0.,!0 Monday morning.
•After a conference with my col
leagues on the committee,” said Sen
ator Smith, we have concluded to
subpoena Jlr. J. Bruce Ismay, P. A. S.
Franklin, Harold Bride, the operator
of the Titanic; H. T. Cottam, operator
of the Carpathia: C. H. Lightoller. sec
ond officer of the Titanic; H. J. Pitt
man. third officer: J. G. Boxhall, fourth
officer, and H. G. Lowe. fifth officer
of the Titanic.
W* have also subpoenaed Mr. Per
kins E. Archer, W. H. Taylor, W.
Bryce, E. Bully, S. Henning, F. O.
Evans, T. Jones, Frederick Bay, l.
Crow. o. Andrews. J. Wiggery. H.
Eteherm. G. W. Howe, John Collins. A.
J. Bright, G. Simmonse, Frank Os
man, G. Moore, A. Cunningham, A.
Oliver. F. Fleet, G. A. Hoag. A. Craw
ford, W. Burke, E. Whelton. F. Clench.
J. Hardy and Albert Haines of the Ti
tanic’s crew.
All of these witnesses have been
summoned to appear in Washington,
next Monday, where the inquiry will
be resumed at 10.30 oclock in the
morning.
J. Bruce Ismay declined to accede
to a request for permission to his men
to relate the narrative of the last dra
matic movements before the Titanic
sank, on the ground that they had
not yet given their evidence
Senator Smith after the hearing ad
toumed made a statement to the press
In which he explained the course the
commute* had pursued during the in
quiry at New York, and touched on
the immediate steps to be taken at
the Washington hearing which will
b-gin. Monday. He said:
The object of the committee in com
ing to New York coincidental with tin
arrival of the Carpathia was prompted
by the desire to avail itself of first
hand information from the active par
ticipants in tills sad affair, ur course
has been guided solely by this pur
pose—to obtain accurate information
without delay.
“We were told that some of the officers
of the Titanic were British subjects and
resided in England, desired and Intended
to return to their homes immediate!
upon arrival at this port. We concluded
that It would he most unfortunate if w
were to be deprived of their testimony
for any indefinite period, and their re
moval beyond the jurisdiction of our au
thority might complicate and possibly
defeat our purpose
We went directly to tile Carpathia
upon her urrival: were received court
ously by the captain and officers of the
ship; were accorded a prompt interview
with the managing director and vice
president of the White Star Line. We
satisfied ourselves that their promise to
appear insured their presence at the
hearing and have not been called upon
to use more drastic means to accomplish
this result.
Mr. I am ay intended to return to Eng
land forthwith, but at our request lia
remained here, as have the other offi
cers and members of the crew.
It was found necessary to take the
testimony of the captain of the Carpa
thia Immediately that he might not or
further Inconvenienced In his departuic
with ills ship after his most creditable
conduct, worthy of the highest praise. j
We felt that it would not be an evidence
of our appreciation to detain him and
his ship and passengers after he had
brought the survivors of the Titanic vol
untarily to this port.
We examined the second officer be
cause he was tu command during the
hours immediately preceding the collision
and we thought it wise to take his tes
timony Immediately. Mr. Bride, the wire
less telegrapher on the Titanic, who sur
vived. had been Injured und was unable
to be conveniently moved from New
York.
 Ids testimony and the testimony
of the. wireless operator of the Carpu
thia were so intimately related, we con
cluded to take the testimony of both
forthwith, and in order that we might
beyond peradventure have the statement
of Mr. tsmay formally on record, we de
cided to take his testimony immediately.
All were notilied of the fact that we had
not finished with them and they were re
1 quested to remain.
After conferring with odr associates
we concluded to exercise our authority
and formally subpoena these officers, to
gether with about 20 men of the ship’s
crew, and take the further testimony at
least for the lime being at Washing
1 ton, where the entire sub-committee could
I be present.
I “In summoning the surviving passen
gers, many of whom were distressed,
some quite ill and others injured, we
have thought it wise to proceed with
care and consideration for their physi
cal and mental condition. Many of them
have already been subpoenaed, but re
turns have not yet been made and I am
unable to give a list of those subpoenaed
to the press,
“I want to acknowledge our debt of
gratitude to the representatives of the
press for their marked consideration and
courtesy and to assure them thut every
thing that has transpired has been en
tirely In their presence and sthat this
course will be pursued so fur as I am
concerned in the future hearings before
the committee.
A cargo of 40,000 Chilian oak ties was
recently shipped from Corral to South
Africa, to the order of a l-cndon syn
dioate. if they prove satisfactory the
syndicate is tit lake 500,000 mitre.
ISMAY’S STATEMENT.
(Continued from Page One.)
Line would receive an additional sum
liy way of bonus or otherwise for at
taining a certain speed is absolutely
untrue. The White Star Line receives
from the British government a fixed
compensation of 770.000 pounds per
annum for carrying the mails, with
out regard to the speed of any of its
vessels, and no additional sum is paid
on account of any increase in Sliced.
1 was never consulted by Capl.
Smith nor by any other person nor did
1 ever make any suggestions whatso
ever to any human being about the
course of the ship. The Titanic, as 1
am informed, was on the southern
most westbound track of trans-Atlan
tic steamers. The tracks, or lanes,
were designated many years ago by
I agreement of all the important steam
ship lines and all captains of the White
I Star Line are required to navigate
their vessels as closely as possible oi.
these tracks, subject to the following
standing instructions:
Commanders must distinctly un
derstand that the issue of these regu
lations does not in any way relieve
them from responsibility for the safe
and effieient navigation of their re
spective vessels, and they are also en
joined to remember that they must
run no risk which might by any pos
sible result in accident to their shins.
It is to lie hoped that they will ever
bear in mind that the safety of tho
lives and property entrusted to their
Care is the ruling principle that should
govern them in the navigation of their
vessels, and that no supposed gain in
expedition or saving of time on the
voyage is to be purchased at the risk
of accident. The company desires to
maintain for its vessels a reputation
for safety and only looks for such
speed on the various voyages as is
consistent with safe and prudent navi
gation.
Commanders are reminded that
the steamers are to a great extent un
insured and that their own livelihood
as well as the companys success, de
pends upon immunity from accident,
no precautions which ensure safe navi
gation is to he considered excessive.
The only information I ever receiv
ed on the ship that other vessels had
sighted ice was by a wireless message
received from the Baltic, which I have
already testified to. This was handed
to me by Cpt. Smith without any re
mark as he was passing me on the
passenger deck on the afternoon of
Sunday. April 14. I reud the telegram
casually and put it in my pocket. At
about 10 minutes past seven, while
I was sitting in the smoke room,
Capt. Smith came in and asked me to
give him the message received from
the Baltic in order to post it for the
information of the officers. I handed
it to him and nothing lurther was said
by either of us. I did not speak to any
of the officers on the subject. If the
information I received had aroused
any misapprehension in my mind—
which it did not—X should not have
made my suggestion to a commander
of rapt. Smith’s experience. The re
sponsibility for the navigation of the
ship rested solely with him.
It has been stated that Capt. Smith
and I were having a dinner party in
one of the saloons from 7.H0 to 10.30.
I Sunday night, and that at the time of
the collision Capt. Smith was sitting
with me in the saloon.
Both of these statements are abso
lutely false. I did not dine with th-»
captain nor did I «ee him during th
pvening of April 14. The doctor din
on with me in me renn.aura.ni. ai
anil I went directly to my stateroom
and went to bed about 10.30. I wa
asleep when the collision occurred. I
felt a jar, went out Into the passage
way without dressing, met a steward,
asked him what was the matter an 1
he said lie did not know. I returned n
my room. I felt the ship slow dow i.
put on an overcoat over my pajamai
and went up on the bridge deck and
on the bridge.
I asked Capt. Smith what was the
matter and lie said we had struck ice.
I asked him whether he thought it
serious and -lie said he did. On re
turning to my room I met the chief
engineer and asked him whether ho
thought the damage serious and he
said lie thought it was.
I then returned to my room and
put on a suit of clothes. I had been
in my overcoat and pajamas up to
this time. I then went back to thu
boat deck and heard Capt. Smith giv
the order to clear the boats. I help I
in this work for nearly two hours as
far as 1 can judge. I worked at the
starboard boats, helping women an i
children into the boats and lowering
them over the side. I did nothing with
regard to the boats on the port side.
“Hy that time every wooden life
boat on the starboard side had been
lowered away and I found that they
were engaged in getting out the for
waid collapsible boat on the starboard
side. 1 assisted in tilts work and all
the women that were on this deck
were helped into the boat. They were
till, 1 think, third class passengers.
As the boat was going over the side,
Mr. Carter a passenger, and myself
got in. At that time there was not a
woman on the boat deck, nor any
passenger of any class, so far as we
could see or hear. The boat had be
tween 3.i ami 40 in it, 1 should think,
most of them women. There were
perhaps four or five men, and it was
afterwards discovered that there were
four Chinamen concealed under the
tnwarts in the bottom of the boat.
“The distance that the boat had to bo
lowered into the water I should estimate
about 20 feet. Mr. Carter and I did not
get Into the boat until they had begun
to lower it away. When the boat reached
the water I helped row it, pushing the
oar from me as 1 sat. This is the expla
nation of the fact that my back was to
the sinking steamer.
“The boat would have accommodated
certainly six or more passengers In addi
tion, if there hud been anyone on the
boat deck to go. These facts can be sub
stantiated by Mr. W. E. Carter of Phil
adelphia. who got In at the time that I
1 did and was rowing the boat with me I
j hope I need not say that neither Mr. Car
ter nor myself would for one moment
have thought of getting into the boat if
there had been any women there to go
in it. nor should I have done so If I
bad thought that by remaining on the
ship I could have been of the slightest
further assistance.
I it is impossible for me to answer every
false statement, rumor or invention that]
has appeared in the newspapers. I am
prepared to answer any questions that
may be asked by the committee of the
Senate or,any other responsible peri-on. I
I shall, therefore, make no further
statement of this kind except to explain
the messages that I sent from the Car
pathian’
These messages have been com
pletely misunderstood. An inference
has been drawn from them that I
was anxious to avoid the Senate com
mittees inquiry which it was intended
to hold in New York. As a matter of
fact, when dispatching these messages
I hadn’t the slightest idea that any
inquiry was contemplated and 1 hail
no information regarding it until the
arrival of the Carpathia at the Cunard
dock in New York, Thursday night,
when 1 was informed by Senators
Smith and Newlands of the appoint
ment of tlie special committee to hold
the inquiry. The only purpose in send
ing these messages was to express my
desire to have the crew returned to
their homes in England for their own
benefit at the earliest possible moment,
and I also was naturally anxious to
return to my family, but left the mat
ter of my return entirely to our rep
resentative in New York.
I deeply regret that I am compelled
to make any personal statement when
my whole thought is on the horror
of the disaster. In building the Titanic
it was the hope of my associates and
myself that we had built a vessel
w hich could not be destroyed by the
perils of the sea or the dangers of
navigation. The event has proven the
futility of that hope. The present le
gal requirements have proved inade
quate. They must be changed, but
whether they are changed or not this
awful experience has taught the
steamship owners of the world that
too much reliance has been placed on
water-tight compartments and on
wireless telegraphy and that they
must equip every vessel with lifeboats
and rafts sufficient to provide for
every soul on board and sufficient men
to handle them.”
DENIES FALSE REPORT.
Says He Didn’t Send Wireless of Vir
ginian Towing Titanic.
London. April 21.—Capt. Haddock of
the White Star Line steamship Olym
pic, on arriving at Plymouth, yester
day morning, from New York, denied
the Olympic sent out a wireless report
to the effect that the Allan Liner Vir
ginian was towing the Titanic and
that all of the latters passengers were
safe.
The passengers of the Olympic,
which is a sister ship of the ill-fated
Titanic, subscribed $7000 to the relief
fund for the survivors.
The story that X sent the report
about the Virginian towing the. Ti
tanic,” Capt. Haddock said, is a Ila
grant invention. So soon as I heard of
the disaster from the Carpathia 1 dis
patched the news by wireless to New
York informing the White Star offi
cials of the number of persons saved
and of the foundering of the Titan
ic. That was on Monday afternoon.”
After hurrying hundreds of miles to
the rescue, the Olympic learned tier
race had been in vain. T^.e Carpathia
announced that she had the survivors
aboard and that the Titanic had disap
peared. Gloom settled over the Olym
pic and all amusements were aban
doned.
A special dispatch received from
Cherbourg says that while the Olym
pic was in the harbor of Plymouth,
Saturday morning, the crew was sup
porting a proposal to refuse to em
bark when the vessel sails for New
York, next Wednesday, on the ground
that the steamer was insufficiently
provided with lifesaving apparatus.
ISMAY SENT MESSAGES.
Wanted Survivors of Titanic’s Crew
Put on the Cedric.
New York, April 21.—The attention
of J. Bruce Ismay was called to three
published telegrams signed "Yamsi,"
in which the White Star Line was
asked to hold the Cedric until the
arrival of the Carpathia, so that the
surviving members of the crew of the
Titanic could be taken back to Eng
land.
He was asked if the published tele
grams were genuine, and if. when he
sent them, it was his intention to go
baek immediately upon the Cedric.
Mr. Ismay said:
‘Although I haven’t had time to
compare the published telegrams with
those I sent, I can say that I did send
telegrams for the purpose of expedit
ing the return of the Titanic’s crew
to England. Most of the crew have
relatives on the other side and were
anxious to get home after their har
rowing experience.
I was afraid if they staid ashore
for a week they might he induced to
spend their money unnecessarily, and
I knew it would be mueli better for
them to go back soon than to be
knocking about town. There was cer
tainly no desire on my part to shut
off a full investigation. 1 knew that
the surviving officers would be com
petent to give full information of the
disaster.
•I, myself, wished to go back its
soon as convenient, although I would
not think of going back as long as t
could lie of the slightest use to the
government in its investigation.
“It will be noted that even in flu
published telegrams and of others
that may be brought out before the
Investigation, that I advised the send
ing of the crew back only ‘If desir
able.’ By .‘if desirable’ I meant that
unless there were any good reason to
the contrary.”
BOSTON MEMORIAL SERVICES.
Many Sermons Bear Words of Tribute
to Titanic’s Dead.
Boston, April 21.—Attendance in
many of the Greater Boston churches
was urusually large, today, on ac
count of memorial services for the
victims of the Titanic disaster. Al
most every point of view was reached
in the sermons of the pastors among
the more striking eastnents being the
following:
Rev. A. Z. Conrad, Park street
church Had the Titanic arrived at the
time expected or before she would have
been geeted with the applause of na
tions. The Titanic was a sacritive to
the public clamor for swiftness at the
coast of safety.”
Rev. Alexander Mann. Trinity
church; It was a light from the Cross
that guided those brave men and there
is nothing like it nor nothing possible
except through the spirit of Jesus
Christ.”
Rev. Herbert S. Johnson, Warren
Avenue Baptist church, The man who
could turn aside his millions and give
jhis life in the attempt to save the pas
I sppgers of the steerage is worthy of
our respect and admiration. Col. Astor
died like a gentleman.”
Rev. G. Wolcott Brooks, Village
church, Dorchester, The officers ami
passengers who sank on the Ill-fated
ship lifted in their dying hands the
whole race.
DWELLS ON AWFUL TRAGEDY.
Mrs. John J. Astor Suffering Keenly
from Shock and Grief.
New York, April 21.—Doctors Ft. if.
Kimball and Herman Biggs, who were
in consultation, today, over the condi
tion of Mrs. Astor, widow of Col. John
Jacob Astor. agreed, tonight, that no
serious development was noted or ex
pected. Mrs. Astor remained abed,
still suffering from the shock of her
experiences in escaping from the sink
ing Titanic and particularly grief over
the loss of her husband. Vincent Astor
and a few Intimate friends isited with
her during the day. Notwithstanding
their efforts to keep her from thinking
or talking too much of the harrowing
experiences, she related over and over
again how she took leave of her hus
band without full realization that he
was going down to his death; of how
the lifeboat she was in was almost un
der the stern of the Titanic when she
sank, and of how she and other wo
men were obliged to bail out the boat
to keep it afloat.
NO SIGN OF BODIES.
Captain of Laurentic Dashes Hopes of
Titanic Survivors.
Halifax. N. S„ April 21.—In a wire
less message, early Saturday, Capt.
Mathias of the Laurentic reported that
he had kept a careful lookout while
passing over the Grand Banks and had
seen neither bodies nor wreckage. The
Laurentic came over practically the
same track as the Titanic.
Investigation,Today,
At Washington,
Washington. April 21.—The federal
investigation of the sinking of the Ti
tanic will be continued here, tomorrow,
at the capital.
J. Bruce Ismay, managing director
of the White Star Line, P. A. S. Frank
lin. vice president, and 37 members of
the lost liners crew arrived here, to
night, to continue testimony before the
Senate sub-committee of which Sen
ator William A Idea Smith of Michigan
is chairman.
Mr. Ismay denied, tonight, that he
made any protest to the British am
bassador, Mr. Bryce, because members
of the Titanic’s crew were held as
witnesses and added that he caine to
Washington to co-operate with the in
vestigating committee in any way he
could. He added he did not talk with
Huntington Wilson, the acting secre
tary of state, about the question. The
hearings will go on, tomorrow morn
ing, at 10.30 o’clock.
Assurances of the co-oieratloh of
the French government with the Unit
ed States further to safeguard human
life at sea were given, today, by Am
bassador Jusserand to Senator Smith.
Ignoring the formalities of proceeding
through the state department. Am
bassador Jusserand called in person
upon the chairman. The visit of the
ambassador attracted much attention.
Ambassador Jusserand told the
Michigan -senator that he called to ex
press his gratification at what had
been accomplished by the investiga
tion and to make plain the desire of
the French government to co-operate
in improving conditions at sea. The
ambassador asked for any suggestions
looking toward an immediate improve
ment in the protection of passengers.
Two suggestions were made by Sen
ator Smith. The first was that every
ship be not only equipped with wire
less, hut that every ship should have
two operators, one constantly on duty.
The other suggestion was that there
be additional life equipment on board
ocean liners, including lifeboat accom
modations for every passenger.
Mr. Smith said, today, that no notice
or intimation either from officials or
from members of the crew of oojectlon
to the committee’s course had reached
him.
I am proceeding on the theory that
what we obtain will be as valuable to
them as to us,” he said.
Major Arthur Peuchen of Toronto, Can
ada, lias notified Senator Smith that he
will be in Washington, tomorrow, to put
bis story into the record.
Lewis Klein, a Hungarian member of
the Titanic crew, has been subpoenaed
at Cleveland, Ohio. He will appear be
fore the committee to verify an account
he gave in that city of his experiences
in the wreck. One feature of the forth
coming hearing will be the inquiry into
the wireless communication as the Titan
ic was sinking. An effort will be made
to ascertain the exact position of the
Herman steamer Frankfurt, which re
sponded to the Titanics signals of dis
tress but, it is alleged, did not offer any
aid. It is desired to ascertain if the
Frankfurt was actually nearer to the
sinking ship than the Carpathia, as Oper
ator Bride estimated the Frankfurt to
have been, judging from the strength of
the electric spark in the wireless com
munication. Whether the Frankfurts
operator will be called as a witness could
not be learned, tonight.
Secretary Meyer of the navy depart
ment called on members of the depart-,
rnent, today, and told them that the wire
less operator of the Chester, who en
deavored to get details of the disaster
from the Carpathia on the latter’s way
to New York from the wreck, would be
held subject to the committees order.
The chairman of the commerce commit
tee expects to have published, tomorrow,
a translation of Norwegian navigation
laws which will be considered in framing
its recommendations to the navy.
If any such laws as the strict Norse
requirements had been in force in Great
Britain,” said Senator Nelton, today,
“there would have been no such disaster
as that in which the large number of
people went to their graves. They pro
vide that lifeboats and other life saving
apparatus shall be sufficient to take care
of every passenger and member of the
crew. There the life saving apparatus
is based upon the number of passengers
while here and in Great Britain it Is
based upon tonnage.”
BODIES RECOVERED.
(Continued from Page One.)
bottom, was sung in all the churches
of the city. There were prayers from
the pulpits for the survivors and the
relatives and friends of the dead,
while in Catholic churches requiem
masses were sung for the repose of
AUGUSTA LOCALS
The Womans Board will moot, at
2 oclock, Monday afternoon, with
Mrs. Herbert M. Heath, State street.
Mrs. Alonzo Gilley.
Carrie A., wife of Alonzo Gilley, died
suddenly from heart trouble, Saturday
morning, at her home at No. 12!* Ban
gor street. The funeral was held, at
2.30, Sunday afternoon. Rev. W. I’.
1. Kingston officiating. The bearers
were Josiah Ellis, Amos Berry, John
T. Fowler and Prescott Wood. The
interment was In the family lot at
Riverside cemetery.
the souls of those who sank with itie
Titanic.
At Trinity church the Rev. Lr. Wil
liam T. Manning, the rector, said:
‘‘At the present time, there is sad
ness and sorrow in many homes
throughout the world, but there are
things apparent which are a comfort
to everyone. We may give thanks lor
the heroes, the calmness and the cour
ageousness on that ship in the last few
horrible minutes.”
He eulogized the devotion of the wo
men passengers who remained with
their husbands, "Even unto death” and
continued:
"There must be a joy in our hearts:
that these men and women, when they
meet the supreme test, faced It in sucli a
manner Their example on board that
sinking ship has made the world rltfher,
lias given this generation a greater herit
age to leave to those generations to
come. We can pay our reverent devotion
to those brave men and women who dlert
in the sinking of the steamer Titanic."
Special services for the survivors of the
Titanic wreck. Dr. Manning, announced,
will be held in Trinity church, Tuesday
morning. In Catholic churches and at
St. Patrick’s cathedral announcements
were made that Cardinal Farley lias di
rected that memorial services lie held in
all churches of the arch diocese, tomor
row morning.
At St. Patrick's, today, Cardlnul Farley
presided at the mass, and the Right Rev.
P. J. Hays offered the pjayer of the
church for the repose of the souls of the
Titanic's dead.
‘‘It is hardly necessary," lie said, “to
call upon Catholics to remember in their
private prayers those who lost their lives
in the disaster."
Hundreds from the Russian colony of
New York attended the services at the
Church of the Holy Virgin Mary on the
East Side, where requiem mass was cele
brated by the Rev. Peter Poreff. In his
sermon tho pastor referred to the large
number of subjects of Emperor Nicholas
who had lost their lives in the disaster.
At tho French Catholic church of St.
Vincent de Paul, in West 23d street.
Father Septier conducted two masses
and prayers were said for the repose of
the souls of those who lost their lives.
At the Free Synagogue at Carnegie
hall Rabbi Emil G. Hirsch of Chicago
lauded the heroism of the Jews who lost
their lives In the disaster.
‘‘It will be a long time,” he added, “be
fore the world will forget the quiet and
manly heroism of Isador Straus and the
wifely devotion of Mrs. Straus, who re
fused to be saved without him."
THE VIRGINIAN AT LIVERPOOL.
Passes Place Where Titanic Sank, But
Finds No Wreckage.
Liverpool, April ill.—The Allan Line
steamer Virginian arrived here, to
day. Capt. Gambell was unable to
throw any light on the messages
which were sent broadcast, last Mon
day, that the Virginian had the Ti
tanic in tow and that other steamers
were standing by.
The Virginian had two wireless op
erators on hoard, who transmitted on
ward all news received. "We passed
the place where the Titanic sank.”
said Capt. Gambell. "at a distance of
six or seven miles. I had to go around
an ice held. The ice was close packed
between us and the position of the
Titanic when she went down, and
there would have been great danger
in going near. No boats, packages or
wreckage were to be seen.”
The Virginian received the first
wireless message concerning the ac
cident to the Titanic front Cape Race,
at 12.40 o’clock, Monday morning. It
announced that the Titanic had struck
an iceberg and K was in need of im
mediate assistance. Capt. Gambell al
tered his course and proceeded 160
miles in the direction of the Titanic,
at 10 o’clock in the morning, he re
ceived a wireless from the Carpa
thla:
"Turn hack. Everything O. 1C. Have
son <>n board. Return to your northern
track.”
The Virginian then proceeded east
ward and sighted a.Held of ice and nu
merous bergs. Previous to this, she
was in communication wtili the Rus
sian steamer Rirma, which, at 3.45 A.
M., was 65 miles from the Titanic and
also with the Californian, Carpathia,
rankfurt and Baltic.
"At .'i.le P. M continued the cap
tain. "I was in communication with
the Californian. Siie was IT miles north
of the Titanic and had not heard any
thing of the disaster. At 6.10 I sent a
Marconlagram: 'Kindly let me know
the condition of affairs when you get
to the Titanic.’ He immediately, re
plied
fan now sec the I Tirpathiu taking
passengers aboard from small boats.
The Titanic foundered about 2 A. M.’”
The Virginian heard the Carpathia
advising the Kaltiy that she had about
son aboard and was proceeding for
Halifax or New York, and advising
tiie dympic that all the boats had been
accounted for: that a careful search
had been made among the wreckage
for survivors and that tiie Californian
was going to remain in the vicinity
for some time.
When tlie Virginian was hastening
to the Titanic, all her boat3 were
swung out ready for use. A party of
bluejackets returning from the Pacific
station under Lieut. 3. S. Morrell, vol
unteered to man the boats.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
